We put a lot of pressure on people today
我们今天给人们施加了很大的压力。
that as soon as they start working, they
他们一旦开始工作，他们
need to get onto that property ladder.
我需要买房置业。
But there's ways to build wealth that
但积累财富的方法有很多种，
don't require you to be in the real
不需要你身处现实
estate game, including three numbers
地产游戏，包括三个数字
that everyone should know when it comes
每个人都应该知道这一点
to their personal finance 65 20. Just
就他们的个人财务而言，65 20。仅
knowing that creates a better life for
知道这能创造更美好的生活
yourself.
你自己。
&gt;&gt; Nisha Shaw is the former high-profile
妮莎·肖是前知名人士
investment banker turned financial
从投资银行家转型为金融从业者
mentor
导师
&gt;&gt; whose content has helped millions
其内容已帮助数百万人
rethink their relationship with money,
重新思考他们与金钱的关系，
&gt;&gt; break free from crippling debt,
摆脱沉重的债务，
&gt;&gt; and take the first steps toward building
并迈出建设的第一步
lasting wealth. Everything is trying to
持久财富。一切都在试图
pull you away from your money. Cost of
让你远离金钱。成本
living going up, prices going up,
生活水平提高，物价上涨
fighting against marketing to keep your
对抗营销，以保持你的
money in your pocket.
口袋里的钱。
&gt;&gt; You earned this.
这是你应得的。
&gt;&gt; So, it's becoming harder and harder. And
所以，这变得越来越难了。和
I've gone through this. I followed
我经历过这些。我跟随
society's version of money until I
社会对金钱的定义，直到我
realized that if I continue living this
我意识到，如果我继续这样生活下去……
way, the freedom, the choice, the
方式、自由、选择、
options that I want aren't going to
我想要的那些选项都无法实现。
exist.
存在。
Um, hold on, give me a second.
嗯，稍等一下，给我一秒钟。
And I felt really trapped at times, but
我有时感觉自己真的被困住了，但是
I don't know how to escape. And I know a
我不知道该如何逃脱。我知道一个
lot of people are probably hearing this
很多人可能都听到了这句话。
and thinking I'm also in that place. And
我觉得自己也身处那种境地。和
so I really feel like my purpose is to
所以我觉得我的使命是……
help as many people to go from feeling
帮助尽可能多的人摆脱这种感觉
trapped to freeing themselves and using
被困于挣脱束缚和利用
money to do that.
有足够的钱来做这件事。
Wasn't expecting that.
没想到会这样。
Okay. So people are hungry for easy
好的。所以人们渴望轻松。
money tips and these stay the same
理财小贴士，这些始终不变。
regardless of how much you earn. So we
无论你收入多少。所以，我们
could talk about the peace of mind fund
可以谈谈安心基金
and doing that puts you ahead of 59% of
这样做可以让你领先于 59% 的人。
Americans. Then there's building your
美国人。然后就是构建你的
emergency buffer and this does more for
应急缓冲，而且这还有更多作用
your emotional well-being than earning
你的情绪健康比收入更重要
over 200k. But with the way cost of
超过20万。但成本却如此之高
living is going, you cannot save your
生命正在消逝，你无法挽救你的
way to retirement. So this is when you
通往退休之路。所以，这就是你
want to move on to investing. That is
想转行投资。那是
the easiest way to make money. And my
最简单的赚钱方法。而我的
principle with investing is very very
投资原则非常非常重要
simple and it's just
很简单，就这么简单
&gt;&gt; listen to my regular listeners, I know
听听我的老听众怎么说，我知道
you don't like it when I ask you to
你不喜欢我问你这个问题
subscribe at the start of these
在这些内容开始时订阅
conversations. I don't like saying I
对话。我不喜欢说我
don't like it being in there. None of us
我不喜欢它放在那里。我们当中没有人
like it. It's frustrating. Do you know
喜欢。真令人沮丧。你知道吗
what's also frustrating? It's also
还有什么令人沮丧的？它还是
frustrating when I go into the back end
进入后台时令人沮丧
of a YouTube channel and I see that 56%
我看到一个 YouTube 频道，其中 56%
of you that listen frequently to this
经常收听这段音频的你们
podcast haven't yet subscribed. And so
我还没有订阅播客。所以
many of you don't even know that you
你们很多人甚至都不知道……
haven't subscribed because I see in the
我还没订阅，因为我在……中看到
comment section you say to me, you go,
评论区里有人跟我说，你就走了。
"I didn't even realize I didn't
我甚至都没意识到我没有
subscribe." And that actually fuels the
订阅。”而这实际上促进了
show. It's basically like you're making
展示。这基本上就像你在制作
a donation to the show. So that's why I
向节目组捐款。所以这就是我的原因
ask all the time because it enables us
经常问，因为这能让我们……
to build and build and build and build
建造，建造，建造，建造
and we're going for the long term here.
我们着眼的是长远发展。
So all I'd ask you is if you've seen the
所以我只想问你，你是否看过
show before and you like it, help me
之前展示过，如果你喜欢，请帮帮我
help my team here. Hit the subscribe
请帮帮我的团队。点击订阅
button and we'll continue to build this
按钮，我们将继续构建这个
show for you. That's my promise. Thank
为您呈现。这是我的承诺。感谢
you to all of you guys that do
向所有这样做的人致敬
subscribe. Means the world to me. Let's
订阅。对我意义重大。我们开始吧
get on with the show.
继续演出。
Misha Sha with your YouTube channel
Misha Sha 和你的 YouTube 频道
which has accumulated almost 2 million
已累计近200万
subscribers in a incredibly short period
在极短时间内获得大量订阅用户
of time. What is the goal? What is the
时间。目标是什么？什么是
mission that you're on? What is it
你正在执行什么任务？它是什么？
you're trying to do?
你想做什么？
Money touches almost every part of our
金钱几乎渗透到我们生活的方方面面。
life and impacts so many choices from
生活和影响如此多的选择
where we choose to live, uh what we
我们选择居住的地方，呃，我们
choose to do for a living, what our
选择以什么为生，我们做什么
weekends even look like. So my mission
周末看起来都像这样。所以我的使命
is really simple. It's take the
很简单。这是需要
complicated financial jargon and turn it
复杂的金融术语，并将其转化为……
into easy, practical, actionable money
转化为简单、实用、可操作的资金
tips that anyone can implement and
任何人都可以实施的技巧
understand.
理解。
&gt;&gt; And what kinds of people and what kinds
以及什么样的人和什么样的
of financial situations? Because
财务状况如何？因为
obviously we've got millionaires on one
显然，我们这里有很多百万富翁。
end and then we've got people like me at
最后，我们还有像我这样的人……
18 years old that are struggling to even
18岁的年轻人甚至连生活都难以维持。
get a couple of quid together to feed
凑点钱吃饭
myself.
我。
&gt;&gt; The principles of money stay the same
金钱的原则始终不变。
regardless of how much you earn. And
无论你收入多少。和
although my mission is to help make
虽然我的使命是帮助制造
money more accessible, the principles,
资金更容易获取，这些原则
the underlying thinking, the mindset can
潜在的思维方式，或者说心态，可以
be applied whether you're making 50,000,
无论你的年收入是5万美元还是其他任何收入，都适用。
500,000 or more.
50万或更多。
&gt;&gt; And we don't really learn about money.
我们并没有真正学习过关于金钱的知识。
&gt;&gt; We don't.
我们不。
&gt;&gt; We don't. Nobody in school was teaching
我们不。学校里没有人教书。
me about money. My parents didn't teach
我跟我谈钱。我父母没有教过我。
me about money growing up either. So
我从小对金钱也没什么兴趣。所以
someone like you who can simplify some
像你这样能简化一些事情的人
of these big complicated words or terms
这些复杂的大词或术语
or strategies I think is um is of the
或者策略我认为是嗯，是的
moment but also more needed now than
虽然现在比以往任何时候都更需要这样做。
ever because people are complaining
总是因为有人抱怨
about cost of living crises and prices
关于生活成本危机和价格
going up and inflation and all these
上涨、通货膨胀以及所有这些
kinds of things. Is that is that what
各种各样的东西。那就是……
you're seeing?
你看到了吗？
&gt;&gt; Absolutely. And at the same time, it's
绝对地。与此同时，它也是
becoming harder and harder to save our
拯救我们变得越来越难
hard-earned money
辛苦挣来的钱
&gt;&gt; because everything,
因为一切，
whether it's marketing, whether it's
无论是市场营销，还是
needs going up, everything is trying to
需要向上发展，一切都在努力。
pull you away from your money.
让你远离金钱。
&gt;&gt; And who are you?
你是谁？
&gt;&gt; I'm a qualified accountant. So I I
我是一名合格的会计师。所以，我
studied finance at university initially,
大学最初学习的是金融专业。
then I qualified as a chartered
然后我获得了特许会计师资格
accountant, and then I spent nine years
我先是当了会计，然后花了九年时间。
in banking. And do you do you think your
在银行业。你觉得你的
sort of psychological or emotional or I
某种心理或情感上的，或者我
don't know trauma response to money
不知道对金钱的创伤反应
plays a role in our relationship with
在我们与……的关系中发挥着作用
money?
钱？
&gt;&gt; Absolutely. We definitely all have our
绝对地。我们当然都有自己的
unique relationship with money. And a
与金钱有着独特的关系。以及
lot of it comes from our upbringing.
很多都源于我们的成长经历。
It's like an invisible backpack that we
它就像一个隐形的背包，我们
carry that we don't even realize that
我们甚至没有意识到这一点。
we're carrying it. And it could be fed
我们正在运送它。而且它可以被喂养
through us through what we've
通过我们，通过我们所拥有的
experienced firsthand or whether we've
亲身经历过，或者我们是否已经
just been on a a fly on a wall. Hearing
就像墙上的苍蝇一样，悄悄观察了一番。听力
a conversation between our parents
我们父母之间的对话
&gt;&gt; and what might feel invisible at the
以及那些可能感觉不到的东西
time has such a big impact on the way
时间对方式有着巨大的影响
you see money, how you use it, how you
你看重金钱，你如何使用它，以及你如何……
earn it, grow it, spend it, save it,
挣钱，赚钱，花钱，存钱
everything.
一切。
&gt;&gt; But that said, you can understand what
但即便如此，你也能理解……
to do to start making it and turning it
要开始制作并转动它
into your favor.
对你有利。
&gt;&gt; What was your relationship like with
你和对方的关系如何？
money when you went to university? I
你上大学时有钱吗？我
didn't understand what money meant to
不理解金钱的意义
me. So I followed society's version of
我。所以我遵循了社会所接受的……
money. So I bought all the things to
钱。所以我把所有东西都买了
make me look better. All the things to
让我看起来更好。所有的事情
make my lifestyle look better. And I did
让我的生活方式看起来更好。我确实这么做了。
that after graduating for years and
毕业多年后
years and years. That was the path that
年复一年。那是条路
I followed for a very long time until I
我跟随了很久，直到我
realized that if I continue living this
我意识到，如果我继续这样生活下去……
way and spending my money this way, the
以这种方式花钱，
freedom, the choice, the options I'm
自由、选择、各种可能性，我
have or that I want aren't going to
我想要的或拥有的都不会
exist.
存在。
&gt;&gt; Was there like a catalyst moment where
是否存在某种催化时刻？
you realized that or was it just an
你意识到这一点了吗？还是这只是……
accumulated feeling?
积压的感觉？
&gt;&gt; So for a long time I believed in this
所以很长一段时间以来，我都相信这一点。
blueprint. Go to school, get a job,
蓝图。上学，找工作，
climb the ladder and security will
爬上梯子，保安就会……
follow. And I did that to the tea for
跟随。我把那件事加到了茶里。
almost a decade,
近十年，
&gt;&gt; nine years in banking. And I'll say I
在银行业工作了九年。我会说我
was about halfway into my career where I
大约在我职业生涯的中期，我
was
曾是
we me I met this amazing woman. She was
我遇到了这位了不起的女士。她
basically my mentor. And we were working
基本上就是我的导师。我们当时正在工作
on multi-billion dollar transactions
在数十亿美元的交易中
late into the nights for weeks in a row
连续数周，每天工作到深夜。
at times. And we were in the middle of
有时。当时我们正处于……
one of the largest deals that we've
这是我们迄今为止最大的一笔交易。
done. And overnight she lost her job.
完毕。一夜之间，她失去了工作。
Overnight she was made redundant and the
一夜之间，她就被裁员了。
very next day I was asked to replace
第二天我就被要求替换
her.
她。
And I remember thinking at the time that
我记得当时我在想，
this person believed in financial
这个人信奉金融。
security. This person believed in the
安全。这个人相信
blueprint and it was taken from her. And
蓝图被人从她那里拿走了。和
now I'm in her shoes. What's to say that
现在我感同身受。谁又能说……
the same won't happen to me? And that
同样的事情不会发生在我身上吧？而那
was the first time I saw a crack in the
这是我第一次看到裂缝
system and I realized
系统，我意识到
if you give someone else the power to
如果你把权力交给别人
feed you, you're also giving them the
你喂饱自己，也喂饱了他们
power to starve you. And that's when I
有能力让你挨饿。就在那时，我
really understood, okay, I need to learn
明白了，好的，我需要学习
about money. I need to stop spending it
关于金钱。我需要停止花钱了。
in the way that I'm spending it. I need
以我目前的消费方式来看。我需要
to stop having this mindset around money
要摒弃这种金钱观念。
because what it's done right now is it's
因为它现在所做的就是……
kind of trapped me. So what I did is
感觉被困住了。所以我所做的就是
took it took the power back in my own
我夺回了主动权。
hands. did everything I needed to learn
手。我完成了所有需要学习的内容
how to save, spend, invest, budget. And
如何储蓄、消费、投资、制定预算。和
it came very easily to me because I was
对我来说很容易，因为我
in banking. That was it was financial
在银行业。那是财务方面的问题。
lingo and I could simplify it very very
行话，我可以把它简化得非常非常
easily for me. And that's really where
对我来说很容易。而这才是真正的原因。
my mindset or my change in thinking
我的心态或我的思维转变
around money changed. And that's the
货币体系发生了变化。就是这样。
same moment where I started my YouTube
就在我开始做YouTube的那一刻
channel.
渠道。
&gt;&gt; Oh, okay.
哦好的。
&gt;&gt; That was it.
事情就是这样。
&gt;&gt; Cuz a lot of people bury their heads in
因为很多人都把头埋在
the sand. I was looking at some stats
沙子。我当时在看一些统计数据。
earlier on that said the vast majority
前面提到过，绝大多数
of people just have this sort of
有些人就是有这种倾向。
avoidant relationship with their
与他们保持回避关系
financial situation, with financial
财务状况，以及财务状况
literacy, with their bills, with their
识字能力，以及他们的账单，以及他们的
bank statements. I mean, there's like
银行对账单。我的意思是，就像……
long-standing jokes from the internet
互联网上流传已久的笑话
that
那
&gt;&gt; people just don't open their banking
人们根本不开银行账户
apps. They just don't look at it.
应用程序。他们根本不看。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. There's there's even a
是的。是的。甚至还有
terminology for this and it's called the
这方面的术语是……
uh ostrich effect and it's a cognitive
鸵鸟效应，这是一种认知现象。
bias that explains people will avoid
这种偏见解释了人们为何会避免
looking at negative financial
着眼于负面财务状况
information because of the fear of how
因为害怕信息泄露而选择隐瞒
it makes them feel. It's the same reason
这让他们有所感触。原因相同。
why we don't check our bank account
为什么我们不查看银行账户
after a night out or we don't open
晚上外出后，我们不开门。
there's a a pile of bills on our table
我们桌子上堆着一摞账单。
and we don't check them.
我们不进行检查。
But it's that thing avoiding it thinking
但正是这种逃避的想法让我产生了这种想法。
that oh it's just going to disappear if
哦，它就会消失。
I don't look at it. It's that thing that
我没看。就是那件事
keeps you stuck. It's that thing that
让你陷入困境。就是那件事
makes you realize I don't even know
这让我意识到我甚至都不知道
which direction I'm going. It's a
我要往哪个方向走？这是一个
disorganized finances. Yeah.
财务状况混乱。是的。
&gt;&gt; So someone's listening to this right now
现在有人正在听这个
and they resonate with this idea of
他们与这种想法产生了共鸣。
they're slightly avoidant. They don't
他们有点回避型人格。他们不
really have a plan. and they're kind of
确实需要制定计划。他们有点像
just they get paid, they they they
他们只是拿工资而已，他们他们他们
answer their bills, and then they wait
他们回复账单，然后等待
till the next payday. They're not being
直到下一次发薪日。他们不是
intentional with their money. Is there a
他们会谨慎理财。是否有
step one in taking back control?
夺回控制权的第一步是什么？
&gt;&gt; The very first thing number one that I
我首先要说的第一件事就是……
would say to do is build a peace of mind
我会说，应该做的就是建立内心的平静。
fund.
基金。
&gt;&gt; A peace of mind fund.
安心基金。
&gt;&gt; This is not about maths. It's not the
这与数学无关。不是的
mathematically optimal thing to do, but
这是数学上最优的做法，但是
it is the psychological because as we've
这是心理因素，因为我们已经
discussed, money is as much about
讨论过，金钱同样重要。
emotions as is it as as it is about
情感，正如它与……有关
numbers.
数字。
So, what I'll say is go through the last
所以，我要说的是，请仔细阅读最后一部分。
30 days of your bank statements and
30天的银行对账单和
calculate exactly how much it costs for
精确计算一下需要多少钱
one month of your living. So, mortgage,
你一个月的生活费。所以，抵押贷款
rent, utilities, bills, minimum debt
房租、水电费、账单、最低债务
payments, car payments, whatever that
付款、车贷，诸如此类。
total is, that's the amount that you
总计就是你支付的金额。
want to saved up for your peace of mind
想攒钱让自己安心
fund.
基金。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So, I go through my last uh 30
好的。所以，我回顾了我最后的30个……
days of my bills. I find out that it's
账单堆积如山的日子。我发现是
cost me, let's say, $1,000.
大概花了我 1000 美元。
&gt;&gt; Okay. That's one month of your core
好的。那是你一个月的核心训练量。
living expenses.
生活费。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So, I need to save $1,000.
是的。所以，我需要攒下1000美元。
&gt;&gt; You don't need to invest it. You don't
你不需要投资。你没有
need to save it. You don't need to It's
需要保存它。你不需要这样做。
not for a holiday. The reason why you
不是为了度假。你的理由
want to save this is because when life
想保存这个是因为当生命
does what it does best, which is throw
它发挥了自己最擅长的作用，那就是投掷
curve balls, you want to make sure that
遇到突发情况，你需要确保……
you have it handled. If a boiler broke,
你已经处理好了。如果锅炉坏了，
breaks, your car dies on a Monday
车坏了，你的车周一抛锚了。
morning, the last thing you want on top
早上，最不想遇到的事就是这件事。
of the stress of dealing with that thing
处理那件事带来的压力
is the financial stress of how you're
你的财务压力来自于……
going to pay for it.
你会为此付出代价的。
&gt;&gt; That's what this thing covers. It tells
这就是它涵盖的内容。它讲述
you, I've got peace of mind. Whatever
有了你，我就能安心了。任何
life throws at me, I can handle it. And
生活带给我什么，我都能应付。和
saving that one month of living costs
节省一个月的生活费
puts you ahead of 59% of Americans and
这让你领先于59%的美国人，
30% of people living in the UK. 59% of
英国30%的人口。 59%
Americans unfortunately can't pay for a
美国人很不幸地付不起……
$1,000 expense.
1000美元的支出。
And 30% of people in the UK can't cover
英国有30%的人无法获得医疗保险。
one month of their living expenses if
一个月的生活费
something happened.
出事了。
&gt;&gt; What is what is step two in that regard?
那么，在这方面，第二步是什么？
&gt;&gt; Step two, this is where we do move into
第二步，我们进入下一阶段。
the mathematical optimal thing. This is
数学上的最优解。这是
you cut the financial bleeding.
你止住了经济上的损失。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; And what I mean by that is I get so so
我的意思是，我得到的只是如此
many times people ask me, Nisha, I have
很多人问我，妮莎，我有什么
4,000 5,000 sitting in my bank account.
我的银行账户里有4000到5000块钱。
What should I do with it? And my first
我该怎么处理它？我的第一个
question back to them is, do you have
反问他们的问题是，你们有
any high interest rate debt? Because if
是否有高利率债务？因为如果
you have savings of $2,000 earning 4%,
你目前有2000美元的存款，年利率为4%。
but you also have credit card debt at
但你还有信用卡债务
20%. You're leaking money more than
20%。你漏钱比别人多得多
you're making it. It's like pouring
你成功了。就像倾倒一样
water into a bucket with holes in it and
将水倒入一个有孔的桶中
wondering why it's not going to fill up.
纳闷为什么它不会注满水。
&gt;&gt; So, what you want to do is you want to
所以，你想做的就是你想……
take all of your debt that you have,
把你所有的债务都还清。
rank it from highest to lowest
按从高到低的顺序排列
&gt;&gt; in terms of interest,
就兴趣而言，
&gt;&gt; in terms of interest rate, and then
就利率而言，然后
everything above 8%. You you want to
高于 8% 的所有数值。你想
make minimum payments across everything
所有款项均需支付最低还款额
first. And then everything above 8%, you
第一的。然后，所有高于 8% 的部分，你
want to throw your extra savings into
想把你的额外积蓄投入到
the highest interest rate first, the
首先是利率最高的，
debt with the highest interest rate, and
利率最高的债务，以及
then move down in that order.
然后按这个顺序往下移动。
&gt;&gt; And interest rate, is that paid monthly
而利率，就是每月支付的利息。
or yearly?
还是每年一次？
&gt;&gt; It's paid monthly.
按月支付。
&gt;&gt; It's paid monthly. So, if I have a
按月支付。所以，如果我有一个
£1,000 loan on a credit card and the
通过信用卡贷款1000英镑，以及
interest rate is 10%. I'm paying
利率为10%。我付钱
&gt;&gt; £100
100英镑
&gt;&gt; paid monthly over the year they're going
他们按月支付，为期一年。
to pay 100. Okay.
付100。好的。
&gt;&gt; But that's split out into monthly
但这是按月计算的。
payments assuming that they're not
假设付款并非
drawing down more on that credit card.
继续刷那张信用卡。
&gt;&gt; And are you against credit cards?
你反对信用卡吗？
&gt;&gt; Credit cards are good if you're using
如果你经常使用信用卡，那信用卡就很好。
them the right way. Really good if
用正确的方式引导他们。如果真是太好了
you're using them in the right way. And
你使用它们的方式是正确的。和
that means the points that you're using,
这意味着你正在使用的积分，
the rewards that you get for it, the
你因此获得的奖励，
bonuses that you get from it, all really
你从中获得的奖励，真的
helpful. only if you're paying them off
有帮助。只有当你偿还他们的债务时才行。
in full every single month. If you're
每个月全额支付。如果你是
not using that or if you're not doing it
不使用那个或者你不做那个
in that way, which is kind of what they
从这个意义上讲，这大概就是他们的目的。
want you to do because they want you to
他们想让你这样做，因为他们想让你这样做。
miss these payments because that's how
错过这些付款是因为……
credit card companies make money by your
信用卡公司通过你的消费赚钱
missed payments. If you're not doing
逾期付款。如果你不这样做
that, then the benefits just don't weigh
那么，这些好处就显得微不足道了。
up.
向上。
&gt;&gt; Okay?
好的？
&gt;&gt; It doesn't make sense. Use credit cards,
这说不通。使用信用卡
but use it in a way that stacks up in
但要以一种能够累积效应的方式来使用它
your favor, not in the credit card
你的好意，而不是信用卡上的。
company's favor.
公司的青睐。
&gt;&gt; It's almost paradoxical that you'd use a
你会使用一个
credit card, but only if you can afford
信用卡，但前提是你负担得起。
to use a credit card.
使用信用卡。
Yeah, that's exact. Yeah, you got to you
没错，就是这样。是的，你明白了。
got to think about it. Can I can I pay
得好好想想。我可以付款吗？
for this thing outright in cash?
这东西可以全款现金买吗？
&gt;&gt; If I can, then I can ship put it on my
如果可以的话，我可以把它寄到我的……
credit card.
信用卡。
&gt;&gt; And that's the the anomaly is property.
这就是财产的异常之处。
If you're using it to make money,
如果你用它来赚钱，
healthare, education, but for anything
医疗保健、教育，但任何方面都是如此。
else, unless it's making you money,
否则，除非它能给你赚钱，
yeah, you that's the way you want to
是的，这就是你想要的方式。
think about it because it does encourage
仔细想想，因为它确实会给人带来鼓励。
extra spending otherwise.
否则会有额外的开支。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So, I'm going to pay off my high
好的。所以，我要还清我的高息贷款。
interest debts first with any spare cash
首先用剩余资金偿还利息债务
that I have.
我有的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; What's number three? Number three is
第三是什么？第三名是
build your emergency buffer.
建立应急储备金。
&gt;&gt; Okay,
好的，
&gt;&gt; so this this is your core living
所以，这就是你的核心生活
expenses that we've already calculated
我们已经计算出的费用
in step one. And you want to times that
第一步。你想达到那个时代
by three if you are single, you have um
如果你单身，到第三年你就有……
predictable income.
可预测的收入。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Or you want to times it by six if you
或者，如果你想把它乘以六，如果你
are head of household, you have a
作为户主，您有
mortgage, you have unpredictable income.
房贷，收入不稳定。
That's your emergency cushion and it
那是你的应急缓冲，而且
protects you from the bigger life
保护你免受更大生活的伤害
things. It's a very It's the third thing
事物。这是第三件事
you want to do. It's protects you if you
你想做什么。如果你
lose your job, if you have a health
如果你有健康问题，你可能会失去工作。
scare, if there are dependents that you
吓唬一下，如果你有需要赡养的人的话。
need to care for. This kind of buys you
需要照顾。这种买单方式
that time. But there's really
那段时间。但实际上并非如此。
interesting research from Vanguard that
Vanguard 的一项有趣研究
actually showed saving 3 to six months
实际上节省了 3 到 6 个月
of your living expenses
你的生活费用
does more for your emotional well-being
对你的情绪健康更有益
than earning over 200k.
比年收入超过20万还要多。
&gt;&gt; So, just the peace of mind again,
所以，我只是想寻求内心的平静。
&gt;&gt; it's that breathing room. Yeah. 3 to 6
正是这种喘息的空间。是的。 3至6
months of breathing room in your bank
你的银行将有几个月的喘息空间
account. It just moves the needle. It's
帐户。它只是起到了一定的作用。它是
the peace of mind. It's the security.
安心。是安全问题。
It's the stability.
关键在于稳定性。
One of the core human needs. And it's
人类的核心需求之一。而且是
interesting because we we're kind of
有趣的是，我们有点像
looking at making more money and earning
考虑如何赚更多钱和收入
more. And we're chasing the next number.
更多的。我们正在追逐下一个数字。
And actually, the thing that's going to
实际上，接下来要发生的事情是……
have the biggest impact or move the
影响最大或推动
needle on our financial well-being is
对我们财务健康的影响是
at this stage having that 3 to six
现阶段有3到6
months of living expenses saved up.
攒下了几个月的生活费。
&gt;&gt; It's all relative, right, at the end of
一切都是相对的，对吧，最终……
the day. So if and it's it's incredibly
那天。所以如果真是这样，那就太不可思议了。
stressful and I've been there when you
压力很大，我也有过同样的经历。
don't know if you can pay this month's
不知道你是否能支付这个月的款项。
rent if you don't know if you can feed
如果你不知道自己能否养活自己，那就先租房住吧。
yourself. Um but also the sort of un
你自己。嗯，但也有点……
back of the mind knowledge that if
潜意识里知道，如果
something were to happen you'd be
如果发生什么事，你就会……
screwed. It's incredibly stressful way
搞砸了。这是一种压力极大的方式
to live and you might not even realize
活着，你可能甚至都不会意识到
the stress consciously but you might
有意识地承受压力，但你可能会
just feel it. It might just be an angst
用心感受。这或许只是焦虑而已。
in your life.
在你的生活中。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And I I this applies at any income
是的。而且，这适用于任何收入水平。
level. Even people earning six figures
等级。即使是那些年收入达到六位数的人。
who are living paycheck to paycheck
那些靠工资勉强糊口的人
&gt;&gt; who don't have that emergency buffer in
那些没有应急缓冲资金的人
place. They have that anxiety. And also
地方。他们有那种焦虑。而且
that same report showed that having that
同一份报告显示，拥有那种能力
3 to six months with the the people that
与这些人相处3到6个月
they surveyed their productivity at work
他们调查了他们的工作效率。
was better just from knowing that they
知道他们
didn't have that financial stress. I
我没有那种经济压力。我
know millionaires, people that have a
认识百万富翁，那些拥有……的人
lot of money that are in a similar
很多钱都花在了类似的事情上。
position in the sense of they are
就其性质而言，它们是
stressed and anxious because their
因为他们感到压力和焦虑
overheads are also in the millions every
各项开支也高达数百万美元。
month and there's a lot of money coming
本月将有大量资金到账。
in but there's a lot of money going out.
投入了很多，但流出的资金也很多。
So they're still sometimes just one or
所以它们有时仍然只有一个或
two months away from being at zero.
距离归零还有两个月。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Um it's a different type of stress
嗯，这是另一种类型的压力。
because their sort of subjective
因为他们某种程度上是主观的
experience and lifestyle is better on a
体验和生活方式在
dayto-day. But it's interesting that
日复一日。但有趣的是……
it's it's really relative to your your
这真的取决于你的……
outgoings.
支出。
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; What's the what's the fourth point then?
那么第四点是什么呢？
So, I've got so far I've got have a
所以，到目前为止，我已经有了一个
peace of mind fund um which is one
安心基金，嗯，这是其中之一。
month's expenses. Number two is pay off
一个月的开支。第二点是回报
high interest rate debt. Number three is
高利率债务。第三名是
build an emergency fund which is three
建立一个应急基金，金额为三
times your monthly expenses if you're
如果你每月支出是……
single and six times if you're in a
单身，如果你在……的话，六次
relationship and and there's people
关系，还有人
depending on you.
这取决于你。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, most people actually stay here.
是的，大多数人确实都住在这里。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; A lot of people just save save. And I
很多人只是不停地存钱。我
just want to before we move on to step
在我们继续下一步之前，我想先说明一下。
four, I want to say that if you're
第四，我想说，如果你是
saving, you only want to save for one of
存钱，你只想为其中一件事存钱
two things. the emergency fund and the
两件事。应急基金和
piece of fund mage fund that we spoke
我们谈到的那部分基金经理基金
about. And the second thing is for any
关于。第二点是，对于任何
goals that you have in the next five
你未来五年内的目标
years, whether that's a house deposit,
多年来，无论是用于支付房屋首付，
car pay, car deposit. Other than that,
汽车付款，汽车押金。除此之外，
you don't want to be saving that money.
你不想存下那笔钱。
It's going to be
将会是
the value is going to be eaten away
价值将会被蚕食殆尽。
quicker with inflation if you're just
如果你只是
keeping it saved in a bank account. So
把它存入银行账户。所以
that's when you want to move on to step
这时你就需要进入下一步了。
four and that is investing.
第四点，那就是投资。
&gt;&gt; Okay? So you don't want to save, you
好的？所以你不想存钱，你
don't want to oversave.
不想过度储蓄。
&gt;&gt; You don't want to oversave. know when to
你不想过度储蓄。知道何时
stop saving and start investing.
停止储蓄，开始投资。
&gt;&gt; And when does one start investing and
那么，什么时候开始投资比较合适呢？
stop saving?
停止储蓄？
&gt;&gt; After they've saved the three to six
在他们救下三到六个之后
months of the living expenses. Okay,
几个月的生活费。好的，
that's the third step. At that point,
这是第三步。那时，
once they've done step one to three,
一旦他们完成了第一步到第三步，
this is the point. And the reason why I
这就是关键所在。而我这么做的原因
say this, Stephen, is because if you
斯蒂芬，这么说是因为如果你
start investing before you've got from
在你获得……之前就开始投资吧
steps one to three and you don't have
第一步到第三步，你就没有
your savings set aside and the market
你预留的储蓄和市场
goes down and you have an emergency,
手机宕机，遇到紧急情况，
you're going to have to pull that money
你得把那笔钱拿出来。
out at a loss.
亏损出局。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. or you're going to have to go into
是的。否则你就得进入
debt, which is why that was step two,
债务，所以这是第二步。
cut the financial bleeding.
止住经济损失。
&gt;&gt; So, it's really important to have steps
所以，采取步骤真的非常重要。
one to three done before you even think
一到三件事在你还没反应过来之前就已经完成了。
about investing.
关于投资。
&gt;&gt; Okay?
好的？
&gt;&gt; Those 3 to six months, it's your core
那三到六个月，是你的核心期。
living expenses. So, it's forget all
生活费。所以，忘掉一切吧。
your spending on the things that you
你花在这些东西上的钱
love or the things that make make life
爱，或者说构成生活的那些事物
good. It's just the things that you need
好的。这只是你需要的东西。
to absolutely survive because if you do
为了绝对生存下去，因为如果你这样做……
job lose your job, you're not going to
丢掉工作，你不会……
be out partying and spending loads of
出去参加派对，花很多钱
money. You're going to think, okay, how
钱。你会想，好吧，怎么会这样
do I pay my bills for the next 3 months?
我该支付接下来三个月的账单吗？
How do I survive for the next month?
接下来一个月我该怎么熬过去？
That's the thing that's going to cover
这就是要涵盖的内容。
that off.
关掉。
&gt;&gt; Okay. Right.
好的。正确的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So, it's not like the season ticket at
所以，它不像季票那样……
Manchester United or the Louis Vuitton
曼联或路易威登
jackets. It's
夹克。它是
&gt;&gt; No. No.
不。不。
&gt;&gt; It's just your your your heating, your
这只是你的供暖系统，你的
bills, your food, survival.
账单、食物、生存。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So, number four is investing.
所以，第四点是投资。
&gt;&gt; Number four is investing. For a while,
第四点是投资。一阵子，
we've heard of the phrase save for
我们听说过“除了……”这个短语。
retirement.
退休。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Saving for retirement. You cannot save
为退休储蓄。你无法保存
your way to retirement with the way cost
以最经济的方式迈向退休。
of living is going, with the way
生活就是如此，随着方式而去。
inflation is going, with the price
通货膨胀正在消退，价格也在下降。
retirement is going to cost by the time
退休到那时将会花费不少钱。
you get there. Saving is just not
你到达那里。储蓄根本不可能
enough. You have to be investing your
足够的。你必须投资你的
money. And there are two main ways that
钱。主要有两种方式
you can invest. But before I even say
你可以投资。但在我开口之前
that, most people know that they should
大多数人都知道他们应该
be investing, but they don't do it. They
他们本应投资，但他们却没有这样做。他们
say, "I'll do it tomorrow or next week
就说，“我明天或下周做。”
or next year
或者明年
&gt;&gt; or when I'm rich
或者等我富有的时候
&gt;&gt; or when I'm rich." And then by the time
或者等我有钱了。”然后到那时
they do start, they've missed out on the
他们确实开始了，但他们错过了……
most powerful lever that they had going
他们所拥有的最有力的杠杆
for them, which is time. That is one of
对他们来说，那就是时间。这是其中之一
the most important things when it comes
最重要的事情
to investing
投资
because of the way when you start
因为你开始时的方式
investing with small recurring amounts,
小额定期投资
it just compounds over time. So early
随着时间的推移，问题会不断恶化。这么早就
often when it comes to investing,
通常情况下，在投资方面，
there's two avenues to invest through.
有两种投资途径。
The first is through your employer
第一种方法是通过你的雇主。
sponsored retirement account
赞助退休账户
&gt;&gt; and the second is through your own
第二种方式是通过你自己
individual
个人
uh tax advantaged account.
呃，税收优惠账户。
&gt;&gt; What are those two things?
那两样东西是什么？
&gt;&gt; The first is done through your employer.
第一件事是通过你的雇主完成的。
So what they do is they invest on behalf
所以他们的做法是代表他人进行投资。
of you. In the UK, you're automatically
你的。在英国，你自动
enrolled into it. In the US, you'll have
已报名参加。在美国，你将拥有
to check check with your HR and get
请与您的人力资源部门核实并获取
yourself enrolled into it. And what this
你自己报名参加了。而这又是什么呢？
does is your company before you it pays
你的公司在你付款之前会做什么？
you or puts money into your bank
你或者把钱存入你的银行
account. It takes a small percentage you
帐户。只需一小部分即可
could decide how much and it puts it
可以决定多少，并将其投入多少。
towards investments
投资
for you on behalf of you pre-tax. So
代表您税前支付。所以
you're not paying tax on that amount.
这笔金额你无需缴税。
You're putting into an investment
你正在进行一项投资
account and then that money is
账户，然后那笔钱就……
compounding for you pre-tax.
税前复利收益。
&gt;&gt; Do all employees do this?
所有员工都这样做吗？
&gt;&gt; Most employers do it. Not all employers
大多数雇主都会这样做。并非所有雇主
do it. And some employers have a match
去做。有些雇主会提供匹配服务。
which means if you put some money in,
这意味着如果你投入一些资金，
they will also match that amount that
他们还会匹配相同的金额。
you're putting in. So, how do I know if
你投入了。那么，我怎么知道
my employee does this?
我的员工会这样做吗？
&gt;&gt; Check with your HR.
请咨询人力资源部门。
&gt;&gt; And is there a cap?
是否有上限？
&gt;&gt; There is a cap to how much they will
他们的消费能力是有上限的。
match.
匹配。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Um, so say if they match up to 3%, then
嗯，比如说如果它们的匹配度达到3%，那么
you want to put in the 3%. But then you
你想投入3%。但是，你
could keep going, but at this stage, you
还可以继续，但到了这个阶段，你
don't even need to go over the match at
甚至不需要回顾那场比赛。
this point of the the steps. You just
这是步骤中的这一点。你只是
want to put in enough to meet that match
想投入足够的资金来匹配对手
because you're getting the tax benefit
因为您可以享受税收优惠。
and then you're also getting free money
而且你还能获得免费的钱
from your sponsored plan on top of that.
除此之外，你还能从你的赞助计划中获得额外收益。
You don't want to leave that on the
你不想把那件事留在……
table.
桌子。
&gt;&gt; And when can I pull that money out? when
我什么时候可以取出这笔钱？什么时候
you retire at retirement. So, this is
你退休时就退休了。所以，这是
for your retirement. You're looking
为了您的退休生活。你正在查看
after your future self. It's today's you
以未来的自己为目标。这就是今天的你
planting seeds for future you. That's
为未来的你播下种子。那是
what this is about.
这是关于什么的？
&gt;&gt; What about people that say, "Listen,
那么那些说“听着，
retirement's a long way away."
离退休还早着呢。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; You know, I'm going to be what, 65, 75.
你知道，我到时候大概会是65岁，75岁吧。
It's just a long way away. I want to
路途遥远。我想要
live a good I want to live it up now,
好好生活，我现在就想好好享受生活。
&gt;&gt; I don't want to be putting money in a
我不想把钱投到……
box that I can't open for 50 years.
一个我50年都打不开的盒子。
&gt;&gt; And you want to spend the money now to
你想现在就把钱花掉
live the good life.
享受美好生活。
I the most important thing when it comes
对我来说，最重要的是
to money is understanding what you want
对金钱而言，就是明白你想要什么。
and then making sure your money backs
然后确保退款。
those decisions. And I say this because
那些决定。我这么说是因为
when I was in the graduate scheme, there
当我参加研究生项目时，
were two very different people who
他们是两个性格迥异的人。
worked in my team. And the first person
在我的团队工作过。以及第一人称
who sat opposite me on the bank of seats
坐在我对面那排座位上的是
in front of me, he used to come in in
以前，他经常在我面前进来。
his Ferrari and he on Monday morning
他的法拉利，还有他周一早上
when we were talking about what we did
当我们谈论我们所做的事情时
over our weekend, what we did on the
周末期间，我们都做了些什么呢？
weekend, he would talk about the
周末，他会谈论……
Michelin star restaurants he tried, the
他尝试过的米其林星级餐厅，
last minute trip to Italy and his
临时决定去意大利旅行，以及他的
computer screen was the next car that he
电脑屏幕是他接下来要开的车。
wanted. And on my left was Phil, who
通缉。而我左边的是菲尔，他
later become my mentor. And he came in
后来他成为了我的导师。他进来了
with his pack lunch. He wore the same
他带着自带的午餐。他穿的也是同样的衣服。
shirt tie combo that I could probably
衬衫领带的搭配，我应该可以。
remember it and sketch it from memory.
记住它，然后凭记忆画出来。
And he had his holidays, he had his
他也有他的假期，他的
vacations, but he was a lot more
假期，但他更多的是
selective about them.
对他们有所选择。
And I didn't see it at the time, but now
当时我没看到，但现在
it's so clear to me that they were
我非常清楚他们是
chasing very different things. The
追求截然不同的东西。这
person opposite of me, he was chasing
坐在我对面的人，他正在追我
this good life, the stories, the status,
这种美好的生活、这些故事、这种地位，
the memories, and that was important to
那些回忆，对……来说很重要。
him, and he went for it. But Phil, and I
他，然后他就放手一搏了。但是菲尔，还有我
visited him just before I came to LA,
我来洛杉矶之前去拜访过他。
him, his wife, um, his two kids, dogs in
他，他的妻子，嗯，他的两个孩子，还有狗……
their countryside home, and he was
他们在乡下的家，而他
enjoying the retired life. He was
享受退休生活。他是
loving life. He bought what he wanted,
热爱生活。他买了自己想要的东西。
which was early retirement, freedom,
那就是提前退休、自由。
time, choice.
时间，选择。
Neither path is wrong, but both paths,
两条路都没错，但两条路都……
both people required taking a series of
两人都需要接受一系列治疗
trade-offs.
权衡取舍。
&gt;&gt; Both had to make some sacrifices. And I
两人都必须做出一些牺牲。我
think that's the thing that people miss.
我认为这是人们容易忽略的地方。
Sometimes it's so easy to say yes to the
有时候，答应别人的请求是如此容易。
thing right in front of you because the
就在你眼前的东西，因为
benefit is there. The benefit is
好处是存在的。好处是
immediate. You don't realize what you're
即时。你没有意识到你是什么
going to miss out on later on in life.
将来会错过很多东西。
&gt;&gt; So the guy that was sat opposite you
所以，坐在你对面的那个人……
with the Ferrari, what was the
开法拉利的时候，是什么感觉？
trade-offs he was making?
他当时在做哪些权衡取舍？
&gt;&gt; He was probably going to be end up
他很可能最终会……
working for the until he had retirement
他一直工作到退休为止
money to spend. He was going to spend
可用于消费的钱。他打算花
his life at banking, but he was going to
他在银行业工作了一辈子，但他打算……
live it big, but he wouldn't have the
他过着奢靡的生活，但他不会拥有……
freedom, the choice, the time because
自由、选择、时间，因为
his spending and his income matched each
他的支出和收入相符
other.
其他。
&gt;&gt; And so what I want to just say is for
所以，我只想说的是……
anyone saying, "Oh, I just want to live
有人说：“哦，我只想活着。”
it big. I want to enjoy the money." Find
它很大。我想好好享受这笔钱。
out what is the thing that's most
找出最重要的事情是什么
important to you. And make sure your
对你来说很重要。并确保你的
your money choices stack that decision
你的金钱选择会影响这个决定
because the wrong choice isn't choosing
因为错误的选择并非真正的选择。
the wrong path. It's just not knowing
走错了路。只是不知道而已。
that you even had a choice in this whole
你竟然还有选择权？
thing. Do you think the guy that's sat
事物。你觉得坐在那里的那个人……
opposite you with the Ferrari was in any
你对面那辆法拉利随时可能出现
way insecure? Was there an element of
极度缺乏安全感？是否存在某种因素
seeking validation?
寻求认同？
&gt;&gt; There might have been. Yeah, there might
或许曾经有过。是的，有可能。
have been. That's that that might been
一直都是。那就是那样了。
what made him happy. But I think it's
什么能让他感到快乐？但我认为是这样
also not having the self-awareness to if
也缺乏自我意识，不知道如果
that made him happy, then by all means.
那肯定让他很高兴。
But if it didn't make him happy, and a
但如果这不能让他快乐，而且
lot of people do that do this, me
很多人都这样做，包括我。
included. I've I've gone through this.
包括。我经历过这些。
I've done it. When you don't know what
我做到了。当你不知道什么
makes you happy, you end up just doing
让你快乐的事，你最终就会去做。
things that gets you that external
那些能让你获得外部体验的事物
validation. And for some people, it
验证。对某些人来说，这
might mean, okay, you know what? I
可能意味着，好吧，你知道吗？我
actually do enjoy this new car. It does
我真的很喜欢这辆新车。确实如此。
bring me happiness. But for others, it
给我带来快乐。但对另一些人来说，却并非如此。
might just be a facade. And later on,
或许只是个幌子。后来，
they later on in life, they just
他们后来，在人生的后期，他们只是
realized that actually no one really
意识到其实根本没人真正
cared. The only person who cared was me.
关心。唯一在乎的人只有我。
And although I did it for other people,
虽然我这样做是为了别人，
it's uh now I realize that all the
呃，现在我意识到所有这些
trade-offs I had to make as a result of
由于以下原因，我不得不做出一些权衡：
it. Because happiness and external
它。因为幸福和外部
validation, they're like cousins.
得到证实，他们就像表亲一样。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; But they're not the same guy. Do you
但他们不是同一个人。你
know what I mean? They're like they look
你明白我的意思吗？它们看起来就像它们实际的样子。
they're kind of like of the same family,
他们就像是一家人一样。
but one of them's they're like
但其中一个就像
dysfunctional sibling,
功能失调的兄弟姐妹，
&gt;&gt; but they kind of look the same. You
但它们看起来有点像。你
know, you look at that guy in his in his
你知道，你看看那家伙，在他的……
Ferrari, you go, "Oh, must be happy."
法拉利，你会想，“哦，他一定很高兴。”
&gt;&gt; And he comes in and he's probably got a
他进来后，可能带着……
smile on his face because he's talking
他脸上带着微笑，因为他正在说话。
about his Ferrari.
关于他的法拉利。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's what he's built
是的。是的。是的。这就是他一手打造的。
himself on, I guess.
我猜是他自己。
&gt;&gt; But I don't know if that's happiness.
但我不知道那是不是幸福。
You know, the guy without the Ferrari
你知道，就是那个没有法拉利的人
might be.
有可能。
&gt;&gt; I think universally most people what
我认为大多数人都会想
they want is
他们想要的是
the freedom and the choice and the time.
自由、选择和时间。
I think more people are after that and
我认为更多的人都想要那个。
that can make more people happier than
这比
any status symbol
任何身份符号
&gt;&gt; because when you do end up going down
因为当你最终下山的时候
the route of buying something to make
购买物品进行制作的途径
your make you happy, you're on a hedonic
你让你快乐，你处于享乐主义状态。
treadmill. you're then buying the next
跑步机。然后你购买下一个
thing and the next thing and the next
一件事，下一件事，以及下一件事
thing and you get those spikes of
事情就是这样，然后你就会看到那些尖峰状的
happiness. There never is really long
幸福。从来没有真正漫长的时光。
lasting fulfilling happiness.
持久而充实的幸福。
&gt;&gt; So investing strategy number one is
所以，第一项投资策略是
asking your employer about their
询问你的雇主关于他们的
investment scheme.
投资方案。
&gt;&gt; Finding out if your employer has yeah an
弄清楚你的雇主是否有
retirement plan and making sure that
退休计划并确保
you're invested into it enough to cover
你投入的资金足以覆盖
the match that they offer.
他们提供的匹配。
&gt;&gt; What's strategy number two?
第二条策略是什么？
&gt;&gt; The strategy number two is your own
第二种策略就是你自己的策略。
individual tax advantaged investment
个人税收优惠投资
account. This is ISA in the UK and this
帐户。这是英国的个人储蓄账户（ISA），而这
is where you put your own money after
就是你之后把自己的钱放在哪里的地方。
tax into an investment account and then
将税款存入投资账户，然后
the money grows over time taxfree. So
这笔钱会随着时间推移免税增值。所以
when you pull it out at the end you
最后把它拉出来的时候
could with um the UK you could pull it
嗯，英国人可以把它拉出来。
out in 5 years and 10 years or in
5年或10年后出局
retirement then you could withdraw that
退休后你就可以提取那笔钱了。
money taxree. So both of them have
免税货币。所以他们俩都有
taxable advantages. One is when you put
应税优惠。一是当你放置
the money in, you're getting the tax
钱存进去，你就拿到税款了。
advantages. The other one's when you
优势。另一种情况是当你
draw the money out, but they both have
把钱取出来，但他们俩都有
tax advantages. And so you're putting
税收优惠。所以你把
the money in and it's growing taxfree.
资金流入，并且免税增长。
That's really a big deal. That's huge.
这可是件大事。那可是件大事。
That's that's money that's compounding
这就是复利效应。
for you and you're not paying tax on
对你来说，你不需要缴纳税款
that.
那。
&gt;&gt; But there's a limit.
但凡事都有个限度。
&gt;&gt; There's a limit uh annually it's 20,000.
每年有限额，是 20,000。
But
但
&gt;&gt; in the UK and the US,
在英国和美国，
&gt;&gt; it changes um year. at the moment I
每年都会有所变化。目前我
believe at $7,000 but with a quick
相信价格是7000美元，但很快
Google search you could stay on top of
你可以通过谷歌搜索掌握最新动态
whatever the current limit is for the
无论目前的限制是多少
account or the taxable advantage account
账户或应税优势账户
that you're investing in.
您正在投资的。
&gt;&gt; So I get paid I put it into my in the UK
所以我拿到工资后，就把它存入我在英国的账户。
it's called an ISA.
它被称为ISA（收入分成协议）。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And the the limit is 20k. So if I put
上限是 2 万。所以如果我放
20k in let's say
比如说，20k
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; If it goes to a 100k because the
如果涨到10万，因为
investments go really well is the whole
投资进展顺利就是全部。
100k taxree.
10万免税。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. You're not paying capital gains
是的。你无需缴纳资本利得税。
tax. You're not paying interest. I mean
税。你无需支付利息。我是说
sorry dividends tax. So pretty much
抱歉，股息税。差不多就是这样
that's the first place everyone should
这是每个人都应该首先去的地方。
really be investing if they want an
如果他们真的想投资的话
alternative to investing in their
投资他们的替代方案
pension.
养老金。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, that's the first thing you want to
是的，那是你首先想要做的。
cap out because of the taxable benefits
由于应税福利，上限被设定。
that come with it.
随之而来的。
&gt;&gt; Is it called a Roth IRA in the US?
在美国它叫罗斯个人退休账户（Roth IRA）吗？
&gt;&gt; That's right.
这是正确的。
&gt;&gt; So it's max contribution is $7,000 to
所以它的最大捐款额是7000美元。
$8,000 a year if you're 50 or older.
50岁及以上人士每年可获得8000美元。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. The specific amounts depending on
是的。具体金额取决于
&gt;&gt; who you are. Standard employee
你是谁。标准员工
contribution limit of $23,000.
捐款限额为 23,000 美元。
Interesting.
有趣的。
&gt;&gt; Whereas in UK it's just a flat
而在英国，它只是一块平地。
20,000 is the current.
目前是20000。
&gt;&gt; And with my ISA, this taxfree ISA that
而我的个人储蓄账户（ISA），这个免税的个人储蓄账户……
everyone is eligible to invest in, do I
每个人都有资格投资，对吗？
then have to pick the things it invests
然后必须选择投资标的。
in?
在？
&gt;&gt; Yes.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; This is the next Oh, we could talk about
这是下一个……哦，我们可以谈谈……
this now actually. Yeah. So, when you
现在确实如此。是的。所以，当你
are deciding what to invest in, this is
正在决定投资什么，这是
with the employer sponsored account, the
使用雇主赞助的账户，
employee sponsored retirement account,
员工赞助的退休账户
you actually just choose what risk
实际上，你只是在选择风险大小。
profile you have and it will do that
你拥有的个人资料就会这样做。
investing for you. So you'll say I'm I
为您投资。所以你会说我是我
feel really risky or I'm not very risky
我觉得自己很冒险，还是我不太喜欢冒险？
at all. Yeah.
完全没有。是的。
&gt;&gt; And it does it for you
它会为你完成这一切。
&gt;&gt; and it does it will invest on behalf of
而且它确实会代表……进行投资。
you.
你。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And so most people don't even realize
所以大多数人甚至都没有意识到这一点。
that they're investing but they are
他们正在投资，但他们是
investing through their company if they
如果他们通过他们的公司进行投资的话
have that employer sponsor plan.
参加雇主提供的养老金计划。
&gt;&gt; Then the individual account is you doing
那么个人账户就是你做的。
the investing yourself. You're picking
自己投资。你正在挑选
what to invest in.
投资什么？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And what shall I invest in?
那我应该投资什么呢？
&gt;&gt; My principle with investing is very very
我的投资原则非常非常
simple and it's just keep it keep it
很简单，就保持现状吧。
simple and do it for the long term. So I
简单易行，并且着眼于长远发展。所以，我
say index funds and target date
例如指数基金和目标日期
retirement funds is what you want to
你想要的是退休基金。
invest in.
投资。
&gt;&gt; What's that?
那是什么？
&gt;&gt; An index fund. Let's put it out. An
指数基金。我们把它放出来吧。一个
index, think of it as a list of
索引，可以把它想象成一个列表
companies. So the S&amp;P 500 is a list of
公司。所以，标普500指数是一份……的列表
the largest the top 500 companies to
排名前 500 的公司中规模最大的
keep this really simple. Footsie 100 is
尽量保持简单。 Footsie 100 是
the top 100 companies in the on the
排名前 100 的公司
London Stock Exchange. The fund is a pot
伦敦证券交易所。该基金是一个资金池
of money that invests in the companies
投资于这些公司的资金
on that list.
在名单上。
So by investing in an S&amp;P 500, you've
所以，通过投资标普500指数，你已经……
invested in a small piece of the top 500
投资了前500强企业的一小部分股份
companies in the US. That's what an
美国公司。这就是……
index fund is. And so even if one
指数基金是。所以即使一个
company goes down, you're diversified.
公司倒闭，你的投资组合多元化了。
And so there'll be another company that
所以还会有另一家公司……
will and the other companies will bring
威尔和其他公司将带来
it back up again.
它又恢复正常了。
&gt;&gt; And what kind of performance can I
我能做出什么样的表演？
expect from investing in the S&amp;P 500?
投资标普500指数的预期收益是什么？
Historically speaking, um the long-term
从历史角度来看，嗯，从长远来看
average has been 8 to 10% per year
平均每年增长率为 8% 至 10%。
depending on the years and the time
根据年份和时间而定
frame that you're looking at. That is
你正在看的画面。那是
different to a one-year holding period.
与一年的持有期不同。
It could go up, it could go down, you
它可能会上涨，也可能会下跌，你
just don't know. So, the longer you
我真的不知道。所以，你待的时间越长
invest for, the chances of you getting
投资，你获得的机会
that 8 to 10% on average increase.
平均增长8%至10%。
&gt;&gt; Is 8 to 10% going to make me rich
8%到10%的收益率就能让我发财吗？
though, Nisha?
不过，妮莎呢？
&gt;&gt; How long are you doing it for?
你打算做多久？
&gt;&gt; You tell me. If you have a lumpsum
你告诉我。如果你有一笔款项
amount that you're like, "Okay, you know
数量多到你会想，“好吧，你知道的。”
what? I have 2,000 that I want to
什么？我有2000个想要
invest. What should I do with it and
投资。我该如何处理它？
it's taking me five years to invest
我花了五年时间进行投资。
this?"
这？”
I would say 1,900 of that. Don't invest
我估计其中有 1900 个。不要投资
it. 100 of it. Invest. And I'll I'll say
它。其中100个。投资。我会说
why I'm saying this. 100. I want you to
我为什么这么说。 100. 我希望你
invest it for anyone listening. I want
把它推荐给所有听众。我想
you to listen. I want you to invest that
你听着。我希望你投资那笔钱。
because I want you to see and feel the
因为我想让你看到和感受到
emotions when you see your money go up
看到你的钱上涨时的情绪
over time. Sure, it's going to be small.
随着时间的推移。当然，它会很小。
It's not going to make you rich
它不会让你一夜暴富。
investing that, but you're going to
投资那笔钱，但你将会……
instill that good habit early on. And
从小培养好习惯。和
you're going to remember that because
你会记住这件事的，因为
the remaining amount, you're going to
剩余的金额，你将……
put that towards increasing your income.
把这笔钱用来增加你的收入。
That's the first thing you're going to
这是你首先要做的事情
do. Think of your income as a river and
做。把你的收入想象成一条河流，
your specific milestones, life
你人生中的具体里程碑，生活
milestones, as buckets across the river.
里程碑，就像跨过河流的水桶。
So, you have retirement, you have your
所以，你有了退休金，你有了你的
house deposit, you have your car payment
房屋首付，你还有车贷要还。
that you're all saving up for. Those
你们都在攒钱买的东西。那些
buckets will fill up faster the quicker
水桶装满的速度越快
and wider that river is. That is your
而且这条河更宽。那是你的
income that's coming through. If you
即将到账的收入。如果你
don't have much of an income coming
没什么收入来源
through, those buckets are going to take
不过，那些桶将会……
ages to fill up. That's why I say if
需要填满的岁月。所以我才说如果
it's taken you a long time to save that
你花了很长时间才保存下来。
amount, I actually would recommend you
金额方面，我其实会推荐你
putting that money towards increasing
将这笔钱用于增加
your income first before investing it.
首先要确保你的收入充足，然后再进行投资。
If however you have disposable income,
但是，如果你有可支配收入的话，
you have an reoccurring amount that you
您有一笔定期支付的款项，您
can invest monthly,
可以每月投资，
use that to your advantage. Harness the
利用这一点来发挥你的优势。驾驭
power of long-term compounding growth
长期复利增长的力量
because that is the thing that is going
因为这就是正在发生的事情
to make you rich. Sure, it will take 25,
让你致富。当然，需要25分钟。
30 years, but that is leverage that you
30年，但这正是你所拥有的优势。
don't get through your day job. It's
别熬过你的日常工作。它是
your money working for you without you
你的钱无需你费就能为你赚钱。
having to be there. So you would suggest
不得不到场。所以你会建议
if you're really at that early level to
如果你真的还处于那个初级阶段
focus on increasing your income,
专注于增加收入，
investing in increasing your income.
投资以增加收入。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, that's the first thing. If you're
是的，这是第一点。如果你是
figuring out, okay, I need to increase
弄清楚之后，好吧，我需要增加
my income. It's taking me a while to
我的收入。我花了一段时间才……
earn this amount and I only have a lump
赚到这么多钱，我只剩下一小块了。
sum of 2,000 5,000. Focus on increasing
总计 2,000 5,000。重点在于增加
your income. Yeah, that's what I would
你的收入。对，我也会这么做。
say.
说。
&gt;&gt; And how does one focus on increasing
那么，如何才能专注于增加
their income?
他们的收入？
&gt;&gt; There are a couple of ways to do this.
有两种方法可以做到这一点。
So the easiest way to increase your
所以，增加你的最简单的方法就是
income is asking for a pay rise,
收入要求加薪，
increasing your responsibility, the work
增加你的责任，工作
that you do, your contributions, and
你所做的，你的贡献，以及
saying to your boss or your manager,
对你的老板或经理说，
this is the value that I've bought. This
这就是我买到的价值。这
is the responsibility that I've taken
这是我承担的责任
on. This is what the market is paying
在。这就是市场愿意支付的价格。
for a similar role, and this is why a
担任类似职位，这就是为什么
pay rise is fair.
加薪是合理的。
&gt;&gt; The other option,
另一种选择是，
&gt;&gt; did you ever ask for a pay rise?
你有没有要求过加薪？
&gt;&gt; Multiple times. multiple multiple times
多次。多次
&gt;&gt; when you're in investment banking.
当你在投资银行工作时。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. It's one of those things where
是的。这是那种事情之一，
if you don't ask, you don't get. Of
不问，就得不到。的
course, you'll get, but you sitting
当然，你会明白的，但你现在坐着。
there and thinking the hard work is
在那里，并认为努力工作是
going to show without you asking for it.
无需你要求，他就会去表演。
It's unlikely. You're going to have to
不太可能。你必须……
build a case and say, "Okay, these are
提出论点并说：“好的，这些是……”
the things I've done. These are the
我做过的事。这些是
things that we said we were going to do
我们说过要做的事情
or I wanted to work on in my performance
或者我想在表演方面改进。
review," which is what I had. get to the
评论”，这就是我所看到的。
end of the performance review and these
绩效考核结束及这些
are the things that I actually did and
这些都是我实际做过的事情。
this is where I went above and beyond.
在这方面，我做得格外用心。
&gt;&gt; So if I'm your boss Nisha. Yeah. If we
所以，如果我是你的老板，妮莎。是的。如果我们
just replay one of those conversations
只需重放其中一段对话即可
you had.
你曾经有过。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; You were sat in a performance review and
你当时正在参加绩效考核，
what did you say to me?
你刚才跟我说什么？
&gt;&gt; I would say hey Stephen. Hey,
我会说，嘿，斯蒂芬。嘿，
&gt;&gt; 3 months ago or 6 months ago, we spoke
三个月前或六个月前，我们谈过。
about um the things that I needed to do
关于我需要做的事情
to get promoted or to get a pay rise.
获得晋升或加薪。
And we mentioned XY Z and I've done all
我们提到了XY和Z，我已经全部完成了。
of those things here and here is the
这里和这里提到的那些东西是……
feedback that I've got. Here is where
我收到的反馈。这里就是
I've gone above and beyond. And this is
我做得远超预期。这就是
some extra things that other people or
其他人或一些额外的事情
the 360 feedback that I've done. And
我所做的360度反馈。和
that this is what it says.
上面就是这么说的。
Yeah. And that's when I was like, do you
是的。那时我就​​想，你……
think that this is the bracket that we
我认为这就是我们要用的括号
discussed? Do you think that's fair?
讨论过吗？你觉得这样公平吗？
&gt;&gt; Research shows that women are much less
研究表明，女性患病率远低于男性。
likely to ask for a pay rise and when
可能会要求加薪，以及何时
they do, they are less likely to get one
如果他们这样做，他们获得一个的可能性就更小。
compared to men.
与男性相比。
Is that kind of what you found?
你发现的情况就是这样吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I've seen those facts and I think
是的，我看到了那些事实，我认为
it's really such a shame that when a
真是太可惜了，当……
woman asks for a pay rise, it may not be
女子要求加薪，可能不会成功。
seen in the same way as when a male
就像男性一样看待
counterpart asks for the payriseise. And
对方要求加薪。和
the factors that we can control are the
我们可以控制的因素是：
being prepared,
做好准备，
having the book of all the things that
拥有那本记载所有事物的书
you've done. But I recommend and this is
你已经完成了。但我推荐，而且这是
things that I done when I was in an
我在大学期间做过的一些事情
organization or when I felt like even I
组织或者当我感觉即使是我
was being paid less than my male
他的工资比我的男性同事低
counterpart is speaking firstly if
如果对方先发言，则表示对方先发言。
there's a HR team in your department
你们部门有人力资源团队。
speaking to them and asking am I online
和他们对话并询问我是否在线
or am I aligned to the average for my
或者我是否达到了平均水平？
department and for what my role is. they
我所在的部门以及我的职责是什么。他们
can give you a really good guideline as
可以为你提供非常好的指导，
to whether you are underpaid or whether
你是否薪资过低，或者
you deserve a bump to be more aligned to
你应该得到提升，以便更好地与……
the general pay in in that role. And the
该职位的一般薪酬。以及
second thing is have an ally or have
第二件事是拥有盟友或
someone in your workplace that you'd
你工作场所中某个你会……的人
always speak to, whether it's a mentor,
一定要和导师之类的人交谈
whether it's a colleague. And it's worth
无论是同事还是其他人。而且它很有价值
always speaking to other people about
总是和别人谈论
money. It's such a taboo topic.
钱。这是一个非常敏感的话题。
&gt;&gt; Yeah,
是的，
&gt;&gt; we hate it. We hate talking to someone
我们讨厌它。我们讨厌和人说话
else about their salary, what they're
关于他们的薪水，他们还有哪些方面呢？
making, but the more financial
制作，但更财务
transparency that we encourage, the more
我们越鼓励透明度，透明度就越高。
we can learn from each other.
我们可以互相学习。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Openly ask the person next to you, hey,
直接问你旁边的人：“嘿，
this is what do you get paid? As much as
这就是你的薪水？尽可能
hard as that is, open up that
虽然很难，但还是敞开心扉吧。
conversation. But the other way to
对话。但另一种方法是
increase your income is actually through
增加收入实际上是通过以下方式实现的：
switching jobs, switching companies.
换工作，换公司。
Because there's so much research that's
因为有大量的研究……
been done,
已经完成了。
and the most popular one is actually one
而最受欢迎的实际上是一个
cited by Forbes that says
福布斯援引的话说
people who stay at the same company for
在同一家公司待了很长时间的人
two years or more on average earn 50%
两年或以上工作经验，平均收入为 50%。
less over their lifetime.
一生中会减少。
And I've made a video on my salary year
我还制作了一个关于我薪资年度的视频。
by year over the last over the nine
按年计算，过去九年
years I spent in banking. And the
我在银行业工作了多年。以及
biggest pay jumps that I saw were from
我见过的最大薪资涨幅来自
switching
交换
companies.
公司。
So those are the the two ways that I
所以，这就是我采用的两种方法。
would actually say yeah increase your
实际上我会说，是的，增加你的
income by asking for more by switching.
通过转换方式要求更多收入。
I do think one of the most effective
我确实认为这是最有效的方法之一。
ways that I've seen as well is just
我也见过其他一些方法，比如……
looking at the industry as well and
同时关注行业动态
presenting a case from the industry and
提出行业案例
people have done that to me several
有人好几次都这样对我。
times. They've over the last 10 years
次数。过去十年里，他们一直如此
they've come to me and said the industry
他们来找我说，这个行业
pay for my role and my seniority level
薪酬与我的职位和资历相符
in this part of the world in this city
在这个世界的这个角落，在这个城市
is this I'm currently on this um is can
这就是我目前正在做的吗？嗯，可以吗？
we have a conversation about about this
我们讨论过这件事。
to rectify it and
为了纠正它并
I can't think of an instance where I
我想不出有什么例子表明我
haven't been receptive to that
一直没能接受这一点。
especially if it's justified you know
尤其是当这样做是合理的，你知道的
because actually sometimes the employee
因为实际上有时候员工
doesn't know the employee doesn't know
不知道员工也不知道
that they might be underpaying you um
他们可能少付了你工资。
that's a a genuine possibility I know
我知道，这确实是一种可能性。
that sounds like crazy talk But
听起来像是疯话，但
sometimes employees don't know because a
有时员工不知道，因为
lot of roles that we're hiring for these
我们正在招聘很多这类职位。
days are new roles. They're not roles
每天都是新的角色。它们不是角色
that existed 10 years ago. Even in
那是10年前就存在的。即使在
podcasting, like there's it's hard to
播客，就像……很难
find benchmarks for what people were
找到衡量人们过去的基准
paid in podcasting 10 years ago for
十年前开始做播客，收入颇丰
different roles that now exist in our
我们目前所扮演的不同角色
industry. So it's worth having a convers
行业。所以值得好好谈谈。
an honest conversation. And I do think I
坦诚的对话。而且我确实认为
do think from the employer standpoint
要从雇主的角度思考。
it's worth leading with the value that
首先值得强调的是以下价值：
you've brought like you've said versus
你已经带来了，就像你之前说的那样，而不是
blunt demands because humans are human
直截了当的要求，因为人就是人。
beings and you can turn someone's nose
人是会说话的，你可以让别人对你嗤之以鼻。
up or their backup by the way in which
顺便说一下，他们的备份是什么？
you deliver your message but delivering
你传达了你的信息，但传递
it from an evidence-based perspective
从证据角度来看
and saying this these are kind of the
这么说的话，这些有点像……
accomplishments that I've made and these
我取得的成就以及这些
are the responsibilities I've taken on
是我承担的责任
and this is like the industry um average
这差不多是行业平均水平。
and I love being here and I want to stay
我喜欢待在这里，我想留下来。
here. Um so I was wondering if it'd be
这里。嗯，所以我想知道会不会是
possible to have a conversation about
可以就此展开对话
&gt;&gt; my salary. I'd receive that very very
我的薪水。我会非常非常感激的。
well.
出色地。
&gt;&gt; And even aligning it to your company's
甚至可以使其与贵公司的……保持一致。
objectives. This is what I was doing.
目标。这就是我当时在做的事情。
Yeah. Exactly. Here is what I've done
是的。确切地。以下是我所做的。
aligned to your objectives that you're
与你的目标一致，你
looking for.
寻找。
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; And you talked about um saving for a
你还谈到了攒钱……
house as well. Is do you see buying a
房子也是。你觉得买一个
house as a good investment? Because it
房子是好的投资吗？因为它
is it is the first thing most people do,
这是大多数人做的第一件事吗？
right? It's like the first thing we're
正确的？这就像我们做的第一件事
told as part of the like script of life.
讲述的故事就像人生剧本的一部分。
When you get some money, save it up, get
当你有了点钱，就把它存起来，然后……
a mortgage.
抵押贷款。
&gt;&gt; A lot of our view about buying or
我们对购买或
renting or buying a house is actually
租房或买房实际上是
formed from what we saw our parents do
我们从小就耳濡目染，模仿父母的行为。
and what we saw the generation before us
以及我们上一代人所看到的
do. And so even looking at my life
做。所以，即使回顾我的人生，也是如此。
formed from the way my parents thought
源于我父母的思维方式
they came to the UK as immigrants and
他们作为移民来到英国，
when they bought their first house it
他们买第一套房子的时候
was like the epitome of success.
简直就是成功的典范。
They had this thing that they can
他们有这样一种能力
that represented wealth for them that
那对他们来说代表着财富。
they could touch, they could see, they
他们可以触摸，可以看见，他们
could feel. It represented stability,
能感觉到。它象征着稳定，
security. And then when we moved out of
安全。然后当我们搬出去的时候
that terrace home into another home, it
那栋联排别墅变成了另一栋房子，它
was between two stations in a catchment
位于同一流域内的两个站点之间
area. So me and my sisters got access to
区域。所以我和我的姐妹们得以接触到
better schools. That was then their
更好的学校。那时他们
happiness. That was then their goal and
幸福。那是他们当时的目标。
the milestone achieved.
里程碑达成。
And for the previous generation
而对于上一代人来说……
and still the way people see it today
而如今人们依然这样看待它。
when people say, "Oh, we need to build
当人们说，“哦，我们需要建造
buy a house for wealth building." It's
买房是为了积累财富。
because a big factor of it is that it
因为其中一个重要因素是……
was a forced mechanism of saving.
是一种强制储蓄机制。
So when you're buying a house or paying
所以，当你买房或付款时
for a mortgage, that's not optional. You
对于抵押贷款来说，这不是可选项。你
have to pay it. You then can't then
必须付钱。然后你就不能那样做了
spend that money on anything else. And
把那笔钱花在其他地方吧。和
so as a result, those monthly payments
因此，这些月供
are going towards building your equity
正在帮助你积累资产
and building this house's value. And as
并提升这栋房子的价值。而且
a byproduct, it's building wealth for
作为副产品，它还能积累财富。
you. So for someone listening to this,
你。所以对于正在收听这段音频的人来说，
if they're hearing this conversation,
如果他们听到了这段对话，
they say, "Okay, you know what? I have I
他们说：“好吧，你知道吗？我有……”
have a goal to buy and they run the
他们的目标是购买，并且他们运营着
numbers, it makes sense for them,
对它们来说，这是有道理的。
they're doing it for the long term."
他们这样做是为了长远利益。
Then I would say that's a really good
那我会说，这真是个好主意。
goal to have. Go for it. But I think we
目标。大胆试试吧。但我认为我们
put a lot of pressure on people today
如今给人们带来了很大的压力。
that they need to buy a house and as
他们需要买房，而且
soon as they start working that they
他们一开始工作就……
need to get onto that property ladder.
我需要买房置业。
So, if you're listening to this and
所以，如果你正在听这段话，
thinking that I don't have a goal to buy
我以为我没有购买的目标。
a house, then there are also ways to
如果拥有一栋房子，那么也有办法……
build wealth that don't require you to
积累无需你付出任何代价的财富
be in the real estate game.
投身房地产行业。
&gt;&gt; I think there's something psychological
我认为这其中存在一些心理因素。
about paying rent that you never see
关于支付你从未见过的房租
again. That makes you think that it's a
再次。这让你觉得它是一个
terrible idea.
糟糕的主意。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And sometimes when you look at the
有时当你观察……
mortgage payment versus the rental
抵押贷款支付与租金
payment, you go, "Well, they're the same
付款时，你会说：“嗯，它们是一样的。”
and I'll end up owning this chunk of
最终我将拥有这块地
concrete,
具体的，
&gt;&gt; so I might as well go for the chunk of
所以我不如就拿下那一大块吧。
concrete."
具体的。”
&gt;&gt; Yeah. But if you are choosing to rent
是的。但如果您选择租房的话
and actually there's been studies that's
实际上，已经有研究表明……
done on this almost nine out of 12
这项任务完成了近 9/12
regions in the UK and the same applies
英国各地区的情况也一样。
for other areas in the world as well.
世界其他地区也同样如此。
It's renting is or can be cheaper than
租房比买房便宜，或者说可能更便宜。
buying in that equivalent neighborhood.
在附近同等地段购买。
And so if you are renting and you're
所以，如果你是租房住，而且你
saving money on that difference then
省下这笔差价，就能省钱了。
you've got to be disciplined and
你必须自律，而且
sensible enough to know that
他足够明智，知道这一点。
you need to invest the difference.
你需要把差额投资出去。
&gt;&gt; What you mean? So, if your rent is 1,500
你是什​​么意思？所以，如果你的房租是1500
and to get that mortgage and you've
为了获得抵押贷款，你已经
checked the mortgage payments and you've
你查看了抵押贷款付款情况，并且……
realized that with the interest that
意识到这一点，并对此表示兴趣。
you're going to be paying on the
你将为此付费
mortgage, all the other things that come
抵押贷款，以及其他所有相关费用
into buying a house, so the stamp duty
购房时需要缴纳印花税。
that you're paying, the property tax,
你所缴纳的税款，即房产税，
the repairs, the maintenance, the
维修、保养、
insurance, if you factor in the cost of
保险，如果你把成本考虑进去的话
both, and you do run the numbers and you
两者都有，而且你确实计算过这些数据，然后你
say, "Okay, renting is cheaper than
比如说，“好吧，租房比买房便宜。”
buying than getting a home." That
买房比拥有房子更划算。
difference is what you want to be able
差异化是你想要具备的能力。
to invest. It's kind of a way for you to
投资。这算是你的一种方式
say, "I'm creating my own forced
比如说，“我正在创造我自己的强制力。”
mechanism of saving. This is my own
储蓄机制。这是我自己的
version of a mortgage. I'm the man I'm
抵押贷款的一种形式。我就是我。
saving. I'm going to set up an
保存。我打算建立一个
investment account and I'm going to
投资账户，我打算
automate it and I'm going to put money
实现自动化，我打算投入资金。
into it every single month."
每个月都投入进去。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; And that's the way you're going to build
这就是你要建造的方式。
wealth. That's just as legitimate. And
财富。这同样合情合理。和
actually, I've I've went onto the
实际上，我已经……
property ladder and the money that I put
房产阶梯和我投入的资金
in towards that flat
朝着那片平坦的方向
hasn't grown as near as much as the
增长幅度远不及……
money that I made through the stock
我通过股票赚的钱
market
市场
&gt;&gt; by investing in the S&amp;P 500.
通过投资标普500指数。
&gt;&gt; So, tell me about that. So, you you
那你跟我说说这件事吧。所以，你你
bought a property in London or somewhere
在伦敦或其他地方买了一处房产。
in the world
在世界上
&gt;&gt; in North London.
在伦敦北部。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; Um to live in.
嗯，适合居住。
&gt;&gt; And I bought it in 2017.
我是在2017年买的。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
and it's gone up in value I'd say about
而且我觉得它的价值已经上涨了。
10%.
10%。
&gt;&gt; Okay,
好的，
&gt;&gt; I've had about eight years. Then you
我已经有八年时间了。然后你
compare that to the stock market. So
将其与股票市场进行比较。所以
sure, there's a numbers side of it where
当然，这其中也涉及到数字方面的问题。
people think, okay, I need to buy a
人们会想，好吧，我需要买一个
house to build wealth, but that's what
买房是为了积累财富，但仅此而已。
I'm trying to explain that actually if
我试图解释的是，实际上如果
you save that money and you invested it,
你把那笔钱存起来并进行了投资。
you might be better off financially. But
你的经济状况可能会有所改善。但
coming back to your point, yes, there's
回到你刚才的观点，是的，有。
that psychological thing of okay, do I
那种心理上的感觉，好吧，我该怎么做？
want to pay that money on rent or do I
我想把那笔钱用来交房租，还是……
want to buy? The other psychological
想买吗？另一种心理
part of it is also
其中一部分也是
the comfort of knowing that you have
知道自己拥有这种安心感
somewhere. And this is a big reason as
某处。而这正是主要原因之一。
to why I bought. The comfort of knowing
这就是我购买的原因。知晓的慰藉
that no matter what happens, you have
无论发生什么，你都有
this place. It's yours. The landlord
这个地方。它是你的。房东
can't serve you notice. You can do
无法向您送达通知。你可以这样做
whatever you want to the
你想做什么都行
flat within certain restrictions and
在一定限制条件下保持平坦
rules. And you have this piece of the
规则。而你拥有这部分
earth that belongs to you. And so that's
属于你的土地。就是这样。
the psychological comfort that came from
来自……的心理安慰
it. Sure, we could talk about the
它。当然，我们可以谈谈……
numbers and what investing will do and
数字以及投资将会产生什么影响
how much you can make on that, but the
你能靠这个赚多少钱，但是
bit that often gets forgotten about is
经常被遗忘的一点是
the invisible side, which is
看不见的一面，也就是
the peace of mind, the psychological
内心的平静，心理
comfort of just owning a home.
拥有房屋带来的舒适感。
&gt;&gt; So, can I ask how much did your
所以，请问您的收入是多少？
apartment cost in London?
伦敦的公寓价格是多少？
&gt;&gt; 530.
530.
&gt;&gt; So, you spent 530k on it? Yeah.
所以，你花了53万？是的。
&gt;&gt; Um, presumably on like a mortgage or
嗯，大概是指抵押贷款之类的吧
something at the time.
当时是这样的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, it was on a mortgage. Yeah.
是的，是用抵押贷款买的。是的。
&gt;&gt; So, 530K. It's gone up 10%.
所以，530K。上涨了10%。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, it's gone up about 50k.
是的，上涨了大约 5 万。
&gt;&gt; About 50k. So, it's now worth 580.
大约5万。所以，它现在价值580。
&gt;&gt; But if you'd put that amount of money
但如果你投入那么多钱……
into the S&amp;P 500.
纳入标普500指数。
&gt;&gt; Well, the thing with the house in a flat
嗯，关于公寓里的房子那件事。
is you could use the mortgage, you
如果你能使用抵押贷款，你
wouldn't put that full amount in it
不会把全部金额都放进去。
because you had the mortgage. But if you
因为你背负着房贷。但是如果你
put that deposit amount into it.
把存款金额存入账户。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. The deposit amount. Yeah.
是的。存款金额。是的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. The the amount that you would have
是的。你将拥有的数量
put on just a down payment. Um the stamp
只需支付首付。嗯，邮票
duty that I would have also paid. If I
我本也应该缴纳这笔税款。如果我
saved that amount and then put it put
存下那笔钱，然后把它放
that amount whatever it was and invested
不管金额是多少，都投资了。
that that's the comparison that I would
这就是我所要进行的比较。
have made.
已经制作完成。
&gt;&gt; So how much was that in total that you
所以总共是多少钱？
paid into the
已支付
&gt;&gt; um
嗯
&gt;&gt; property?
财产？
&gt;&gt; I put about
我写了大约
50 I think K.
50 我想是 K。
&gt;&gt; 50k and probably the net return on that
5万，以及可能由此产生的净收益。
if it's gone up
如果它上涨了
&gt;&gt; 10%.
10%。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So tank
是的。所以坦克
&gt;&gt; 55k.
55k。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And the S&amp;P 500 in the same time
是的。同时，标普500指数也出现了类似的情况。
has delivered roughly 10 to 12% per year
每年大约带来 10% 到 12% 的收益。
on average. It has more than doubled in
平均而言。它已经翻了一番多
value since 2017.
自 2017 年以来的价值。
So you would have probably got
所以你大概会得到
&gt;&gt; there you go.
好了。
&gt;&gt; Pretty incredible return on the S&amp;P 500.
标普500指数的回报率相当惊人。
Even in the last 5 years, the S&amp;P 500
即使在过去5年里，标普500指数也……
has grown 90%.
增长了90%。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, makes sense.
嗯，有道理。
&gt;&gt; So it's almost doubled in the last 5
所以过去5年里，它几乎翻了一番。
years alone, which which means you would
独自一人待上几年，这意味着你会
have basically doubled your money just
基本上，你的钱翻了一番。
investing it in an index fund.
将其投资于指数基金。
&gt;&gt; Are you looking at that from the lows of
你是从低谷的角度来看待这件事的吗？
the co? Yeah, it says even with the co
公司？是的，它说即使有合作方也是如此。
lows, it says so um it has more than
低谷，它说，嗯，它有不止一个。
doubled in value since 2017 driven by
自 2017 年以来价值翻了一番，主要原因是
strong growth in technology despite the
尽管科技领域发展强劲，但
co crash and 2022 pullback
共同体崩溃和2022年回调
&gt;&gt; last years.
过去几年。
&gt;&gt; Case in point that we we're we're
举例来说，我们……
looking at building wealth just through
仅仅着眼于通过以下方式积累财富
one mechanism
一种机制
that feels like it's urgent and needs to
感觉这件事很紧急，需要……
be done by everyone. But actually, if
人人都要这样做。但实际上，如果
you're looking at it purely from a
你完全是从另一个角度来看待这个问题的。
numbers and building wealth perspective,
数字与财富积累视角
there are other ways to do that.
还有其他方法可以做到这一点。
&gt;&gt; My brother is was an investment banker.
我哥哥以前是投资银行家。
He now works full-time um helping with
他现在全职工作，帮忙……
my money and helping in my my companies.
我的钱，以及对我的公司提供的帮助。
He went to LSC. He's a very smart guy.
他去了LSC。他是个非常聪明的人。
He's always been like the buffin in the
他一直就像……
family. He always talked to me about
家庭。他总是跟我谈论……
this ter opportunity cost. So, when I
这是机会成本。所以，当我
told him I said, I want to buy this
我告诉他，我说我想买这个
house in Cape Town. He was like, you
位于开普敦的房子。他当时就说，你
know, this is going to cost you X
要知道，这将花费你 X 美元。
millions. Um, think about the
百万。嗯，想想……
opportunity cost.
机会成本。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And he always every time I say I want to
每次我说我想……的时候，他总是
do this, he's like, think about the
他会说，这样做，想想……
opportunity cost. And he he basically
机会成本。而且他基本上
stands in the way of it. What is
阻碍了这件事。什么是
opportunity cost? And why should why
机会成本？为什么应该这样做？
should people be thinking about this
人们是否应该考虑这个问题
when they're spending their money?
他们什么时候花钱？
&gt;&gt; So every pound or dollar that we spend
所以，我们花的每一英镑或每一美元
is one less that we could use on
我们少了一个可以用来……
something else. And that is the
别的什么。这就是……
opportunity cost in essence.
本质上就是机会成本。
And we often
我们经常
don't think about life in terms of
不要从以下角度思考人生：
opportunity costs because we only look
机会成本，因为我们只关注
at the thing that is in front of us. So
关注我们眼前的事物。所以
your brother was telling you about how
你哥哥跟你讲过……
you can make more money investing
投资可以赚更多钱
somewhere else. But what you saw is this
别的地方。但你所看到的却是这样的
one thing in front of you and you
你面前只有一件事，而你
thought no, I don't even know if I'm
我想，不，我甚至不知道我是不是
going to make this money elsewhere. I
我打算在别的地方赚这笔钱。我
don't know if that's going to happen.
不知道会不会发生。
This thing is right in front of me.
这东西就在我眼前。
&gt;&gt; And that's the thing with the with
这就是“with”的含义。
opportunity cost is always a a trade-off
机会成本始终是一种权衡取舍。
of what you can see and what you can't
你能看到的和你看不到的
see. But with every decision you make,
看。但你做的每一个决定，
there's something else that you're
你还有其他事情
saying no to. is coming at the cost of
拒绝。这样做的代价是
something else.
别的什么。
&gt;&gt; I was thinking about that as you you
我当时也在想这件事，就像你……
were talking and just to give a bit of
我们正在聊天，顺便提一下……
color to this for people at home and a
为居家人士增添色彩
good example of opportunity cost. So
这是机会成本的一个好例子。所以
like yesterday I bought lunch for the
就像昨天一样，我买了午饭。
team, right? And the lunch cost $100. It
团队，对吧？这顿午餐花了100美元。它
was like the salad bar in in Los Angeles
就像洛杉矶的沙拉吧一样。
cost me $100. Fine. $100, who cares? But
我花了100美元。美好的。 100美元？谁在乎？但
then when I think about the numbers you
然后当我想到这些数字时，你
shared earlier on, if I'd taken that
之前分享过的，如果我当时接受了
$100 and put it into the S&amp;P 500 in 40
投入100美元，投资标普500指数，40年到期。
years, assuming I got 10% return a year,
假设每年收益率为10%，那么几年后……
which is like the average of the S&amp;P,
这类似于标普500指数的平均值，
&gt;&gt; that is almost $5,000.
那差不多是5000美元。
&gt;&gt; So in terms of opportunity cost, buying
因此，就机会成本而言，购买
the team lunch for $100 has effectively
团队午餐花费100美元，效果显著。
cost me in opportunity $5,000 that I
这让我损失了5000美元的机会。
would have had um presuming that return
本来应该有的，假设回报
in 40 years from now. So that lunch
40年后。所以那顿午餐
yesterday actually cost me potentially
昨天实际上让我损失惨重。
roughly $5,000.
大约5000美元。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And I guess for you it's
是的。我想对你来说也是这样。
&gt;&gt; that's the last time the team get lunch.
那是球队最后一次一起吃午饭。
&gt;&gt; But on the other side, you might have
但另一方面，你可能也有
missed out on how the team felt
错过了了解球队感受的机会。
&gt;&gt; going to that lunch and the invisible
去参加那次午餐和那看不见的东西
benefits that you might have got from
您可能从中获得的益处
that. Whether it was just the memories
那。或许仅仅是那些回忆
at that moment in time, whether it's the
在那一刻，无论是
motivation,
动机，
&gt;&gt; whether it's the culture that you're
无论是你所处的文化
bringing in, that's the thing that you
引入，那就是你……
might miss out on if you choose that
如果你选择那样做，可能会错过一些东西。
$5,000 in X years of time. And I guess
X 年后获得 5000 美元。我想
it's a balancing act as well. Like you
这也是一种平衡的艺术。就像你一样
know, I was thinking about the guy you
你知道吗，我一直在想你这个人。
mentioned with a Ferrari and if he were
提到他开法拉利，如果他是
to die today, one could argue that in
如果今天就死去，有人可能会说……
fact he played life correctly.
事实上，他正确地对待了人生。
&gt;&gt; Absolutely.
绝对地。
&gt;&gt; Because he lived it. He saw it. He did
因为他亲身经历过。他看到了。他确实
it.
它。
&gt;&gt; And this is I think the difference you
我认为这就是你们之间的区别。
see in people. Some people have that
能从人身上看到这一点。有些人有这种能力。
long-term view where they think, "No, I
从长远角度来看，他们认为，“不，我
want my money when I'm 65 or 70 in my
等我65岁或70岁的时候，你们还要我的钱？
pension fund." And other people play a
养老基金。” 其他人也参与其中
bit more short term in their life and
他们的生活更注重短期利益。
go, I just want to have good experiences
走吧，我只想拥有美好的体验。
now.
现在。
And so it's hard to understand who's
因此很难理解谁是
right because we don't know how this
对，因为我们不知道这会如何发展。
story ends, I guess.
故事大概就此结束了。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And I think there's a fine line,
是的。我认为这其中的界限很微妙。
but there's also a way to balance living
但生活也可以找到平衡之道。
in the present with planning with for
现在通过计划来应对
the future by understanding that you are
通过了解自己，把握未来。
going to allocate a specific amount of
将分配特定金额的
the money that comes in towards the here
这里收到的钱
and now. And then the rest you are going
现在。然后剩下的部分你就要走了。
to look use towards the future you
展望未来，你
because there's something very rewarding
因为这样做会有非常有意义的事情发生
about spending now. When you know the
现在该如何花钱了。当你了解
future you has already been looked
未来的你已被展望过。
after, it makes you want to spend it
之后，它会让你想要花钱。
without thinking, oh, what is this
不假思索地，哦，这是什么？
coming at the opportunity cost of?
这样做会付出什么机会成本？
&gt;&gt; Do you think people should buy a house
你认为人们应该买房吗？
if their objective is to make money or
如果他们的目标是赚钱，或者
do you think there are other
你认为还有其他的吗？
opportunities like the S&amp;P 500, like
像标普500指数这样的投资机会，
using your tax-free ISA? A lot of people
使用免税个人储蓄账户 (ISA) 吗？很多人
listening probably don't have or on
听可能没有或没有
their way to building a deposit or
他们建立存款的方式或
working their way to have the money for
他们努力赚钱
a deposit. If they're putting themselves
押金。如果他们把自己置于危险境地
under pressure and they think that
在压力之下，他们认为
they're just buying a house to build
他们只是买房子来盖房子而已。
wealth, I would say actually look into
财富，我建议你好好研究一下。
investing through that stocks and shares
通过股票进行投资
ISA as a start that is taxfree. If you
ISA（个人储蓄账户）是一个免税的起点。如果你
haven't even started investing through
甚至还没开始投资呢。
that stocks and shares is which by the
股票和股份是由
way 75%
方式 75%
roughly of people in the UK aren't
英国大约有百分之十的人不是
investing.
投资。
So yeah, I would definitely say open
所以，是的，我肯定会说开放。
that up first.
首先是这个。
&gt;&gt; And do you think one should split a
你认为应该把一个
proportion of their investments into
他们投资的比例
different categories of risk
不同类别的风险
because you got like crypto on the one
因为你把加密货币放在了某个地方
side of it which sometimes feel like
它的一部分，有时感觉像是
being at roulette table and then you've
在轮盘赌桌旁，然后你
got things that are typically safe like
有一些通常很安全的东西，比如
the S&amp;P 500.
标准普尔500指数。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I'm going to say with the stocks
是的，我会说股票方面……
and shares actually when you invest in
实际上，当你投资股票时，
and a lot of people also want to invest
很多人也想投资。
in crypto but they also want to invest
他们不仅想投资加密货币，还想进行其他投资。
in individual stocks as well. Should I
个股也存在这种情况。我应该吗？
go after the next big winning company
瞄准下一个大赢家公司
stock? Should I invest in this stock?
库存？我应该投资这支股票吗？
Um, what I want to say is that there's
嗯，我想说的是，有
two parts to think about the returns but
需要考虑回报的两个方面，但
also the behavioral concepts.
还有行为概念。
How you feel when it comes to investing
您对投资有何感受？
because
因为
your one of the biggest impacts on
你对……的影响最大
market performance
市场表现
is your contributions but also your
是你的贡献，也是你的
behavior.
行为。
So,
所以，
Fidelity did a re found that
富达重新调查发现
people who invested in funds
投资于基金的人
underperformed the fund that they were
表现逊于他们所代表的基金
in.
在。
It sounds impossible.
听起来不可能。
How can you be underperforming a fund
如何才能使基金业绩不佳？
that you're in? But then when they
你参与其中了吗？但当他们
looked into it, they found that when
经过调查，他们发现当
fear and anxiety took over, when the
恐惧和焦虑袭来，
market dropped, these people bought sold
市场下跌，这些人买卖了。
bought sold. They essentially danced in
买入 卖出。他们基本上是在跳舞
and out of the fund as a result
因此，资金被挪用。
underperforming the fund that they were
表现逊于他们所处的基金
already holding.
已持有。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So it went when it went down, they
好的。所以，当它倒下的时候，情况就是这样。
sold.
卖。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. When it went down, they sold. When
是的。股价下跌时，他们就抛售了。什么时候
they went up, they bought. And so what
他们上去买了。所以呢？
you want to do is you want to invest in
你想做的就是投资
something that makes you buy and hold.
让你买入并长期持有的东西。
Fidelity looked into the groups of
富达投资对以下群体进行了调查：
people that had invested in their funds
那些投资了他们基金的人
to see which group performed the best.
看看哪个组表现最好。
And when they looked into it, they found
当他们调查此事时，他们发现
one group significantly outperformed all
其中一组的表现显著优于所有组。
other groups when it came to investment
与其他群体在投资方面相比
returns. And that was dead people. Dead
返回。那些都是死人。死的
people outperformed the living when it
当人类……的时候，它的表现优于活着的人。
came to investment returns
最终体现在投资回报上
because they didn't touch their
因为他们没有碰他们的
investment account. They just said it,
投资账户。他们就这么说了。
forget it. They didn't chase the next
忘了它。他们没有追逐下一个
company stock. They don't go after the
公司股票。他们不会追究
thing that's going to go up really
确实会上涨的东西
quickly and down really quickly. And
迅速下降，速度非常快。和
that all ties into the behavior.
这一切都与行为有关。
You're not letting your emotions drive
你没有让情绪左右你的决定。
the investments. And by the way, this
投资。顺便说一句，这
they found the second best performing
他们发现表现第二好的。
group were the people who forgot that
这些人是那些忘记了这一点的人。
they had a fund in the first place. So
他们本来就有一笔资金。所以
when it comes to deciding what
当要决定什么
allocation you want your portfolio to
您希望您的投资组合如何分配
be, it's understanding, okay, what is
是，是理解，好吧，什么是
going to give you the returns, but also
会给你带来回报，但同时也
what is the thing that's going to help
什么能有所帮助？
you stay the course even when the market
即使市场动荡，你也要坚持到底。
goes and drops?
去掉？
What will make you feel like, okay, I
什么会让你觉得，好吧，我
could still stay and hold my position?
我还能留下来保住我的职位吗？
That's how to decide what kind of
这就是决定哪种类型的方法
percentage portfolio you want for
您希望投资组合的百分比是多少
yourself. And I've done that with my
你自己。我已经用我的
portfolio. There's with crypto, it's
文件夹。加密货币领域就是这样。
less than 2% of my overall portfolio.
不到我整体投资组合的2%。
I've invested the amount that I feel
我投入了我认为合适的金额。
like it won't make a difference if I
好像就算我这么做也不会有什么区别。
lose it. And if it goes to the moon,
丢掉它。如果它能飞到月球，
great. And that's how when I say
伟大的。这就是我所说的
somewhere here, the last thing I want to
这里某个地方，我最不想看到的就是
do is encourage people before they've
应该做的是在人们……之前鼓励他们。
even set up the financial foundations to
甚至还奠定了财务基础
invest in something that can go up and
投资那些价格会上涨的东西
come go down when 75% of the population
当75%的人口下降时，就会出现这种情况
isn't investing.
不是投资。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; And the reason why they're not investing
而他们不投资的原因在于……
is because, and I keep hearing this from
因为，而且我一直听到有人这么说
time and time again from the people I
一次又一次，来自我身边的人
speak to, is either they're really
与人交谈，要么他们真的
scared they're going to lose money or
害怕赔钱或
they don't know where to start. And so
他们不知道从何入手。所以
when it comes to losing money, I always
说到赔钱，我总是
say do the foundations first, set up
先打好基础，做好准备。
your portfolio there, and then move on
把你的投资组合放在那里，然后继续前进。
to speculative assets should you want to
如果你想投资投机性资产的话
go down that path. I remember the first
沿着那条路走。我记得第一次
time I invested and I I downloaded this
我投入了时间，我下载了这个
app and I put some money in there and
我使用了这个应用，并在里面存了些钱。
then I watched it and I was watching it
然后我就看了，我一直在看。
so much and it was going up and down and
太多了，而且一直在上下波动。
up and down and like three four months
上上下下，大概三四个月吧
later I sold it and I didn't really make
后来我把它卖了，但其实没赚到什么钱。
a I think I lost a couple of a couple
我想我丢了一对
hundred quid or whatever and then I
一百英镑或者其他什么，然后我
watched that same investment over the
密切关注着这笔投资
next five, six, seven years just go to
接下来的五、六、七年就这么过去了
the moon.
月亮。
&gt;&gt; Yeah,
是的，
&gt;&gt; it went up and I remember thinking,
它升了上去，我记得当时我在想，
I should have just kept it in
操，我真应该把它留着。
there. And then the best investment I
那里。然后，我最好的投资就是
ever made correlates to what you were
曾经与你所做的事情相关的事物
saying because I lost my password.
因为我忘记了密码。
&gt;&gt; I like lost the password to log in.
我好像忘记了登录密码。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
是的。是的。是的。是的。
&gt;&gt; And so I couldn't do anything about it
所以我对此无能为力。
anyway. And I watched it and it went
反正。我看了，然后就……
down and up and down and up and down and
下，上，下，上，下，
up. But over 5 years it went really
向上。但五年多来，情况真的发生了变化。
really high. And so when I first started
非常高。所以，当我最初开始的时候
investing in crypto and I invested in
我投资了加密货币。
Ethereum and now Bitcoin, my strategy
以太坊，现在还有比特币，这就是我的策略
was the same. My strategy was get the
是一样的。我的策略是获得
the private keys and give half of them
交出私钥，并分出其中一半。
to one person that I trust and half of
给我信任的一个人，以及一半
them to the other person that I trust.
把它们交给另一个我信任的人。
And even if I want to, I can't do
即使我想，我也做不到。
anything about it. And that's proven to
关于这件事的任何事。这一点已被证明是
be one of my greatest returns in
这将是我最大的回报之一
investing because I just
投资是因为我就是
&gt;&gt; I don't even know what's going on with
我甚至不知道发生了什么事。
it. I'm not paying attention.
它。我没在听。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And that's the thing, you've just
是的。关键就在这里，你刚刚
taken the motions out of the equation.
把动作因素排除在外。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; There's no fear, greed. There's nothing
没有恐惧，只有贪婪。什么也没有
else that controls your financial
否则，你的财务就会受到影响。
decisions other than logic.
非逻辑性的决策。
&gt;&gt; I think actually on that first
我认为实际上首先
investment I made when I was like must
我当时做的投资就像必须
have been in my early 20ies, I needed
我二十出头的时候，我需要
the money.
钱。
&gt;&gt; Like I didn't have the emergency fund or
就好像我没有应急资金一样
a peace of mind fund. So when it started
安心基金。所以当它开始时
to go down a little bit naturally you
自然地往下走一点
kind of panic. So I think in that the
有点恐慌。所以我认为，在这一点上
second season of life where I started
人生第二季，我从这里开始
investing in Ethereum and Bitcoin it
投资以太坊和比特币
didn't really matter if I lost the
输赢其实并不重要
money. So it made it easier to hold my
钱。所以握住我的手就更容易了。
nerves. And I think nerves are such a
紧张。我觉得神经真是太……
huge part of investing. Um, it goes to
投资的重要组成部分。嗯，它通往
what you said earlier, like it's worth
你之前说的那些话，好像很有价值。
taking $100 or £100 or whatever you can,
拿走100美元或100英镑，或者你能拿的任何金额。
which is a really inconsequential number
这是一个微不足道的数字。
of money, and putting it into some kind
把钱投资到某种用途
of S&amp;P 500 or even a stock just to feel
标普500指数成分股，甚至只是一只股票，仅仅是为了感受一下。
that almost to like train your
那几乎就像训练你的
psychology and emotions of like what the
心理学和情感，比如……
ups feel like and what the down feel
高潮是什么感觉，低谷是什么感觉
like.
喜欢。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, exactly.
对，没错。
&gt;&gt; So, your investment strategy, your
所以，你的投资策略，你的
portfolio, you mentioned it there.
你的投资组合，你在那里提到了。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; What does it look like?
它长什么样？
&gt;&gt; It's 40% funds.
资金占比40%。
&gt;&gt; Okay. What kind of funds? index funds,
好的。什么类型的资金？指数基金
&gt;&gt; S&amp;P 500, uh I also do international
标普500指数，嗯，我也做国际市场。
markets, so UK um so emerging developed
市场，所以英国，嗯，所以新兴市场
uh across all sectors I also do and I
嗯，在所有领域我都这样做，而且我
keep it very very diversified S&amp;P 500
保持高度分散化，标普500指数
target date retirement funds that
目标日期退休基金
automatically rebalance. So target date
自动重新平衡。所以目标日期
retirement fund for anyone who's
任何人的退休基金
listening and wondering what it is, it's
听着，我在想这是什么，是
essentially a fund that has different
本质上是一个具有不同性质的基金
types of investments within it. So you
其中包含的投资类型。所以你
could go on to a platform of your choice
可以转到你选择的平台。
that you use to invest and you could
你用来投资的，你可以
type in target date retirement fund and
输入目标日期退休基金
at the end of every fund will have a
每个基金结束时都会有一个
year and so you want to pick the year
所以你想选择年份
that is the closest to the year that you
那是最接近你出生年份的年份。
plan to retire. So if you plan to retire
计划退休。所以，如果你计划退休的话
in 2050, that's the year that you will
2050年，就是你将要到来的那一年。
pick. And what that fund does is it
挑选。而该基金的作用是……
rebalances
再平衡
and the
以及
the percentage of different investments
不同投资的百分比
changes to become more conservative as
向更加保守的方向转变
you approach retirement.
你即将退休。
&gt;&gt; So it starts to protect you a little bit
所以它开始对你起到一定的保护作用。
more.
更多的。
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; So it goes risk off. it kind of goes
所以风险降低了。它有点像
less risky or
风险较小或
&gt;&gt; it becomes less risky because you don't
因为你没有这样做，所以风险就降低了。
want to be investing the same when you
想在投资时也进行同样的投资
don't have that much time as you if
如果你没有那么多时间的话
you're investing in your 20s 30s you
你在20多岁到30多岁之间进行投资
have enough time to ride out the stock
有足够的时间熬过这波股市。
market waves
市场波动
&gt;&gt; so that's 40% of your portfolio
所以这占你投资组合的40%。
&gt;&gt; that's 40% 30% is real estate
那占40%，30%是房地产。
&gt;&gt; okay in all parts of the world
在世界各地都很好
&gt;&gt; no just in the UK
不仅限于英国
&gt;&gt; just in the UK
仅在英国
&gt;&gt; yeah then I'll say about 25% I'm putting
是的，那我大概会说我投入了25%的资金。
back into my business at the moment
目前我已重返商界
&gt;&gt; okay
好的
&gt;&gt; and then the remaining is between crypto
剩下的部分则属于加密货币领域。
to and cash cash and cash reserves.
现金、现金储备及其他现金。
&gt;&gt; Okay. What about investing in yourself?
好的。为什么不投资自己呢？
Because because you know we think about
因为你知道，我们会考虑
education and skills and stuff like
教育、技能等等
that. Should we be investing a small
那。我们是否应该小额投资？
amount of money into our selves in some
在某些方面，我们给自己投入了相当数量的资金。
capacity?
容量？
&gt;&gt; 100%. I think you just don't stop
100%。我觉得你根本停不下来。
investing in yourself at any point in
在任何时候投资自己
time. It goes down to increasing your
时间。关键在于提高你的
income, increasing your skills,
收入增加，技能提升
increasing your value, which then has a
提升你的价值，然后……
knock on effect on everything else that
对其他一切事物产生连锁反应
you're investing into.
您正在投资。
&gt;&gt; It's a really interesting time to be
这是一个非常有趣的时代。
leading a business. New skills are
领导一家企业。新技能是
constantly being invented, and ones that
不断有新发明，以及那些
didn't exist a few months ago are now
几个月前还不存在的东西现在却存在了。
all of a sudden essential. Our team at
突然变得必不可少。我们团队
Flight Story thrives on staying ahead of
Flight Story 的成功秘诀在于始终保持领先地位
emerging tech and innovation. So
新兴技术与创新。所以
whenever we need to plug into those
每当我们需要接入这些设备时
skills of the future like vibe coding,
未来技能，例如氛围编码，
AI agent development, generative engine
AI代理开发，生成引擎
optimization, all of the technical
优化，所有技术
things we've talked about on the show
我们在节目中讨论过的事情
before, we always go to the same place,
以前，我们总是去同一个地方。
which is Fiverr, our show sponsor, and
那就是 Fiverr，我们的节目赞助商，
the place where that future focused
那个聚焦未来的地方
talent quietly shows up before the rest
人才总是在其他人之前悄然出现。
of the world catches on. Their
全世界都明白了。他们的
freelancers are reliable, high
自由职业者可靠、高
performing, and also highly vetted. And
表演精彩，而且经过严格筛选。和
you'll find them in over 750 categories.
您可以在超过 750 个类别中找到它们。
Fiverr isn't just for quick jobs. We use
Fiverr 不仅仅是用来接短期工作的。我们使用
their talent more on complex long-term
他们的才能更多地体现在复杂的长期发展上。
projects, ones that require an expert to
需要专家参与的项目
take charge. And you can tap into
掌控局面。你可以利用
tomorrow's talent at fiverr.com/diary.
明日之星，尽在 fiverr.com/diary。
And for 10% off your first order, use
首次下单即可享受 10% 的折扣，使用优惠码
code diary. You actually you made a
代码日志。你实际上做了一个
video um about 40 books that you've read
视频里大概讲了你读过的40本书。
that improve your own financial
改善你的财务状况
literacy. If there was one book that you
读写能力。如果只能选一本书，你
recommend people to read
推荐人们阅读
that you think is most accessible and
你认为最容易实现的
will advance their financial literacy in
这将提高他们的金融素养
the most profound way that did that for
最深刻的方式就是如此。
you, what book would you recommend?
你，你会推荐哪本书？
&gt;&gt; Think and Grow Rich by Napoleon Hill.
《思考致富》，拿破仑·希尔著。
It's not actually about financial
其实这与财务无关。
literacy, but it's around money mindset.
虽然识字能力有所提高，但关键在于金钱观。
And the other book to start with when it
还有另一本可以先从这本书开始读起。
comes to financial literacy is also The
谈到金融素养，这也是……
Richest Man in Babylon. when people
巴比伦最富有的人。当人们
don't learn about money is because they
不学习理财是因为他们
find it quite boring
觉得很无聊
&gt;&gt; and not very interesting. So, Richest
而且没什么意思。所以，最富有的
Man in Babylon does a good job in
《巴比伦人》做得不错
intertwining a novel into financial
将小说融入金融领域
literacy concepts.
读写概念。
&gt;&gt; I've not read that book. I've heard a
我没读过那本书。我听说过一个
lot about it though.
不过，关于它有很多内容。
&gt;&gt; It's the underlying principles when it
关键在于其基本原则。
comes to money don't really change much
说到钱，其实变化不大。
and it's really starts at the basics
一切都要从基础开始。
when it comes to saving and spending.
在储蓄和消费方面。
So, it's it's a good starting point. Are
所以，这是一个很好的起点。是
there any other principles of of
还有其他原则吗？
building wealth that we haven't talked
积累我们尚未谈及的财富
about? I mean, we we haven't talked
关于？我的意思是，我们还没谈过。
about payday routines. Um, but I've
关于发薪日流程。嗯，但我有
heard you talk at length about what we
我听你详细地谈过我们的事情。
should do when we get paid every single
我们应该在每次拿到工资的时候都这样做
month. Some of the things we've talked
月。我们谈过的一些事情
about already, like uh knowing your
关于已经，就像呃，知道你的
reference point, which is was point one,
参考点，即点一，
right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; That was your piece of mind fund. I
那是你的安心基金。我
guess knowing your reference point is
猜猜看，知道你的参考点是
essentially just
基本上就是
&gt;&gt; understanding where your finances break
了解你的财务状况是如何透支的
down and what buckets they fall into.
落下，然后落入哪些桶里。
&gt;&gt; So I would
所以我会
actually say this is really important
实际上，这一点非常重要。
for anyone to know and it's the three
任何人都应该知道，而且是三个
numbers. It's called the 65205
数字。它叫做65205
and it's three numbers that anyone
这是任何人的三个数字
should know when it comes to money and
应该了解金钱方面的事情
their own personal finance.
他们自己的个人财务状况。
&gt;&gt; Okay. 65205. Okay. And the way it works
好的。 65205。好的。它的运作方式
is you want to the idea of it is to take
你想表达的意思是，要采取
your
你的
net income. This is your take-home pay
净利。这是你的实际到手工资
after you pay taxes, not the number on
缴税之后，而不是税款上的那个数字。
your job description,
您的职位描述，
the number after you paid state
付款后的数字状态
contribution, all other taxes. And you
捐款，以及所有其他税费。你呢
want to split that into three buckets.
想把它分成三桶。
The fundamental, which is your core
根本，也就是你的核心
living expenses, everything that is
生活开支，所有的一切
essential to your living costs. mortgage
对您的生活开支至关重要。抵押
or rent, utilities, groceries, minimum
或房租、水电费、食品杂货、最低限度
debt payments,
偿还债务，
car payments, all of that should make up
汽车贷款，所有这些应该都算进去了。
approximately 65% of your net income.
约占您净收入的 65%。
&gt;&gt; Okay?
好的？
&gt;&gt; The 20% that's for your fund spending.
那20%是你的基金支出。
These are for the pottery painting that
这些是用于陶器彩绘的。
you booked last minute, the Glastonbury
你最后一刻才预订了格拉斯顿伯里音乐节。
tickets, the Pilates class. That should
门票，普拉提课程。那应该
make up about 20% of your take-home pay.
约占你实际到手收入的 20%。
And the remaining 15% that's for your
剩下的15%归你所有。
future you. That's today's you planting
未来的你。这就是你今天的种植任务
seeds for tomorrow's you. And that
为未来的你播下种子。而那
should go to savings, investments, and
应该用于储蓄、投资和
extra debt payments. And those are three
额外偿还债务。那是三个。
good numbers that I think everyone
我觉得这都是些好数字。
should know and understand as a good
应该了解并理解，作为一个好人。
starting point to try and benchmark your
以此为起点，尝试进行基准测试
numbers or your income against those
数字或你的收入与这些
spending categories. I would say however
消费类别。不过我想说的是……
if you are someone who's living closer
如果你是住在附近的人
to paycheck to paycheck
月光族
&gt;&gt; those numbers might look slightly
这些数字看起来可能略微
different and it might be that you're
不同，也许你是
you want to dial down that fund
你想减少那笔资金
percentage to have enough saved over for
达到一定比例，有足够的储蓄
the future you so you can continue
未来的你，这样你才能继续
contributing to your savings investments
为您的储蓄投资做出贡献
or if you're finding that your housing
或者如果你发现你的住房
and mortgaging is higher than 80 90%
抵押贷款比例高于 80% 至 90%。
start with when it comes to future you
首先，谈到未来的你
start with what you can whether it's
先从你能做到的事情开始，无论是什么
saving 2% 3% % start somewhere. You just
节省 2% 3% % 从某个地方开始。你只是
want to build that habit.
想养成这个习惯。
&gt;&gt; And in terms of spending, should I, you
至于支出方面，我应该……
mentioned cars earlier and we talked
之前提到过车，我们也聊过。
about houses briefly. Should I be buying
简要介绍房屋。我应该买吗？
a car? Should I be leasing a car?
一辆车？我应该租车吗？
&gt;&gt; A car is, let me just say, it's one of
汽车，这么说吧，是其中之一。
the two areas that most people
大多数人关注的两个领域
overspend.
超支。
And it's because we don't just buy the
这是因为我们不仅仅购买
numbers. We buy the emotions of the car.
数字。我们购买的是汽车带给我们的情感。
How the car might make us feel, how
这辆车会给我们带来怎样的感受？
we'll look like in the car, the family
我们坐在车里的样子，就像一家人一样。
memories we'll create in the car.
我们将在车里创造的回忆。
And I know cuz I did this when I um
我知道，因为我以前做过这件事。
got my first job. The very first thing I
我找到第一份工作了。我做的第一件事
did was upgrade my car. I went into a
我只是升级了我的车。我走进了
car showroom, found a car that I thought
在汽车展厅里，我找到了一辆我心仪的车。
I'd look cool in, walked out with the
我穿上它看起来会很酷，然后走出去。
car an hour later, drove out with the
一小时后，我开车离开了。
car, and didn't run my numbers, didn't
车，而且没算我的账，没算
check if I could afford the monthly
检查一下我是否能负担得起每月的费用。
payments, and for the next couple of
付款，以及接下来的几个月
months was figuring out how I was going
几个月的时间我都在琢磨自己该如何前进。
to make the rest of my finances meet.
为了维持我其他方面的财务平衡。
And car dealerships know this. So they
汽车经销商也深知这一点。所以他们
will manipulate the monthly payments in
将调整每月付款金额
a way that makes you buy more car than
一种让你买更多车的方法
you can afford. And if you don't
你负担得起。如果你不这样做的话
understand how the numbers work, this is
理解数字是如何运作的，这才是最重要的。
probably one of the
可能是其中之一
quickest ways to destroy your chance of
最快毁掉你机会的方法
building real wealth. The way I
积累真正的财富。我的方式
recommend buying a car is to buy
建议买车就是买
something that's 3 to 5 years old
3到5年前的东西
straight.
直的。
And I say 3 to 5 years old because at
我说3到5岁是因为……
that point it's enough it's depreciated
这一点就足够了，它已经贬值了。
enough as someone else's expense and
作为别人的开销，这已经足够了。
won't depreciate as much during the time
在此期间贬值幅度不会那么大
that you have it. But if you are someone
你已经拥有了。但如果你是某人
who is wealthy and you don't mind taking
谁有钱，你也不介意拿走
that hit on the depreciation or you want
那会影响折旧吗？或者你想
a nice car every couple of years and you
每隔几年换辆好车，你
want to trade it in and you don't mind
想把它置换掉，你不介意吗？
that fact that it's not the best
事实上，它并不是最好的。
financial choice then lease. That's how
选择财务方案，然后选择租赁。就是这样
I think of the buy the lease situation.
我想到了购买租赁的情况。
Then you also want to think about how
那么你还需要考虑如何
much can you reasonably afford as a
作为一名……，你合理能负担得起多少？
monthly payment when it comes to um the
每月付款，嗯……
proportion of your income that you're
你收入中属于你的那部分
spending towards it.
投入资金。
&gt;&gt; So what do you do you buy new cars or do
所以你是买新车还是……
you
你
&gt;&gt; No, I actually at the moment it was more
不，实际上当时我更倾向于……
economical for me to get a taxi
对我来说，打车更经济实惠。
everywhere. So I don't have a car.
到处。所以我没有车。
&gt;&gt; So you've run the numbers and thought
所以你已经计算过数据并思考过了。
&gt;&gt; the amount I'm traveling away from home
我离家出差的次数
makes more sense just to
这样做更有意义
&gt;&gt; get a taxi an Uber every time. Yeah. I'm
每次都打车或叫优步。是的。我是
saving on the for me and
对我来说，这能省钱。
it makes sense for this point in my
就我目前的情况而言，这很有意义。
life. It might be in 5 years, 10 years
生活。可能是5年，也可能是10年。
time that I want a nicer car and I don't
我想要一辆更好的车，但我没有
want to restrain myself from having it.
我想克制自己不去拥有它。
But for now with the numbers, I can use
但就目前这些数字而言，我可以……
that num that amount somewhere else.
那个数字代表了其他地方的那个金额。
&gt;&gt; What about other things we spend money
那么我们花钱的其他东西呢？
on? Where are the big sort of traps in
在？哪里有大型陷阱？
spending that that we haven't mentioned?
还有哪些我们没提到的开支？
So we talked about cars, talked about
于是我们聊了汽车，聊了……
houses. What about uh iPhones and iPads
房屋。那么，iPhone 和 iPad 呢？
and technology?
还有科技？
&gt;&gt; I think there's traps in spending in
我认为消费中存在陷阱。
almost everything that we do that we
我们所做的几乎每一件事
don't even see. going to a grocery shop,
根本看不见。去杂货店购物，
which is a fundamental living cost for
这是基本的生活成本
everyone. You're fighting against
每个人。你正在与……作战
marketing to keep your money in your
营销手段让你的钱留在你身边
pocket. You walk to a shop, a grocery
口袋。你步行去商店，一家杂货店。
store, they have the eggs, the milk, the
商店里有鸡蛋、牛奶等等。
bread right at the back, which makes you
面包就在最后面，这让你
walk through the the shop to get there.
穿过商店就能到达那里。
They have the premium products eye
他们拥有高端产品的眼光
level,
等级，
the sweets for the kids at the kids eye
儿童眼中的糖果
level. So these are also areas where you
等级。所以这些也是你需要关注的领域。
don't even realize that you're
你甚至没有意识到自己
overspending because there's these
过度消费是因为有这些
subliminal marketing messages around
潜意识营销信息
you.
你。
&gt;&gt; Mh.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; So that's one area where people spend
所以这是人们花费时间的一个领域。
where it's just like spending on the
就像花钱一样
necessities but not even realizing that
必需品，却甚至没有意识到这一点
there's a way to
有一种方法
um save there.
嗯，保存在那里。
&gt;&gt; So what you suggest going in going into
所以你建议进入什么阶段
those supermarkets with a shopping list?
那些需要购物清单的超市？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I mean that's one way shop going
是啊，我的意思是，那条路走不通了。
into going into the going into the
进入进入进入
supermarkets with shopping list. Also
带着购物清单去超市。还
checking if you're shopping at the
检查你是否正在购物
cheapest supermarket near you. I mean,
离你最近的最便宜的超市。我是说，
shopping at M&amp;S and Waitro is different
在玛莎百货和维特罗购物的感觉截然不同。
to shopping at Audi if that's where you
如果你在奥迪购物的话，那就去那里吧
want to save your money and you're more
想省钱，而且你更……
paycheck to paycheck and you're thinking
你靠工资勉强维持生计，你正在想……
about where where to save your money.
关于如何省钱。
Other areas where people overspend is
人们过度消费的其他领域包括：
everything now can be bought as an
现在所有东西都可以买到
impulse buy. You could buy now pay
冲动消费。您可以现在购买并付款
later. There's Apple Pay on your phone.
之后。你的手机上有Apple Pay。
There's so many debt financing methods
债务融资方式有很多种。
that make you pay more. And so just
那会让你付出更多。所以就这样
understanding
理解
running this budget, running these
执行这项预算，执行这些
numbers, understanding what you actually
数字，理解你实际拥有的东西
have available to spend towards these
可用于支付这些费用
things is a really good way of fighting
这是一种非常好的对抗方式。
against everything else that is trying
对抗其他一切试图
to take your money away from you.
把你的钱拿走。
&gt;&gt; What about like iPhones and iPads and
像iPhone和iPad之类的设备呢？
stuff like that? Do you think people
诸如此类的事情？你认为人们
should be getting new ones or
应该换新的了，或者
&gt;&gt; The way I think about this is the law of
我的想法是这样的：
diminishing returns. When you first get
收益递减。当你第一次……
something, there's a really big impact
某件事，影响真的很大。
on your happiness. When you first get
关于你的幸福。当你第一次……
like an iPhone and you don't have an
比如你有一个iPhone，但你没有
iPhone, that's good. That's big. You're
iPhone，那不错。那可是件大事。你是
like walking around your iPhone, this is
就像拿着你的iPhone四处走动一样，这
pretty cool. Then with every upgrade,
挺酷的。然后每次升级时，
that diminishing return starts to
收益递减开始
plateau.
高原。
&gt;&gt; It's not as exciting. So actually
没那么令人兴奋。所以实际上
thinking about, do I need the next
我在想，我是否需要下一个
upgrade or is that something I could
升级吗？或者这是我可以做的吗？
pass up on? But always remembering that
错过？但要始终记住这一点
the first time you buy something is
你第一次购买某件东西是
worth it. The upgrades after that, the
值得。此后的升级，
happiness doesn't increase as much.
幸福感并没有显著提升。
And what about hair, nails,
那么头发、指甲呢？
dying your hair, and all those kinds of
染发，以及所有类似的
things? Do you think people should be
事物？你认为人们应该
trying to sacrifice those kinds of
试图牺牲那些
things as well? Or
还有其他事情吗？或者
&gt;&gt; I'm not in this camp of trying to save
我并不属于试图拯救这一阵营。
money on everything. I really do believe
所有东西都要花钱。我真的相信
that you should have a percentage that
你应该有一定比例
you allocate towards the fun things in
你把钱花在娱乐活动上
your life and not being restrictive
你的生活，而不是被限制。
about what it is that you love. If it is
关于你所热爱的事物。如果是
getting your nails done, getting your
去做美甲，去做
hair done, getting a new bag, go for it.
头发弄好了，买了新包，就这么定了。
Enjoy it. as long as on the other side
好好享受。只要在另一边
that's not at the opportunity cost of
那并非以机会成本为代价的
you in five years or you in 10 years
五年后的你或十年后的你
&gt;&gt; because you talk about this term
因为你谈到了这个术语
lifestyle inflation.
生活方式膨胀。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Which I've never heard before. What is
我以前从未听说过。什么是
lifestyle inflation?
生活方式膨胀？
Lifestyle inflation is when as your
生活方式膨胀是指当你的生活方式膨胀时，你的
income increases, your spending also
收入增加，你的支出也会增加。
increases in a way that you think might
以你认为可能的方式增加
be necessary, but actually they are all
可能是必要的，但实际上它们都是必要的。
necessities being hidden away as just
必需品被藏起来，就像……
upgrades and luxuries. It's essentially
升级和豪华配置。它本质上是
your spending rising at the same place
你的支出在同一地点增加。
that your income is increasing. And what
你的收入正在增加。还有什么
you want to do to counteract lifestyle
你想做些什么来抵消这种生活方式的影响
inflation is you want to make sure that
通货膨胀是你想确保的。
your spending increases. Sure, you want
你的支出增加了。当然，你想
to treat yourself. You want to reward
犒劳一下自己。你想奖励
yourself, but not at the same pace that
你自己，但速度不能跟别人一样。
your income increases. You want to make
你的收入增加了。你想制作
sure that the gap between your income
确保你的收入差距
and your spending is getting wider as
而且你的支出范围越来越广
you earn more money, not narrower.
你赚的钱更多了，而不是更少。
&gt;&gt; What's the best way for someone to track
追踪的最佳方式是什么？
their money? Because there's lots of
他们的钱？因为有很多
figures here. Some people aren't
此处填写数字。有些人不是
mathematically literate.
具备数学素养。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Um, many people don't want to be in
嗯，很多人都不想参与其中。
Excel documents. Are there simple tools
Excel文档。有没有简单的工具
or an app that I could use to track my
或者一款我可以用来追踪我的应用程序
spending and saving and income?
支出、储蓄和收入？
&gt;&gt; So many bank accounts nowadays have
如今很多银行账户都有
categorized spending within them
对它们内部的支出进行分类
&gt;&gt; and it will tell you what you're
它会告诉你你是什么
spending and what you're spending on. So
支出以及你的钱都花在了哪里。所以
if you are someone that even me, I don't
如果你是连我这样的人，我也不认同。
sit every single month and
每个月都要坐一次
track every single transaction, but I do
我会追踪每一笔交易，但我确实会这样做。
have a ballpark figure in my mind based
我心中有一个大致的数字。
on my banking apps about what I'm
我的银行应用程序上显示着我的信息
spending and where. And the key isn't,
消费地点及消费方式。关键不在于……
oh, should I be allocating this much
哦，我应该分配这么多钱吗？
here? I've over spent here. Oh, I spent
这里？我在这里花钱太多了。哦，我花了
a little bit more on my trip than I
我的旅行比我想象的要多一些。
needed to. The key is, are you saving
需要。关键在于，你是否在储蓄
10% minimum of your salary? Whatever you
至少拿出你工资的10%？无论你
decide to do with everything else,
决定如何处理其他所有事情，
that's up to you.
那取决于你。
&gt;&gt; And when you think about it that way,
当你这样想的时候，
you think of this whole budgeting,
你想想整个预算编制过程，
managing finances is a lot more freeing
理财让人感觉轻松自在得多。
than something that's restricting you.
而不是限制你的事物。
If you're someone who doesn't want to
如果你是那种不想……的人
sit in the spreadsheets, spit in the
坐在电子表格里，往里面吐口水
numbers, just think, what am I saving
数字，想想，我到底在节省什么
and what am I spending? Am I sp saving
我的开销都花在了哪些地方？我是否正在节省
the right percentage? Cool. Doesn't
合适的百分比？凉爽的。不
matter how I'm allocating the rest.
无论我如何分配剩余的资金。
That's what I recommend for those
这就是我对那些人的建议。
people.
人们。
&gt;&gt; Oh, they're like budget trackers that
哦，它们就像预算追踪器一样。
are already built that I can use
已经构建好，我可以使用它
because, you know, my bank might tell me
因为，你知道，我的银行可能会告诉我
how much I'm spending, but it doesn't
我不知道自己花了多少钱，但它却不显示。
necessarily
一定
doesn't necessarily inform me in real
这并不一定能告诉我真实情况。
time of how much money I have left.
看看我身上还剩多少钱。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I mean, I have a budget tracker
是的。我的意思是，我有一个预算跟踪器
which actually tells you in real time.
它实际上可以实时告诉你。
It's not connected to your bank
它与您的银行无关。
accounts, but when you put your numbers
账户，但当你输入你的数字时
into it, it will tell you what you have
输入进去，它会告诉你你拥有什么
left to spend for the remaining of the
剩下的钱用来支付剩余的
month.
月。
&gt;&gt; And what is that? Is that an Excel
那是什么？那是Excel吗？
document?
文档？
&gt;&gt; It is an Excel document. Yeah.
这是一个Excel文档。是的。
&gt;&gt; Can I have your Excel document?
我可以看一下你的Excel文档吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, sure. I
当然可以。我
&gt;&gt; I'll link it below so people can use it
我会在下面附上链接，方便大家使用。
if they want to use it.
如果他们想用的话。
&gt;&gt; What about um money and love and how
那么，金钱、爱情以及其他方面呢？
these two worlds collide? Because I I
这两个世界碰撞了吗？因为我
was speaking to Kevin Olri recently on
最近和凯文·奥尔里谈过这件事
the show and he was telling me that one
节目里，他跟我说了那件事。
of the reasons people end up in divorce
导致离婚的原因
is because of financial insecurities and
这是由于经济上的不安全感造成的；
pain and friction and arguments. Do you
痛苦、摩擦和争吵。你
get a lot of messages from people about
收到很多人的信息，关于
money, love, joint bank accounts and all
金钱、爱情、联名银行账户以及所有
these kinds of things? I have a lot of
这类事情？我有很多
questions about from people asking
人们提出的问题
firstly how to
首先如何
bring up the conversation of money and
提起关于金钱的话题
secondly how to manage their finances
其次，他们如何管理自己的财务？
with a partner in a way that keeps the
与伴侣以一种保持……的方式
autonomy but still makes it feel like
自主性，但仍然让人感觉
you have a shared life.
你们共同生活。
&gt;&gt; What are those big questions
那些大问题是什么？
&gt;&gt; when it comes to how to bring up a
至于如何提起一个
conversation? Yeah, I guess with your
对话？是啊，我想和你
partner. This is really important
伙伴。这非常重要
because the top two reasons why people
因为人们选择这个原因的前两个主要原因就是
argue or why couples argue is money and
夫妻争吵的原因，或者说夫妻争吵的原因，是金钱。
sex. And when it comes to money, it's
性别。而说到金钱，那就是
lack of transparency, lack of openness,
缺乏透明度，缺乏开放性
and lack of shared goals together.
以及缺乏共同目标。
And that's not to say, yeah, you should
但这并不意味着，是的，你应该
go on a first date and ask someone what
第一次约会时问对方什么
their credit score or debt utilization
他们的信用评分或债务利用率
is. But it is to say having those
是。但也就是说，拥有这些
conversations, asking the right
对话，提出正确的问题
questions in a way that can help you
以有助于你的方式提出问题
understand someone else's money beliefs
了解他人的金钱观
in a way that can
以一种可以的方式
help you create a financial life
帮助你创造财务生活
together.
一起。
&gt;&gt; So, what should I be asking my partner?
那么，我应该问我的伴侣什么问题呢？
I'm your partner. Okay.
我是你的搭档。好的。
&gt;&gt; What do you what do you say to me and
你跟我说什么？
when do you say it?
你什么时候说？
&gt;&gt; I think there's levels of the questions
我认为这些问题是有层次的。
that you could ask someone. Mhm.
你可以问问别人。嗯。
&gt;&gt; And if you're just getting to know
如果你刚刚开始了解
someone, you can ask them something
你可以问某人一些问题
along the lines of if you found or if
类似于如果你发现或如果
you won 10,000 tomorrow, how would you
如果你明天赢了10000块，你会怎么做？
spend it?
花掉它吗？
&gt;&gt; Lamborghini.
兰博基尼。
&gt;&gt; That will tell you a lot about what they
这将告诉你很多关于他们的信息。
value. So then that that automatically
价值。所以，那样就自动生效了。
tells you that they probably value
这说明他们可能很看重
status.
地位。
&gt;&gt; If you say, "Oh, I'll probably save it."
如果你说：“哦，我可能会保存它。”
&gt;&gt; If I said Lamborghini, I'm going to rent
如果我说兰博基尼，我就打算租一辆。
a Lamborghini for for two months.
一辆兰博基尼，租了两个月。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; What should you then do about that? You
那么你应该怎么做呢？你
take that information and you understand
记住这些信息，你就能明白了。
this is what the person values. Yeah.
这是这个人所珍视的东西。是的。
&gt;&gt; Because money is just a symbol for what
因为金钱只是某种东西的象征。
the person values and if they if they
这个人重视什么，以及如果他们重视什么
want to spend it on a Lamborghini that's
想把钱花在一辆兰博基尼上。
not to say you should then judge the way
并不是说你应该因此就评判这种方式。
they're spending but you take that
他们花钱了，但你得接受这一点。
information you understand what do you
你理解的信息是什么？
want to do with it. Is this
想用它做什么。这是什么？
way of thinking something that you want
你想要的那种想法
to have a life with?
共度一生？
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
Is there is there a good answer to that
这个问题有好的答案吗？
question? M
问题？ M
&gt;&gt; I think it comes down to understanding
我认为关键在于理解
because even if someone says I just want
因为即使有人说我只想
to save
保存
&gt;&gt; you might think okay this is great it's
你可能会想，好吧，这太棒了。
stability security but you might be
稳定性和安全性，但你可能会……
someone who wants experiences you want
想要体验你所渴望的经历的人
to spend on flights to take your friends
花钱买机票带朋友去旅行
and family away around the world
以及远在世界各地的家人
&gt;&gt; so it's just about understanding how
所以关键在于理解如何
your money values fit in with their
你的金钱价值观与他们一致
money values and are they completely in
货币价值，它们是否完全符合
conflict with each other or are they
它们之间是否存在冲突？或者它们之间是否存在冲突？
actually do they marry up and can you
他们真的会结婚吗？你能吗？
see yourselves creating a financial life
想象一下自己创造财务生活的样子
together because if someone's like oh
在一起，因为如果有人说“哦”
I'll spend all my money on
我会把所有的钱都花在……
like status symbols and not save
就像身份象征一样，而不是保存
anything and you're a saver, that is
任何东西，你都是个省钱的人。
going to be a cause for arguments.
这将引发争论。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Especially if uh you get bad news
是的。尤其是如果你收到坏消息的话
&gt;&gt; and things get tight. You know, someone
情况变得很紧张。你知道，某人
loses their job and then when things get
他们失去了工作，然后当事情变得
tight, you're really going to be focused
紧张起来，你真的会非常专注。
on the money or you have kids and you
要么你付钱，要么你有孩子，然后你
know any sort of pressure on the budget.
了解预算方面的任何压力。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. and like other questions and
确切地。和其他问题一样
that those kind of questions come down
这类问题最终都会落到我们头上。
further further down the line actually I
实际上，再往后走一点，我
guess as well when it comes to financial
在金融方面，我也猜对了。
goal setting but I guess another
设定目标，但我想还有另一种可能。
question you could ask someone is and it
你可以问别人的问题是，而且
comes back to what we spoke about at the
又回到了我们之前讨论的内容……
start of the podcast is where did your
播客的开头是你的……
beliefs about money come from
关于金钱的信念源于
because so much of the way we think
因为我们思考方式的很多方面都受到了影响。
about money is inherited through what we
关于金钱的继承是通过我们……
saw our parents do what we saw during
我们看到父母做了我们在……期间看到的事情
our upbringings and it has an impact on
我们的成长经历，以及它对……的影响
the way we are with money it might be
我们对待金钱的方式或许是
that we're an impulse spender as a
我们都是冲动型消费者。
result of it might be that we see debt
结果可能是我们会看到债务。
in a certain way. It might be that we're
在某种程度上。或许我们是
really frugal. But what that does is it
非常节俭。但这样做的好处是……
opens up a conversation of empathy and
开启关于同理心的对话，
compassion rather than judgment. And
以同情代替评判。和
that automatically can lead to more
这自然会导致更多
conversations about okay, how do you
关于“好吧，你怎么做？”的对话
view debt? How can we manage our
查看债务？我们如何管理我们的
finances
财政
based on your views and my views and how
基于你我的观点，以及如何
can we work together as a whole to make
我们能否作为一个整体共同努力，实现
this sustainable? And then the the next
这可持续吗？然后是下一个
question is when it comes to family and
问题是，当涉及到家庭和……时
kids and how you're going to manage your
孩子以及你打算如何管理你的
finances there. That's when it comes to
那里的财务状况。这时就涉及到了
like the third layer of questions where
就像第三层问题一样
you ask asking someone what does our
你问别人我们的是什么
2year, 5year, 10 year goal look like?
2年、5年、10年的目标是什么？
And if we were to merge our finances
如果我们合并财务……
together, what would that look like?
如果结合起来，会是什么样子？
&gt;&gt; Should we merge our finances together?
我们应该合并财务吗？
Nisha,
妮莎，
&gt;&gt; my straight answer to this is no. We
我的直接回答是：不。我们
have very unique individual money
拥有非常独特的个人资金
personalities and habits and we are
性格和习惯，我们
getting married later in life where
晚婚
these personalities are really set in
这些性格确实根深蒂固
stone.
石头。
And you know how they say opposites
你知道他们怎么说相反的说法吗？
attract in a relationship. The same goes
在恋爱关系中相互吸引。情况也是如此。
with money. Savers typically attract
用钱。储户通常会吸引
spenders and spenders typically attract
消费者通常会吸引
savers.
储蓄者。
So if you have a saver saving and then a
所以，如果你有一个储蓄账户，然后……
spender who's spending the savings,
花光积蓄的消费者
that's going to be a cause for arguments
那将会引发争论。
regardless of if there's financial
无论是否存在经济损失
shortcomings. Mhm.
缺点。嗯。
&gt;&gt; So, what I recommend is having a team
所以我建议组建一个团队。
fund and then a Mi fund.
基金，然后是小米基金。
Team fund is for the grown-up adult
团队基金是为成年人设立的
stuff, the joint expenses, mortgage,
杂项开支、共同支出、房贷
rent, bills, council tax. And this isn't
房租、账单、市政税。但这并非如此。
50/50. You both pay into that
五五开。你们俩都为此付出了代价。
proportionate of your income. 90% of
与你的收入成比例。 90%
your household income that you're
你的家庭收入是多少？
making. You pay 90% of the expenses.
制作。你承担90%的费用。
You're bringing in 30% of the household
你带来了家庭收入的30%。
income. You're paying for 30% of the
收入。你支付了30%的费用
expenses.
开支。
That's a team fund. And then you have
那是团队基金。然后你就有
the MI fund. And this is for your own
MI基金。这是为了你自己。
individual personality to stay alive.
个性是生存的根本。
Your own money habits. No one else can
你自身的理财习惯。其他人都做不到
see the way you're spending here. If you
看看你在这里都怎么花钱。如果你
have a match addiction, go for it. If
如果你有火柴瘾，那就去吧。如果
you want to buy that nice watch, go for
你想买那款漂亮的手表，那就去买吧
it. You can do whatever you want. Spend
它。你想做什么都可以。花费
this money however you want. If you want
这笔钱你想怎么花都行。如果你想
to save it, save it. But that way,
为了保存它，就保存它。但那样的话，
you're creating that
你正在创造那个
unity, but also having that autonomy.
团结，但也要拥有自主权。
And I think this is really, really
我觉得这真的非常
important for both parties, women and
对双方而言，女性和
men, but specifically for women. They
男性，但特指女性。他们
want to, you want them to have their
你想让他们拥有他们的
independent access to their finances.
能够独立支配自己的财务。
And I've seen situations, I've spoken to
我见过一些情况，也和一些人交谈过。
people who have merged their finances,
合并财务的人们，
and
和
it's when the relationship has turned
当这段关系发生转变时
sour unsafe. They haven't been able to
酸的，不安全的。他们一直未能……
know what to do because they haven't had
他们不知道该怎么做，因为他们没有……
the independent access to their money.
他们能够独立支配自己的资金。
&gt;&gt; Do you think people should be getting
你认为人们应该得到
prenups?
婚前协议？
&gt;&gt; Did you get You're married, aren't you?
你收到“你已经结婚了，对吧？”这句话了吗？
&gt;&gt; I am. I think everyone has a prenup
我是。我认为每个人都签了婚前协议。
whether you know it or not.
无论你是否知道。
Prenups, you could either have your
婚前协议，你可以选择……
own customized prenup.
自行定制婚前协议。
&gt;&gt; Mhm. Or you could have what the state is
嗯。或者你可以了解一下该州的情况。
telling you as what's going to happen if
告诉你如果……将会发生什么
you decide to go your separate ways.
你们决定分道扬镳。
Depending on where you are, the prenup
根据你所在地区的规定，婚前协议可能适用。
holds different values. So some areas
具有不同的价值。所以有些地区
might not look beyond what the couple
可能不会考虑这对夫妇之外的事情。
agree and they just say, "Okay, this is
他们同意了，然后说：“好的，这是……”
what the couple's agreed. this is how
这对夫妇达成的共识。就是这样
the finances are going to be split or
财务状况将被分割或
the assets are going to be split in the
这些资产将被分割。
UK and I'm not a divorce lawyer or
英国人，我不是离婚律师，
anything. I don't believe that the
任何事物。我不相信
prenup is fully legally binding.
婚前协议具有完全的法律约束力。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; So, it's useful to have in some
所以，在某些情况下，拥有它是有用的。
circumstances, but it's the courts will
具体情况如何，最终由法院决定。
still look past it and see what is fair
还是应该抛开这些，看看什么是公平的。
as a couple.
作为一对伴侣。
&gt;&gt; This term passive income is quite a
“被动收入”这个词相当……
popular term.
常用词。
&gt;&gt; What is passive income? The way I see
什么是被动收入？在我看来
passive income, it's money that you do
被动收入，就是你通过努力赚到的钱。
not have to work
不必工作
or to invest time in to make. And in all
或者投入时间去制作。在所有
honesty, I think the word passive income
说实话，我认为“被动收入”这个词很贴切。
gets thrown around a lot and people
经常被提及，而且人们
forget that
忘了这件事吧
the things that you do see that might be
你看到的那些东西可能是
passive income streams required a lot of
被动收入来源需要很多
work upfront to start with. What are
先做好前期准备工作。什么是
some passive income ideas that you think
你觉得有哪些被动收入的好点子？
some people could pursue? Like the the
有些人可能会追求？就像
average person could potentially pursue
普通人可能追求
on top of their their 9 toive job?
除了他们那九份工作之外？
&gt;&gt; I would go back to the easiest way for
我会选择最简单的方法。
someone to pursue passive income is
追求被动收入的人
through investing
通过投资
&gt;&gt; from like the S&amp;P 500 and stuff like
比如标普500指数之类的
that.
那。
&gt;&gt; That is the easiest way if you want to.
如果你想的话，这是最简单的方法。
Everything else and this is how I see
其他一切，这就是我的看法。
it. Everything else requires some level
它。其他一切都需要一定程度的
of time or energy because you could
耗费时间或精力，因为你可以
increase your income through a couple of
通过以下几种方式增加你的收入：
avenues if that's what you're looking to
如果您正在寻找这样的途径，那么可以考虑以下几种。
do. You can, like we spoke about, ask
做。就像我们之前谈到的那样，你可以问
for a pay rise at work. You can, if
争取加薪。你可以，如果
that's not available to you, set up side
那对你来说不可用，设置边
businesses
企业
&gt;&gt; to increase your income. And there's two
增加你的收入。而且还有两台。
ways to do that. There's the tapand go
实现这一目标的方法。有点击即走功能
that I like to call it, and it's ways to
我喜欢这样称呼它，以及它的几种方式
increase your income that you can do
增加你的收入，你可以这样做
immediately. This isn't passive. This is
立即地。这不是被动的。这是
things like putting a spare room on
比如把空房间放在那里
Airbnb or um an dog walking or Ubering.
Airbnb，或者遛狗，或者叫优步。
They require your time. M
他们需要你花费时间。 M
&gt;&gt; for money, but they are immediate. The
虽然是为了钱，但它们立竿见影。这
downside is there is a cap to how much
缺点是金额有上限。
you could earn because it's not leaning
你可以赚钱，因为它不倾斜
into your unique advantages, your market
发挥你的独特优势，开拓你的市场
advantage, your unique selling points.
优势，你的独特卖点。
The other side is value and skill-based
另一方则基于价值和技能。
income. And this is where you lean into
收入。而这正是你要靠近的地方。
your individuality, your unique selling
你的个性，你的独特卖点
point. You tap into your skills and you
观点。你发挥自己的技能，然后
create businesses around that that can
围绕这一点创建可以……的企业
scale. The downside with that, even if
规模。即使如此，缺点也依然存在。
it is passive, say if you want to create
它是被动的，比如说，如果你想创建
um content and then through that sell
嗯，内容，然后通过销售
products which you could then earn
您随后可以赚取的产品
passively with that kind of income
被动地依靠这种收入
stream, there's always it always takes
直播，总是有的，总是需要
longer to make that money. And there's a
赚这笔钱需要更长时间。而且还有
time period where you are putting in
您正在投入的时间段
more time or even more money before you
在你花费更多时间甚至更多金钱之前
start earning that. So when I talk about
开始挣钱吧。所以当我谈到
passive income, that's when I say sure,
被动收入的话，我当然会说好。
there are avenues for passive income,
存在获得被动收入的途径，
but the easiest one that's accessible to
但最简单易行的方法是……
everyone is investing. Everything else
人人都在投资。其他一切
does require some upfront time or
确实需要一些前期时间或
energy.
活力。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I was we obviously we were talking
是的。当时我们显然在聊天
before we started recording about
在我们开始录制之前
Standtore, which is a company I've
Standtore，一家我曾就职的公司。
become a co-owner in, and that business
成为该企业的共同所有人
allows you to sell digital products
允许您销售数字产品
online. And we did this 30-day challenge
在线的。我们完成了这项为期 30 天的挑战。
and I was looking through the results of
我正在查看结果……
how much money people had made and also
人们赚了多少钱，以及其他方面
how much how much of a following they
他们有多少粉丝？
had because I think digital products are
之所以有，是因为我认为数字产品是
really like interesting entrepreneurial
非常喜欢有趣的创业精神
opportunity. And there was this one, I
机会。还有这个，我
was going through all of them yesterday
昨天把它们全都看完了
over in the studio and there was like so
录音棚那边，当时的情况是这样的……
many people, but there's this one that
很多人都这样，但有一个人……
stood in mind because she had a thousand
她之所以一直记在心里，是因为她有千个
followers and she's helping women to get
她拥有众多粉丝，并且正在帮助女性获得
control of binge eating and other sort
控制暴食症和其他类型的
of eating disorders by selling like
通过销售类似产品来治疗饮食失调症
digital products and information and
数字产品和信息以及
really like a community. She had like a
真的很喜欢社区氛围。她就像……
thousand followers or something. And in
一千个粉丝什么的。并且
the last 30 days, she's made4 or 5,000
过去30天里，她赚了4000到5000美元。
doing that. She sold like 40 like
这样做。她卖出了大约40份。
digital products and like basically PDFs
数字产品，例如PDF文件
and stuff like that. I just thought this
诸如此类的事情。我刚才想到了这一点
is a massive untapped opportunity for
这是一个尚未开发的巨大机遇
the vast majority of people who have
绝大多数人
spent 10 years, 20 years in a career and
在职业生涯中花费了10年、20年的时间，
know something, have some kind of
知道一些事情，具备某种能力
expertise.
专业知识。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Using what you've learning through
是的。运用你通过以下途径学到的知识
your day job and turning it into a
把你的日常工作变成
business on the side that can be
副业
scalable.
可扩展的。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Not necessarily through creating
不一定是通过创造
content, which is what I think a lot of
内容，这正是我认为很多方面所在。
people think that they need to do. Mhm.
人们认为他们需要这样做。嗯。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; I imagine like everybody knows something
我想大概每个人都知道些什么吧。
and there's a demand now for people to
现在对人们有需求
buy that expertise that you know if
购买你所了解的专业知识
especially if you've been in the working
尤其是如果你一直在工作的话
world for like a couple of years.
世界大概持续了两年。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I'd say if you want to figure out
是的。我想说，如果你想弄清楚
what it is that that expertise is for
这种专业知识的用途是什么？
you cuz sometimes we're sitting on a
你，因为有时候我们坐在……
mountain of knowledge but we don't even
我们拥有海量的知识，但我们甚至都不知道。
know it until we kind of take a step
直到我们采取某种行动，我们才会明白。
back and then look to see what that
回去看看那是什么
thing is. Ask your friends what is it
问题是……问问你的朋友那是什么
that you'd come to me for advice on?
你会来向我寻求建议的那件事？
Because I know I have people in my life
因为我知道我生命中还有人陪伴着我。
who I go to for advice on specific areas
我会在特定领域向谁寻求建议
or if I want planning for an event, hey,
或者如果我想要活动策划，嘿，
what should I do? How should I do this?
我应该怎么办？我该怎么做？
&gt;&gt; If I need help with Excel, hey, can you
如果我需要Excel方面的帮助，嘿，你能帮帮我吗？
help me with this formula? If I've got
请帮我解答一下这个公式？如果我有
back pain,
背痛
&gt;&gt; just a quick message or WhatsApp to
只需发个短信或WhatsApp消息即可
someone saying, hey, what can I do in
有人说，嘿，我能做什么？
this situation? Find out what are people
这种情况？了解人们是什么
coming to you for advice on. Mhm.
来向您请教一些问题。嗯。
&gt;&gt; That kind of will give you a signal as
那种方式会给你一个信号，
to what people want to know about you,
人们想了解你的什么？
what people want to learn from you, and
人们想从你身上学到什么，以及
see if there's a way to turn that into
看看有没有办法把它变成
an income stream.
收入来源。
&gt;&gt; I mean, it's very much what you did.
我的意思是，这很大程度上是你做的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, it is exactly what I did. It's
是的，我就是这么做的。它是
turning the finance knowledge, which at
将金融知识转化为……
the time my tagline was sharing
我的标语是分享的那段时间
everything I know and I'm learning along
我所知道的一切，以及我正在学习的一切
the way to create a life that I love.
创造我所热爱的生活的方式。
And it was me kind of doing it as an
而我当时就是以这种身份去做这件事的。
online diary, sharing this is what I'm
在线日记，分享我的所见所闻
learning, this is what I'm doing. And
这就是我正在做的事情：学习。和
then it ultimately ended up into
然后最终变成了
something that I do full-time.
这是我全职从事的工作。
&gt;&gt; And that's changed your life in a pretty
这彻底改变了你的生活。
profound way.
深刻的方式。
&gt;&gt; I wouldn't be here if I if I didn't take
如果我不接受，我就不会在这里。
the bet.
打赌。
&gt;&gt; Every single one of you watching this
正在观看这段视频的各位，你们每一个人。
right now, has something to offer,
现在，它有一些东西可以提供，
whether it's knowledge or skills or
无论是知识还是技能，
experience. And that means you have
经验。这意味着你拥有
value. Stand, the platform I co-own, who
价值。 Stand，我共同拥有的平台，谁
are one of the sponsors of this podcast,
是本播客的赞助商之一，
turns your knowledge into a business
将你的知识转化为事业
through one single click. You can sell
只需轻轻一点。你可以卖
digital products, coaching, communities,
数字产品、辅导、社群
and you don't need any coding experience
而且你不需要任何编程经验
either. Just the drive to start. This is
任何一个。只需要启动车辆。这是
a business I really believe in. And
一家我真心看好的企业。
already $300 million has been earned by
目前已赚取 3 亿美元
creators, coaches, and entrepreneurs
创作者、教练和企业家
just like you have the potential to be
就像你也有成为……的潜力一样
on Stan's store. These are people who
在斯坦的商店里。这些人
didn't wait, who heard me saying things
没等，谁听到我说的话了
like this, and instead of
像这样，而不是
procrastinating, started building, then
拖延了一段时间，然后开始搭建，
launched something, and now they're
他们推出了一些东西，现在他们是
getting paid to do it. Stan is
做这件事还能获得报酬。斯坦是
incredibly simple and incredibly easy,
极其简单，极其容易
and you can link it with a Shopify store
您可以将其与 Shopify 商店关联。
that you're already using if you want
如果你愿意的话，你已经在使用你正在使用的东西了。
to. I'm on it and so is my girlfriend
到。我和我女朋友都在用。
and many of my team. So, if you want to
以及我的团队中的许多人。所以，如果你想
join, start by launching your own
加入，首先创建你自己的项目
business with a free 30-day trial. Visit
企业版提供 30 天免费试用。访问
stevenbartlet.stan.store
stevenbartlet.stan.store
and get yours set up within minutes.
几分钟内即可完成设置。
Whether you are a novice or you've been
无论你是新手还是经验丰富的玩家
in the tax and bookkeeping industry for
在税务和簿记行业
years, if you want to work with an
多年来，如果你想与一个
experienced team of professionals who
一支经验丰富的专业团队
are invested in your learning and
我们致力于你的学习，并且
growth, there's a real career
发展前景广阔，拥有真正的职业生涯。
opportunity with our sponsor, Intuit,
与我们的赞助商 Intuit 合作的机会
the maker of Turboax and QuickBooks.
Turboax 和 QuickBooks 的开发商。
Their self-paced training, Intuit
他们的自主学习培训，Intuit
Academy, presents you with a pathway to
学院为您提供了一条通往成功的道路
gain the necessary skills that you'll
获得必要的技能，你将
need to feel confident expanding your
需要有信心拓展你的
career within tax and bookkeeping. And
从事税务和簿记方面的工作。和
their team is extremely supportive, too,
他们的团队也给予了极大的支持。
with a large network of experienced,
拥有庞大的经验丰富的网络，
credentialed professionals right by your
就在您身边的认证专业人士
side as you learn and gain experience.
在学习和积累经验的过程中不断进步。
On top of all of this upskilling, they
除了这些技能提升之外，他们
also offer flexible working schedules,
也提供灵活的工作时间安排。
whether that's full-time, part-time,
无论是全职、兼职，
virtual, on-site, or even letting you
虚拟的、现场的，甚至让你
select your hours to grow at the pace
选择你的上课时间，按你的节奏成长
that you want to grow at. Intu is
你想在哪方面发展。 Intu 是
currently growing their network of tax
目前正在拓展他们的税务网络
and bookkeeping professionals. So if you
以及簿记专业人员。所以如果你
want to build a career with them on your
想和他们一起发展你的职业生涯
own terms, just head to
按照自己的方式，直接前往
intuitit.comexpert.
intuitit.com专家。
I'll put that on the screen. That's
我会把它显示在屏幕上。那是
intuitit.com/expert.
intuitit.com/expert。
Talk to me about that journey. Was it um
请你跟我谈谈那段经历。是吗？嗯……
was it faster than you expected? And was
比你预想的要快吗？是
it are you in a place that is higher
你身处一个更高的位置吗？
than you expected when you started?
比你最初预想的要好？
You've done 151 videos on YouTube.
你在 YouTube 上发布了 151 个视频。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And is it safe to say it's made
是的。可以肯定地说，它已经制造出来了。
you millions?
你拥有数百万美元吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
I would never have thought I was in the
我做梦也没想到自己会身处其中。
place that I am now
我现在所在的地方
through sitting in my spare bedroom and
我坐在空余的卧室里，
creating videos. Monday to Friday I'll
制作视频。周一至周五我将
be going to work glitz and glamour
去上班时光鲜亮丽
meeting clients. There was a kind of
会见客户。有一种
allure to it. And then the weekends I'll
它具有某种吸引力。然后周末我会
be spend spending in my spare bedroom
在我的空卧室里消磨时光
googling what's a-roll, what's B-roll,
在谷歌上搜索什么是A-roll，什么是B-roll，
how do I do color grading,
如何进行色彩分级？
&gt;&gt; which are all terms in terms of editing
这些都是编辑方面的术语。
videos.
视频。
&gt;&gt; It's all terms of editing videos cuz
这都是视频剪辑的术语，因为
that's what I was doing on my weekends
我周末就做这个。
and evenings
以及夜晚
&gt;&gt; while you were still at work.
当时你还在上班。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I quit my day job just over two
是的，我两年前辞掉了我的日常工作。
years ago. And so for a very long time,
几年前。因此，在很长一段时间里，
this was just a creative outlet for me
这只是我发挥创造力的一种方式。
and I loved it. I found so much
我非常喜欢。我发现了很多
interest in it, but my purpose for it
我对它感兴趣，但我的目的是什么？
really grew as the channel grew. It grew
随着频道的发展，我的事业也真正成长了。它生长
very quickly from 1,000 to 50,000 within
在很短的时间内，数量就从 1,000 增长到 50,000。
a few days and then 100,000 within a few
几天之内就达到了10万。
weeks of that. And as the channel grew,
这种情况持续了好几个星期。随着频道的发展，
I saw the comments that were coming in.
我看到了收到的评论。
Hey, I've just invested in this for the
嘿，我刚刚投资了这个
first time because of what you've said
这是第一次，因为你刚才说的话。
here or I've just asked for a pay rise
要么就在这里，要么我就直接要求加薪了。
at work because of this conversation.
因为这次谈话，我在工作中受到了影响。
And
和
when you see something like that come
当你看到类似的事情发生时
through, there is no amount of money
然而，无论多少钱都无济于事。
that can be made through a day job that
这可以通过一份日常工作来赚取，
beats that. There is nothing. What was
比那好多了。没有什么。是什么
previously external fulfillment for me
以前对我来说，外在的满足感才是最重要的。
turned into internal fulfillment. So, it
转化为内在的满足感。所以，它
has been the best thing I've done, hands
这是我做过的最好的事，双手。
down, and it is the thing that I would
下来，这是我会做的事。
continue to do, even if I wasn't making
即使我不赚钱，我也会继续这样做。
money from it.
从中获利。
&gt;&gt; You made one video seven months ago
你七个月前制作过一个视频。
about
关于
things you stop doing to waste your
你停止做的事情，是为了浪费你的
evenings after work. The video is
下班后的晚上。视频是
titled, "Five things I did to stop
标题为“我做的五件事来阻止
wasting my evenings after work."
下班后把晚上都浪费掉了。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
Because I had to be really disciplined
因为我必须非常自律。
with my time when I uh was working in
在我工作期间
banking.
银行业。
&gt;&gt; So, what is it what is the essence of
那么，它的本质是什么？
that video? Is it telling people to use
那个视频？它是在告诉人们使用
their their time as an asset more
他们的时间是一种更宝贵的资产。
effectively? And
有效地？和
&gt;&gt; so often we just are living in autopilot
我们常常只是生活在自动驾驶模式下。
mode. We don't even think about the time
模式。我们甚至都没考虑过时间。
that we're using and how we're using it.
我们正在使用它以及我们如何使用它。
We are just coming home after work and
我们刚下班回家
turning on the TV and watching Netflix
打开电视，看Netflix
and sinking into the couch because we've
然后瘫倒在沙发里，因为我们……
done that the day before and the day
前一天和当天都已完成。
before and it's comfortable.
之前就很舒服。
And the essence of that video is to say
这段视频的精髓在于：
there there's probably more out there.
可能还有更多。
If you're sitting there and you're in a
如果你坐在那里，而且你身处一个
place where you're thinking, I don't
你在想什么的地方，我没有
really like my job. I don't really like
我非常喜欢我的工作。我不太喜欢
what I'm doing. I'm not really happy. I
我正在做的事情。我不太高兴。我
want to meet new people, but I'm not
我想认识新朋友，但我不是。
doing that. Then this video is about
这样做。那么，这段视频是关于
saying, "Hey,
说：“嘿，
come out that autopilot mode that you
摆脱那种自动驾驶模式吧
might be in and you have hours maybe on
可能在里面，你可能有几个小时的时间。
the weekend, maybe in the evening that
周末，或许在晚上
you can use to create a better life for
你可以利用它来创造更美好的生活
yourself."
你自己。”
&gt;&gt; It's almost like budgeting your time.
这几乎就像是在规划你的时间。
&gt;&gt; It is budgeting your time. Exactly. That
这是合理安排时间。确切地。那
thinking about how you can spend each
思考如何支配每一分每一秒
hour in a way that brings you closer to
以一种让你更接近的方式度过一小时
the version of the life that you want. I
你想要的生活版本。我
think about that a lot because
多想想这件事，因为
ultimately our time is the center point
归根结底，我们所处的时代才是中心点。
of our influence. Like it's the thing
我们的影响力。就像是那件事
that's going to determine our long-term
这将决定我们的长期发展。
outcomes pretty much more than anything
结果比什么都重要。
else. Whether we spend it reading a book
别的。我们是否把时间花在读书上
that's going to educate us or learn how
这将使我们有所收获，或者让我们学会如何做。
to color grade for YouTube videos like
为 YouTube 视频进行调色
you did or whether we spend it, you
你做了还是我们没花掉，你
know, watching Love Island.
我知道，我在看《爱情岛》。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; On the TV or something like in the same
在电视上或者类似的地方，以同样的方式
way that that $100 is going to compound
那100美元将如何复利增长呢？
at 10% a year in the S&amp;P 500, that
标普500指数年收益率为10%，
choice is going to compound.
选择的影响会不断累积。
&gt;&gt; Like so let's play that out. So instead
好，那我们就来演练一下。所以，取而代之的是……
of watching Love Island, I decide to
在观看《爱情岛》之后，我决定
read that book you recommended about
读了你推荐的那本书。
money. And then that means that I make a
钱。这意味着我制作了一个
series of different decisions which
一系列不同的决定
change the trajectory of several areas
改变几个领域的发展轨迹
of my life. I maybe stop spending as
我生命中的一部分。我或许会停止消费
much. I start budgeting a little bit. I
很多。我开始做一些预算规划。我
go and educate myself in a new skill.
去学习一项新技能。
And if you zoom out on that as a graph
如果你把图表放大观察的话。
over like 10, 20, 30 years, you're in an
经过10年、20年、30年的时间，你就处于……
entirely different position because you
因为你的立场完全不同，所以你
used one hour differently 30 years ago,
30年前，一个小时的用法与现在不同。
but you'll like never see the return
但你可能永远也看不到回报。
because it's so compounding is so hard
因为复利效应太强了，所以很难叠加。
to see. It's invisible
查看。它是隐形的
&gt;&gt; in the moment. But
当下。但
&gt;&gt; yeah,
是的，
&gt;&gt; I really think about this a lot. I I try
我真的经常思考这个问题。我尝试
and remind myself on a frequent basis
并经常提醒自己
that like the actual currency I'm
就像我实际使用的货币一样
spending is these these hours that I
我把这些时间都花在了这些时间上。
have
有
&gt;&gt; and how intentional and wellplaced and
以及多么用心和巧妙的安排
aligned they are to my long-term goals
它们与我的长期目标一致
is maybe maybe the most important thing.
这或许是最重要的事。
&gt;&gt; And it's the most powerful thing that
而它最强大的地方在于……
you have.
你有。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; What about your happiness? What is um
你的幸福感呢？嗯是什么？
what makes you happy, Nisha?
妮莎，什么能让你感到快乐？
&gt;&gt; The way I'm living right now, which is
我现在的生活方式是
doing what I'm doing for a living is
我从事的这份工作是……
making me extremely happy. And it's the
这让我非常开心。而这正是
happiest I've been since starting a
这是我自开始……以来最快乐的时刻
career in banking.
银行业职业生涯。
&gt;&gt; It comes back to finding a meaning in a
归根结底，还是要从中寻找意义。
purpose in what you're doing. And to say
做事要有目的性。并且要说
that I make money from
我从中赚钱
helping people get better with their
帮助人们改善他们的
finances.
财政。
I don't think there there's stuff and
我不认为那里有东西，而且
you can't get much better than that. I
这已经非常好了。我
don't think there's many jobs in life
别以为人生中有很多工作机会。
that are more rewarding than giving back
比回馈社会更有意义的事情
in some way.
在某种程度上。
However that looks like for you through
然而，对你来说，这看起来是怎样的呢？
your own skills, your own
你自己的技能，你自己
expertise, your own unique selling
专业技能，您独特的销售策略
points.
积分。
I can't imagine a like a better place
我无法想象还有比这更好的地方。
for me myself to be in. And it's taken a
我自己也参与其中。这需要……
long time to get to that. But it's been
花了很长时间才达到这个目标。但一直以来都是如此
good. It's been a it's been a journey,
好的。这是一段漫长的旅程。
but it's it's been a good one.
但这确实是一次不错的经历。
&gt;&gt; AI is this, you know, the the topic of
人工智能就是这个话题，你知道的。
the moment because it's just impacting
此刻，因为它正在产生影响
everything. It's impacting people's
一切。它正在影响人们的
ability to get jobs. It's impacting how
获得工作的能力。它正在影响着……
I'm hiring as a employer. It's impacting
我以雇主身份招聘。它正在产生影响
how I do my creative work and even me as
我如何进行我的创作工作，甚至我自己
a podcaster as well. I was wondering if
他也是一名播客主播。我想知道是否
you what you're doing, how you're
你知道你在做什么，你怎么样
thinking about AI.
思考人工智能。
&gt;&gt; I'm seeing more and more people leaning
我看到越来越多的人倾向于
into AI to get money tips and money
利用人工智能获取赚钱秘诀和资金
advice. Mhm.
建议。嗯。
&gt;&gt; And I think that's great because it's
我认为这很好，因为……
everything's at the expertise. If you're
一切都取决于专业知识。如果你是
looking at what was available 20 years
回顾20年前的可用资源。
ago versus what was available 5 years
与五年前的情况相比
ago versus what was available a year ago
与一年前的情况相比
to what is available now, there's so
就目前的情况而言，有很多……
much more information that is vastly
更多信息，这非常……
available at your fingertips for you to
触手可及，供您使用
learn financial literacy
学习金融知识
&gt;&gt; and be prepared for it.
做好准备。
&gt;&gt; The thing that I'd always ask people to
我总是会问人们的一件事是
remember is
记住是
don't forget the emotional side of money
别忘了金钱的情感因素。
because greed, fear, that all comes into
因为贪婪、恐惧，所有这些都会汇聚于此。
how you're managing your finances as
你如何管理你的财务
well.
出色地。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So, use AI, use it to your
是的。所以，利用人工智能，把它用在你的……
advantage. I think it's brilliant and I
优势。我觉得这太棒了，而且
think you always need to lean into it.
认为你应该始终全力以赴。
Um, but there's a there's the human
嗯，但是，这里有人类。
component that can never be taken out of
永远无法从……中取出的组件
the equation, especially when it comes
这个等式，尤其是在它
to money and finance.
涉及金钱和金融。
&gt;&gt; Could I not just go on like chat GPT and
我难道不能像 GPT 那样继续聊天吗？
ask it to be my personal accountant
请它做我的私人会计
every month and tell it my situation,
每个月都告诉他们我的情况，
tell it my goals, and then tell it to
告诉它我的目标，然后告诉它
give me advice every every day, week,
每天、每周都给我一些建议，
month on what I should be doing. I think
一个月内我会做很多事情。我认为
that would be a great starting point to
那将是一个很好的起点
understand what do I need to do if I'm
如果我……，我该怎么做？
absolutely clueless.
完全一窍不通。
That's not to say cha cha GPT is always
这并不是说恰恰 GPT 总是
correct. Um, as you probably know,
正确的。嗯，正如你可能知道的那样，
there's some errors in it. So, take it
这里面有一些错误。所以，收下它吧。
with a pinch of salt. But if you're
加一小撮盐。但如果你是
starting from scratch, even saying,
从零开始，甚至可以说是，
"Hey, this is my income. This is my
“嘿，这是我的收入。这是我的
spending. How do you recommend I budget?
开支。您建议我如何制定预算？
Give me three or four ways to consider
请给我三到四种考虑方法。
it."
它。”
Yeah, that would be a a way for you to
是的，那将是你的一种方式
take if that's a way for you to take
如果你觉得这是个办法，那就接受吧
that next step, then I definitely think
那么下一步，我肯定会这么认为。
that's a avenue to be explored.
这是一个值得探索的方向。
&gt;&gt; Jack, you were telling me um the other
杰克，你刚才跟我说的是……另一个
day that you're now using AI a lot for
如今你大量使用人工智能的一天
financial support and advice.
提供财务支持和建议。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; What are you What are you doing? Um, so
你在做什么？嗯，所以
I got like this prompt on on chat GPT
我在聊天 GPT 中收到了类似这样的提示
where I've I've asked it to be the
我曾要求它成为……
world's best financial adviser for me
对我来说，世界上最好的理财顾问
and uh I screenshotted all my bank
呃，我把所有银行账户都截屏保存了。
statements and I every time I tell
声明，我每次都这么说
people this they kind of went because
人们这样认为，因为他们就是这样。
it's like a lot a window into your life
它就像一扇窥视你生活的窗口。
and I don't kind of know the GDPR or
我不太了解GDPR或
whatever around it but it's been so
不管周围环境如何，但一直以来都是如此
useful. So, I've screenshotted
有用。我已经截屏了。
everything on my bank statement, and
我的银行账单上的所有信息，以及
then it tells me how much I spend a
然后它会告诉我我花了多少钱
month, how much I can put into
一个月，我可以投入多少
investments and stuff. And I also
投资之类的。而且我
screenshotted this investment account I
我截屏了这个投资账户。
had, and it told me that I was
它告诉我，我是
overpaying on my investment account, and
我的投资账户支付过多，而且
that I should switch to another one
我应该换另一个
because the fees were better. And then
因为费用更优惠。进而
it was like, you
就像，你
don't have enough in savings, so you
积蓄不够，所以你
should stop investing and put your money
应该停止投资，把钱放回原处。
into savings.
存入储蓄账户。
gave me a advice on a savings account to
他给我提了个关于储蓄账户的建议。
put it into with a high interest like 4%
以4%的高利率投资。
interest and it's actually been
对此感兴趣，而且实际上一直如此。
gamechanging because it's kind of a base
这具有颠覆性意义，因为它某种程度上是一个基础。
knowledge that I wouldn't have had an
我知道我本不会有这种感觉
understanding towards and I get very
理解，我非常
excited when I listen to these podcasts
我听这些播客时很兴奋
cuz I sit here and they tell you like
因为我坐在这里，他们告诉你就像
ones to invest in and I think it was a
值得投资的股票，我认为这是一个不错的选择。
particular guest we had on and she said
我们请来了一位特别嘉宾，她说
you should invest in this kind of stock
你应该投资这类股票。
and I said like oh what do you think
然后我就说，哦，你觉得怎么样？
about this stock and it was just like
关于这支股票，情况就像……
don't be silly you're not this person
别傻了，你不是这个人。
and it's just been really helpful for me
这对我真的很有帮助。
to kind of understand it's it's um
要想弄明白，嗯……
advice changes and adjusts.
建议会根据情况变化和调整。
&gt;&gt; Oh, was that Kathy Wood?
哦，那是凯西·伍德吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; It was it was it Tesla?
是特斯拉吗？
&gt;&gt; Well, it told you to behave. It was like
它告诉过你要注意规矩。就像
behave yourself.
守规矩。
&gt;&gt; Cuz I asked it to be brutally honest
因为我要求它实话实说。
about all the advice it gave me. And I
它给了我很多建议。我
was like, Kathy Wood had this advice.
就像凯西·伍德给出的建议一样。
Tell me tell me should I put in should I
告诉我，告诉我，我应该放进去吗？我应该放进去吗？
put all my money into Tesla? And it was
把所有钱都投到特斯拉？确实如此。
like, look, you're not Kathy Wood. Like,
拜托，你又不是凯西·伍德。喜欢，
you don't have enough. It's kind of what
你不够。这有点像……
you said about um having emergency
你说过你遇到了紧急情况
funds. Yeah. It's like you don't have
资金。是的。就好像你没有
enough in your emergency funds. Top that
应急资金要充足。太棒了！
up first. And that's like if you want to
首先。就像你想……
invest in Tesla, we'll have another pot.
投资特斯拉，我们就能再赚一笔。
So the new one I've done trading 212.
所以我新做的交易是 212。
Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And you can do pies. So I've got a safe
你还可以做馅饼。所以我有一个保险箱
one
一
&gt;&gt; and a not so safe one and then a high
一个不太安全的，然后是一个高
interest account.
利息账户。
&gt;&gt; That's really interesting, Jack, that
杰克，这真有意思。
that that you've done that. And I think
你已经做到了。我觉得
that's that just shows the power of AI
这正体现了人工智能的强大力量。
now. And there's two really interesting
现在。还有两个非常有趣的
things that I picked up on then. first
我当时注意到的一些事情。第一的
is that it's very tailored based on you
因为它非常个性化，完全根据你的需求量身定制。
which with AI it's probably understood
有了人工智能，这或许就能理解了。
who you are as a person from the
你作为一个人是怎样的？
information that you fed to it your risk
你提供给它的信息会给你带来风险
profile your amounts the bank statement
银行对账单上的金额概况
had your savings and from that it
你把积蓄都用在了那里。
derived a profile and gave you the
根据分析结果，你得出了一个个人资料。
correct information based on
基于正确信息
your current situation
你目前的处境
&gt;&gt; and the second thing that probably
第二件事可能
doesn't get mentioned in maybe podcasts
可能在播客节目中都不会被提及
that you've done so far, Stephen, is the
斯蒂芬，你目前为止所做的就是
the savings, the putting it into a high
节省下来的钱，投入到高……
interest savings account. It's a very
利息储蓄账户。这是一个非常
easy basic personal finance tips that
简单易懂的个人理财技巧
actually do make a difference when it
实际上，当……时，确实会产生影响。
comes to habits, but also it's easy.
这关乎习惯，但也很容易做到。
That's passive income for you, but it
这就是被动收入，但它
would get missed out on a lot of the
会错过很多……
advice if you're watching a specific
如果你正在观看某个特定的节目，以下是一些建议。
investing focused YouTube video
专注于投资的YouTube视频
&gt;&gt; or podcast. So, it just harnesses the
或者播客。所以，它只是利用了
power of chat GPT. I don't know yet if
聊天功能 GPT。我还不清楚是否
or I don't know if we have any
或者我不知道我们是否有任何
information about how much information
信息量
we can actually feed into chat GPT and
我们实际上可以将数据输入到聊天 GPT 中，
where that goes but it sounds like it's
不知道会引向何方，但听起来像是……
just you've given it the underlying
你只是赋予了它基础。
framework or this is my current
框架，或者说这是我目前的框架
situation and it's given you the correct
情况就是这样，它给了你正确的答案。
um initial guidance at least and then
嗯，至少是初步指导，然后
you've been able to say okay that makes
你已经能够说“好的”，这使得
sense for me or no I'm not going to
对我来说有意义与否，我不会……
listen to this.
听听这个。
&gt;&gt; Yeah I think the the I keep asking it
是的，我觉得我一直在问这个问题
like am I on track and it changes its
比如，我是否走在正确的轨道上，然后情况发生了变化。
advice. So although it's been really
建议。所以尽管这真的很
good initially, I think I'm now with
一开始还不错，我觉得我现在和
that base knowledge just going to go and
那些基础知识就会消失。
sort of and everything I've learned on
差不多，还有我学到的一切
these podcasts as well, just kind of go
这些播客也是，就这样开始了
and run with it.
然后全力以赴。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And that's really important thing
是的。那才是真正重要的事。
because you know there's there's so much
因为你知道，有很多东西。
information online when it comes to
关于网上信息方面
money that you don't actually know who
你根本不知道是谁给的钱
to listen to and who to get advice from
应该听取谁的建议，以及应该向谁寻求建议。
and who to trust because you could be
以及该信任谁，因为你可能……
scrolling through Tik Tok and the first
浏览TikTok，然后是第一个
video you see is put all your money into
你看到的视频就是把你所有的钱都投入进去。
Tesla or crypto or one asset or you
特斯拉、加密货币、某种资产，或者你
could see another one that says, "Oh,
可以看到另一个写着：“哦，
stop buying lattes so otherwise you'll
别再买拿铁了，否则你会……
die broke." And then the next video
“破产而死。”然后是下一个视频
might be mine and you might think, "Oh,
可能是我的，你可能会想，“哦，
the last two people just told me BS. Why
最后两个人说的全是废话。为什么
should I listen to this person?
我应该听这个人的话吗？
And so finding a person who
所以，找到一个
whose principles and philosophy align
其原则和理念相一致
with your way of thinking is a way that
你的这种思维方式是一种
will keep you motivated and inspired to
这将使你保持动力和灵感
want to keep getting better with
想不断进步
finances. And so you've probably got
财政。所以你可能已经……
that information from chat GPT and it
这些信息来自聊天 GPT 及其
said to you, hey, based on your profile,
我说，嘿，根据你的个人资料，
this is what's important. And you've
这才是最重要的。而你已经
kind of leaned into the leaned into that
有点倾向于那种倾向。
and thought, this is right for me.
我心想，这很适合我。
Actually, this makes sense. and you've
其实，这很有道理。而你已经
probably actioned it. And so it's it's a
可能已经采取了行动。所以，它就是
um fine line between finding someone who
嗯，找到合适的人之间只有一线之隔
you resonate with and also understanding
你对此感同身受，并且也理解
that their principles align with yours,
他们的原则与你的原则一致，
I would say to that.
我会这么说。
&gt;&gt; And how much do you think about credit
你对信贷有多大看法？
scores? Because I absolutely butchered
分数？因为我彻底搞砸了
my credit score before I even realized
在我意识到之前，我的信用评分就已经很高了。
it existed and my credit score was in
它确实存在，而且我的信用评分也很高。
the bin. I I got uh two CCJs, which are
垃圾桶。我收到了两份CCJ（县法院判决书），分别是：
county court judgments, which is where
县法院判决，也就是
you really up
你真的搞砸了
&gt;&gt; because I didn't know a thing about
因为我对此一无所知
money when I was 18, 19 years old, and
我18岁、19岁时的钱，
they gave me these credit cards and I
他们给了我这些信用卡，然后我
had overdraft and defaulted and didn't
透支并违约，而且没有
pay them back and went to an ATM, put it
还了钱，然后去自动取款机取了钱。
in, it didn't come back out.
进去之后就没再出来。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Um and then I found out that I had
嗯，然后我发现我……
destroyed my credit rating before I knew
在我不知情的情况下，我的信用评级就被毁了。
what it was. And I hear this quite a lot
那是什么？我经常听到这种说法。
from people. They don't understand the
来自人们。他们不理解
importance of it or, you know,
它的重要性，或者，你知道，
&gt;&gt; you don't realize the importance of it
你没有意识到它的重要性。
until you're looking to buy something
直到你想买东西为止。
big.
大的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. because that's what it impacts the
是的。因为这就是它对……的影响。
credit score. It two people can go into
信用评分。两个人可以进去
a car showroom and choose the same car
去汽车展厅，选择同一款车
and the amount they pay for it will be
他们为此支付的金额将是
completely different based on the
完全不同，这取决于
history.
历史。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; The credit background and so there are
信用背景等等。
it is something that you need to think
这是你需要考虑的事情。
about. It is something that you need to
关于。这是你需要做的事情
make sure you're paying off in time in
确保按时还款。
full your credit card for instance. And
例如，刷爆你的信用卡。和
it is definitely one of the main things
这绝对是主要因素之一。
or one of one of the things people
或者说是人们所做的事情之一
should always look at and consider. And
应该始终关注并考虑。和
you can check your credit rating online
您可以在线查询您的信用评分。
for free.
免费。
&gt;&gt; There are websites that do that and you
有些网站会这样做，而且你
can check it just make sure all of your
可以检查一下，只要确保你所有的……
details are correct. If there's any
信息准确无误。如果有的话
anomalies, correct that. But most
出现异常，请纠正。但大多数
importantly, just make sure and it
重要的是，一定要确保它
really comes down to are you paying the
归根结底，问题在于你是否在支付费用。
things that are outstanding on time.
按时完成的杰出事项。
&gt;&gt; I think most people, especially younger
我认为大多数人，尤其是年轻人，都会这么想。
people, don't actually realize that they
人们其实并没有意识到他们
have a credit score and that they can
他们拥有信用评分，而且他们可以
check it right now for free. And they
现在就免费查看吧。他们
also probably don't realize that things
他们可能也没有意识到这些事情
like being registered to vote has an
就像登记投票一样……
impact on their credit rating. Cuz I
对其信用评级的影响。因为我
remember the first time I logged in to
还记得我第一次登录的情景吗？
check my credit score and I was like
我查了一下我的信用评分，然后我就……
&gt;&gt; 45 and it said the reason why one of the
45，并说明了其中一个原因是
reasons why it's low is because you
之所以这么低，是因为……
haven't registered to vote. I was like
尚未登记投票。我当时就像
what the hell?
我勒个去？
&gt;&gt; Yeah. You register to vote that that's
是的。你登记投票就是这么回事。
one of the things even something like
其中一件事情，甚至类似的事情
you could call up your credit card
你可以打电话给你的信用卡公司。
company or your uh the company that you
公司或者你的公司，呃，你所在的公司
have a debt at and say hey can you
欠债了，然后说，嘿，你能……
increase the amount that I have
增加我拥有的数量
available. What that does is it reduces
可用的。这样做会减少
your utilization when you're using debt.
当你使用债务时，你的债务利用率是多少？
&gt;&gt; And by just saying, okay, you have
仅仅说一声，好的，你就有
instead of utilizing 50% of your credit
而不是使用您信用额度的 50%。
available, you're now using 20%.
可用，您现在使用 20%。
&gt;&gt; What companies now see is, oh, okay,
企业现在看到的是，哦，好吧，
then they're being sensible, they're not
如果是这样，那他们就是明智的，他们就不是。
really relying on this debt on their
他们真的非常依赖这笔债务。
day-to-day living. So, there's a couple
日常生活。所以，有两个
of things that you can take into
你可以带进去的东西
account, but even if you do, and again,
账户，但即使你这么做了，而且再说一遍，
people don't realize this, even if you
人们没有意识到这一点，即使你
do have interest rates because you're
确实会有利率，因为你是
not paying your debt off in time, you
如果你未能按时偿还债务，你
can negotiate that. You can call up the
可以协商。你可以打电话给
company and say, "Okay, this is the
公司并说：“好的，这就是
interest rate I'm paying, but this is
我支付的利率，但这
what I have planned. This is how I plan
我已计划好。我的计划是这样的
to pay off my debt, and I want to do it
为了偿还债务，我想这么做。
over the next 12, 18 months. Can you
在接下来的 12 到 18 个月内。你可以吗
reduce or can you look at reducing my
减少或者你能考虑减少我的
interest rate?"
利率？”
&gt;&gt; I have these personas here. There's
我这里有这些人物角色。有
three of them. And I was wondering,
其中三人。我当时就在想，
there are three different people at
有三个不同的人
three different stages of life. When you
人生的三个不同阶段。当你
think about the advice you'd give these
想想你会给他们什么建议
people, does it come back to this
人们，最终还是会回到这个问题上来。
framework, this 65, 20, 15 framework
框架，这个65、20、15框架
really regardless of what stage they're
无论他们处于哪个阶段
at?
在？
&gt;&gt; You know what? Most things in finance do
你知道吗？金融领域的大多数事情
come back to that framework, the 65,
回到那个框架，65，
2015 or even a variation for it. With
2015 年，或者更确切地说是它的某种变体。和
Andy, he's just started his job. He's
安迪刚开始工作。他是
early on in his career. He's making less
在他职业生涯早期。他的收入减少了。
now than he will in 10 years, 20 years
现在比10年后、20年后他更糟。
time. So it may not be that his paycheck
时间。所以，问题可能不在于他的薪水。
allows for 65% to go towards his rent
其中65%用于支付房租。
and his car, which is what he wants
还有他的车，那是他想要的。
something new of. It might be that it
一些新的东西。或许就是这样。
might be 70 or 75%. But the key is,
可能是70%或75%。但关键在于，
especially at this stage, the most
尤其是在这个阶段，最
important thing that he has going for
他拥有的重要优势
him is time. So save, invest early, do
时间就是他。所以要储蓄，尽早投资，行动起来！
it recurringly, which is often, and
它反复出现，这种情况很常见，而且
harness the power of long-term growth is
利用长期增长的力量是
what I'll say to Andy. When it comes to
我要跟安迪说的话。说到
the new phone, remember that there is a
新手机，记住还有
trade-off for every decision you're
你做的每一个决定都有利弊权衡。
making. If it's not an absolute
制作。如果它不是绝对的
necessity or an urgency, that can be
必要性或紧迫性，可能是
spent and the value of that maybe
花费及其价值可能
thousands today can be worth
如今数千元可能价值连城
significantly more in 10 years or 20
10年或20年后，数量会显著增加。
years time.
几年时间。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; So balance that together. Again, if
所以要权衡利弊。再说一遍，如果
there's budget with his after he's put
他投入之后，预算就到位了。
down the money for his savings
他把钱存了起来
investing, if he wants to spend that on
如果他想把钱花在投资上的话。
the fund, then go ahead.
如果资金到位，那就继续。
&gt;&gt; With him though, do you think his risk
但你觉得他的风险有多大？
appetite should be a little bit higher?
食欲应该会稍微好一些吧？
Cuz I when I look at uh Andy here, he
因为当我看着安迪的时候，他
looks like he's early 20s, maybe late
他看起来像二十出头，也可能接近三十岁。
teens or something.
青少年之类的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; With him, I think you need to take risk.
我觉得和他在一起需要承担风险。
You need to go work at an AI startup
你应该去一家人工智能初创公司工作。
because he wants to fill that bucket of
因为他想把那桶东西装满
knowledge with like really high
知识水平非常高
yielding, relevant skill.
具备相关的技能。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So, I don't know. I think of him. I go,
所以，我不知道。我想起了他。我走了，
"Bro, roll the dice. You got nothing to
兄弟，掷骰子吧。你没什么可做的。
lose. You ain't got a mortgage yet. You
失去。你还没有房贷。你
ain't got kids."
我没有孩子。
&gt;&gt; In your 20s, you can play the long-term
20多岁的时候，你可以进行长期投资。
game. Absolutely. Everything feels like
游戏。绝对地。一切都感觉像是
it's urgent in your 20s. You feel like
这在你二十多岁的时候很紧迫。你感觉像
you need the promotion. You feel like
你需要升职。你感觉像
you need to invest straight away. You
你需要立即投资。你
feel like you need the pay rise
感觉自己需要加薪
immediately. But decades over dopamine
立即地。但几十年来，多巴胺一直备受关注。
and he's got a long time and the the
他还有很长一段时间，而且
things that he learns now, the things
他现在学到的东西，那些东西
that he invests in, the skills and the
他投资的领域，技能和
risks that he take, he can bounce back
他承担的风险，他都能反弹。
from that.
由此而来。
&gt;&gt; And even when it comes to investing,
即使在投资方面，
actually, when you're in your 20s, you
事实上，当你二十多岁的时候，你
can be more risk averse because you have
可能更厌恶风险，因为你有
the upward trend of the market
市场的上升趋势
that will see you through.
这会帮助你度过难关。
&gt;&gt; Mhm. So 20s is the time to take the
嗯。所以20多岁是采取行动的时机。
risk, take all the tiny experiments,
冒险，进行所有的小实验，
and just be a sponge where you absorb
就像海绵一样吸收一切
everything.
一切。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, that's what I'll take.
嗯，我就选这个。
&gt;&gt; What about Lisa in the middle, though?
那么中间的丽莎呢？
&gt;&gt; Lisa is she's got a mortgage, she's got
丽莎有房贷，她有
an income, and she's got a good amount
她有收入，而且收入相当可观。
of savings, and she is keen to start
她有一笔积蓄，而且她很想开始
investing, but she doesn't know where to
她想投资，但她不知道该往哪里投资。
start. And this is where a lot of people
开始。而这里正是很多人聚集的地方
fall into. They have their savings
落入。他们有积蓄
setting aside. Um, and this is she's
暂且搁置。嗯，这是她的
doing really well, someone like in
做得非常好，就像……
Lisa's position. But if anyone listening
丽莎的职位。但如果有人在听
to this is similar to Lisa's position,
这与丽莎的立场类似。
it chances are they're not investing
他们很可能没有投资。
because they are scared and fearful of
因为他们害怕和恐惧
what to do and they don't know where to
他们不知道该怎么办，也不知道该去哪里。
start. So Lisa, I would say have your
开始。所以丽莎，我想说，有你的
emergency fund in place. Pay off any
已设立应急基金。偿还所有款项
debt. It doesn't look like you have any
债务。看起来你好像什么都没有。
debt. If your mortgage isn't over 8%,
债务。如果你的房贷利率不超过8%，
you can make more from instead of paying
你可以从中获得更多收益，而不是支付费用。
down your debt, you can make more
减少债务后，你就能赚更多钱。
investing. So, you're great to start
投资。所以，你开局很棒。
wanting to invest. And I would say keep
想要投资。我会说继续
it simple. Do it for the long term. Keep
很简单。要着眼长远。保持
it simple. You want to if especially if
很简单。你想，尤其是在……的时候
you're just starting out, your emotions
你才刚刚起步，你的情绪
and the behavior is going to play a key
而这种行为将发挥关键作用。
part in your investing. So, 100% of your
参与您的投资。所以，100%的你
portfolio, stick to index funds and
投资组合，坚持投资指数基金。
target date to retirement funds at the
退休基金的目标日期
moment. And then if you are ready as you
片刻。然后，如果你准备好了，就像你
get more senior, you haven't increased
资历再深，你的资历也没有提高。
your income, then you can dip into other
然后，你可以用你的收入来支付其他费用。
assets should you want to.
如果您愿意，可以拥有这些资产。
&gt;&gt; And we've got Matt over there who's a
那边还有马特，他是一位
single parent earning about So Lisa was
单亲母亲的收入大约是索·丽莎
earning roughly 140,000 a year. Yeah.
年收入约14万。是的。
&gt;&gt; Matt's earning60,000 a year.
马特年收入6万美元。
&gt;&gt; Over over 50% of his income is going
他超过50%的收入都花光了。
towards his rent. He has credit card
他要用这笔钱来支付房租。他有信用卡。
debt of 1,500. The first thing I would
负债1500。我首先会做的事
say looking at someone in Matt's
比如说看着马特的某个人
position is if you've already saved for
如果你已经存了钱，那么你的立场就是如此。
your peace of mind fund, you the first
您的安心基金，您是第一位
thing you want to do is pay off that
你想做的就是还清那笔钱。
high interest rate debt. It is like
高利率债务。它就像
running with weights on your ankles. You
脚踝绑重跑步。你
want to take them off so you can start
想把它们脱掉，这样你就可以开始了
moving on to the next path of your
继续你的下一条道路
financial journey. So focus on paying
财务之旅。所以，重点在于支付。
off that credit card debt. He wants to
还清信用卡债务。他想
increase income income sources but has
增加收入来源，但有
little time outside of work and being a
工作之余几乎没有时间，而且……
dad. So that says to me that he probably
爸爸。所以这说明他很可能
doesn't have time or energy to spend on
没有时间和精力投入到
trying to see if something's going to
试图看看某件事是否会发生
work and see what comes out of it. He
先做做看，看看结果如何。他
wants to um make an immediate source of
想要立即建立一个来源
income. So the easiest way to increase
收入。所以增加的最简单方法
your income is getting an increase in
你的收入正在增加
your current job,
你目前的工作，
getting a pay rise, and if not switching
争取加薪，如果不行就换工作
companies to see if you get a pay rise
看看公司是否会给你涨工资
that way. When I'm looking at my own
那样做。当我审视自己时
career, when I stayed at the same
职业生涯，当我一直待在同一家公司时
organization, it was the increase was
组织，是增长是
between
之间
3% 5% sometimes a bit higher if I got
3% 5%，有时如果我有……会更高一些。
promoted to 10%. And then when I
晋升至10%。然后当我
switched companies, it was always
换了公司，一直都是这样。
between 20 and 30% when I moved. And I
搬家时价格在 20% 到 30% 之间。我
know that is I I was in a lucky place
我知道我当时身处一个幸运的地方。
where I had the movement to get those
我当时有能力去争取那些
pay jumps and to get that salary
薪资大幅上涨，才能获得那份薪水
increase. And not everyone's in that
增加。但并非所有人都如此。
position. Um but if you have or if
位置。嗯，但是如果你有或者如果
you're in an industry which there is a
你所在的行业存在……
there is more path to earn more then I
赚钱的途径不止我一条
would definitely say first and foremost
首先，我肯定会说：
increase your income. You don't have to
增加收入。你不必
put in any more time towards it given
投入更多时间
you also have uh children to look after
你还要照顾孩子呢
as well.
也一样。
If you've
如果你有
stopped, if you've already exhausted
如果你已经筋疲力尽，就停下来。
those two avenues, then the next thing
这两种途径，然后是下一件事
I'll say if you want an immediate income
我会说，如果你想要立即获得收入。
is picking up income streams that
正在获取收入来源
unfortunately might be tied to your
不幸的是，这可能与您的有关。
time, but they will have an immediate
时间有限，但他们会立即……
impact on your income because that's
会对你的收入产生影响，因为……
probably what you might be looking to do
这可能是你想做的事情
because your rent and I'm guessing your
因为你的房租，我猜你的
other living expenses are taking up a
其他生活开支占据了很大一部分
lot of your take-home pay. So, you want
你实际到手工资的大部分。所以你想
to find out that extra buffer to start
找出开始所需的额外缓冲区
paying towards the debt that you have.
用于偿还你的债务。
things like
诸如
&gt;&gt; so this could be things like uh selling
所以这可能包括销售之类的事情。
secondhand stuff online um selling
网上二手商品销售
products online renting out a spare room
在线出租空余房间的产品
if you have that on Airbnb um things
如果你在Airbnb上有那个，嗯……
that you don't actually need to put
实际上你不需要输入
capital in to make money straight away
投入资金立即赚钱
from
从
&gt;&gt; are there things you never spend money
有没有什么东西你从来不花钱买？
on
在
&gt;&gt; at this point in my life me specifically
就我而言，在人生的这个阶段，具体来说，就是我。
I don't think I bought a designer
我觉得我没买设计师品牌。
&gt;&gt; item in two years which is a lot for me
两年内买到这件东西，对我来说已经很多了。
because I was dripped out in the
因为我被淋透了
designer wear beforehand I've found
我之前发现的设计师服装
that my validation in life has come
我的人生价值终于得到了认可
through by work and through internally
通过工作和内部
and it took me on a journey to do that
我为此经历了一段漫长的旅程。
and I just don't believe in
我就是不相信
the premium prices that you pay for
你支付的溢价
promoting another product or a brand
推广其他产品或品牌
if it's for utility. If you're buying a
如果是为了实用目的。如果你要买一个
branded item or a designer for utility,
品牌商品或实用型设计师作品
i.e. this design or this brand
例如，这种设计或这个品牌
works better, then go for it. But if
如果效果好，那就去做吧。但是如果
you're doing it purely to show, then for
你这样做纯粹是为了炫耀，然后为了
me at this point in my life, it's just a
就我目前的人生阶段而言，这只是……
no-go. I could spend that money in other
不行。我可以把那笔钱花在其他地方。
ways that brings me a lot more um
这让我感觉更……
fulfillment in different ways.
以不同的方式获得满足感。
&gt;&gt; Do you spend on fast fashion instead of
你会把钱花在快时尚上吗？
the luxury high-end stuff?
是那种奢侈品级别的奢侈品吗？
&gt;&gt; Oh, that's a good question. No, I don't
哦，问得好。不，我没有
spend on fast fashion unless it's a
除非是特殊情况，否则不要在快时尚上花钱。
really urgent last minute buy and I
真的非常紧急，最后一刻才买的，而且
haven't found anything else. But I tend
还没找到其他东西。但我倾向于
to have a capsule wardrobe which means I
拥有一个胶囊衣橱，这意味着我
could play around. I spend
可以玩玩。我花费
&gt;&gt; a good amount on quality pieces
很多都是优质货。
&gt;&gt; and that's important to me. Quality
这对我来说很重要。质量
pieces I could use time and time again
我可以反复使用的部件
and can switch in and out of. And I I
并且可以随时切换。而我
think for me when it comes to clothing,
说到穿衣打扮，请替我考虑一下。
it's more just okay
还行吧。
with work. It's what can remove the
努力工作。它能够移除
decision- making for me.
替我做决定。
&gt;&gt; What about books?
书呢？
&gt;&gt; I think that is one area that I love
我认为那是我喜欢的一个领域。
spending money on. There's an infinite
花钱的地方。存在着无限
return. There really is. And actually
返回。确实有。实际上
some of the breakthroughs I've had have
我取得的一些突破性进展包括：
come from the books I've read. Even the
源自我读过的书。甚至
first book I read which was Rich Dad
我读的第一本书是《富爸爸》。
Poor Dad that just that concept of
可怜的爸爸，那只是那个概念而已
understanding assets versus liabilities.
了解资产与负债的区别。
Just knowing that from an early age can
从小就知道这一点就可以
start changing your thinking in a way
开始以某种方式改变你的思维方式
that you wouldn't be able to having a
你将无法拥有一个
normal conversation because the people
正常的对话，因为人们
you hang around with, the people who you
你经常和那些人混在一起，你
spend time with, they have a massive
花时间陪伴他们，他们拥有巨大的……
impact on where you end up. And I think
对你最终去向的影响。我觉得
it's easy to say just hang out with
说起来容易，就只是和……一起玩而已。
another crew or just hang out with a new
换个团队，或者只是和新成员一起玩。
crowd that pushes you. But actually for
人群推搡着你。但实际上是为了
a lot of people, they don't have access
很多人，他们没有机会
to that. And that's where books,
正是如此。而这正是书籍的意义所在。
podcasts, YouTube videos, it almost has
播客、YouTube 视频，几乎都有了。
that averaging effect of the five people
五个人的平均效应
around you.
你周围。
&gt;&gt; It mirrors that effect. So even if you
它反映了这种效果。所以即使你
don't have access to the people who you
无法接触到你认识的人
want to learn from by reading their
想通过阅读他们的著作来学习
book, watching the videos, listening to
读书、看视频、听音乐
the podcasts, you can still gain that
通过播客，你仍然可以获得这些信息。
knowledge and it's almost equivalent to
知识，而且几乎等同于
you sitting with them for an hour.
你和他们一起坐了一个小时。
&gt;&gt; So you're saying people should
所以你的意思是人们应该
definitely subscribe?
一定要订阅吗？
&gt;&gt; Always
总是
subliminal messaging.
潜意识信息。
&gt;&gt; You wear black a lot like me. Is that an
你和我一样，经常穿黑色衣服。那是……
intentional choice? It started off
这是有意为之的选择吗？事情开始于
because when I was doing my YouTube
因为当我做我的 YouTube 频道时
channel alongside working in banking, I
除了在银行工作之外，我还经营着一个频道。
had to find every way possible to
必须想尽一切办法
eliminate any sort of decision- making
取消任何形式的决策
that will stop me from doing the thing.
那样我就不会去做那件事了。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And so it was a way for me to create a
所以，这对我来说是一种创造的方式。
system, not rely on motivation. So there
系统，而不是依赖动机。所以就是这样。
was about four outfits of black that I'd
我大概有四套黑色衣服。
always change from and it made my life a
总是变化，这让我的生活变得
lot easier. Now this has carried
容易多了。现在这件事已经持续下去了。
through. It's been a lot of just it just
通过。一直以来，就只是这样而已。
makes me think about things less. But
让我少想事情。但
no, I do also wear other colors just as
不，我也会穿其他颜色的衣服。
much. It just happens to be that black
很多。它恰好是那种黑色的
is 60% of my wardrobe.
占我衣橱的60%。
&gt;&gt; Nisha, we have a closing tradition on
妮莎，我们有一个结束的传统……
this podcast where the last guest leaves
在这个播客节目中，最后一位嘉宾离开了。
a question for the next not knowing who
下一个问题，不知道是谁
they're leaving it for. And the question
他们把它留下来是为了……这个问题
that's been left for you is who is the
留给你的就是……
one person that was slash is responsible
其中一个被斜杠标记的人要为此负责。
for the person that you are today and
因为你就是现在的你
the reason why you are sitting here?
你坐在这里的原因是什么？
It goes back to the person who when I
这要追溯到我……的时候的那个人。
started my YouTube videos
我开始制作我的 YouTube 视频
and I got a lot of noise and a lot of
我听到了很多噪音和很多
people saying, "Oh, like what is she
人们说：“哦，她是什么？”
doing? Does this make sense?" The person
正在做？这样说得通吗？”
who really kept me going was my dad.
真正让我坚持下去的是我爸爸。
Yeah. He saw my videos and he said to
是的。他看了我的视频，然后他说
me, "What you're doing is so good for
对我而言，“你所做的一切都太好了。”
the world. Your education is going to
世界。你的教育将会
help so many people. don't stop.
帮助了很多人。不要停。
And I didn't.
而我没有。
So,
所以，
thanks, Dad, for believing me when there
谢谢爸爸，感谢你相信我。
was like nine or 10 views on my videos.
我的视频大概只有九到十次观看。
Wasn't expecting that.
没想到会这样。
It's crazy how someone just saying a few
真是不可思议，有人只是说了几句话……
words at the right moment can be so sort
在恰当的时机说出合适的话语，是多么的简短
of pivotal to your like trajectory.
对你的人生轨迹至关重要。
Does he know how much he inspired all of
他知道自己对所有人产生了多大的影响吗？
this?
这？
&gt;&gt; I don't think he knows the extent to it.
我认为他并不了解事情的严重性。
I sent him like a message maybe a few
我给他发了条信息，可能还有几条。
months ago
几个月前
um telling him like, "Hey, remember that
嗯，告诉他，“嘿，记住那……”
day when I showed you my YouTube video
那天我给你看我的YouTube视频
and it was just me in my dining room and
当时只有我一个人在餐厅里。
I couldn't even speak properly and it
我甚至都无法正常说话，而且
was set up in a weird lighting and it
拍摄时的灯光很奇怪，而且
was getting nine or 10 views and you
浏览量达到了九到十次，而你
said, "Don't stop. Keep passing this
他说：“别停。继续传递这个。”
education down." And I said to him, I
教育水平下降。”我对他说，我
did send that message to him and said,
我确实给他发了那条信息，并且说：
"I'm so glad you did that because I've
“我很高兴你这么做了，因为我……”
continued because of that." And we're
正因如此才得以延续。”而我们
not really wordy with each other, but I
我们彼此之间不太爱说话，但是
think he heard it. I don't know if he
我想他听到了。我不知道他是否
knows the extent, but I think he'll be
他知道程度，但我认为他会
happy to know the extent of it now.
很高兴现在知道了事情的严重程度。
You got the tissues, Jack.
杰克，你有纸巾吗？
&gt;&gt; Thank you.
谢谢。
&gt;&gt; Thanks. Yeah, I think we're good.
谢谢。是的，我觉得我们没问题。
&gt;&gt; Who is the one person that was is
那个人是谁？
responsible for the person that you are
对你所扮演的角色负责
today and the reason why you're sitting
今天以及你坐在这里的原因
here now? And that is dad.
现在在这里吗？这就是爸爸。
That is dad.
那是爸爸。
&gt;&gt; He must be pretty shocked to some
他肯定对某些事情感到非常震惊。
degree. Like no one could have imagined
程度。简直超乎想象
and
和
your channel would be this big and you'd
你的频道会发展到这么大，而你也会
be reaching this many people.
能够触达这么多人。
&gt;&gt; He didn't expect it. I didn't expect it.
他没想到会这样。我没想到会这样。
I think he
我认为他
believed that
认为
for him he believed
他相信
that a job was security for us. I'm one
对我们来说，工作就意味着安全感。我是其中之一
of three girls. I'm the middle sister.
三个女孩。我是家中排行第二的姐妹。
And all he wanted was for us to get a
他想要的只是我们得到一个
good job and be secure. And so whilst
干得好，注意安全。因此，尽管
this is beyond I could ever expect, when
这完全超出了我的预期，当
I quit and I quit taking a big pay cut,
我辞职了，而且我拒绝接受大幅降薪。
that was hard for him.
对他来说，那很艰难。
&gt;&gt; How big was the pay cut?
降薪幅度有多大？
&gt;&gt; 84%.
84%。
&gt;&gt; So you were on
所以你当时在
&gt;&gt; 220.
220.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Which is about $300,000.
大约是30万美元。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And I was just about to get a a
是的。我正要拿到一个
six figure bon. So I left before a six
六位数奖金。所以我在六点前离开了。
figure bonus. Just before the biggest
人物奖励。就在最大的时候
bonus of my career. I negotiated it. I
职业生涯的额外收获。我协商解决了这个问题。我
spent months negotiating it. And two
花了几个月的时间进行谈判。还有两个
months before that six figure bonus
几个月前，那笔六位数奖金就到账了。
landed, I resigned.
落地后，我辞职了。
&gt;&gt; Why didn't you just wait?
你为什么不等等呢？
&gt;&gt; There's always going to be a carrot
总会有诱饵。
waved in front of your face. And that
在你眼前挥舞。而那
carrot's going to come in different
胡萝卜会有各种各样的品种。
shapes, sizes, forms,
形状、大小、形式
and it's going to be a distraction to
这会分散注意力
keep you on the default path.
让你保持在默认路径上。
The carrot for me was that bonus
对我来说，最大的诱惑就是那笔奖金。
telling me, "Hey, just wait. Just wait
告诉我，“嘿，等等。等等。”
another two months and then wait another
再过两个月，然后再等一个月。
year and another year and 5 years and 10
一年，又一年，五年，十年
years and just wait till you're 60." And
几年后，等你到了60岁就知道了。”
I had this once in a-lifetime
我一生中只有一次这样的经历
opportunity
机会
that was just exploding on the side.
那东西就在旁边爆炸了。
And with it came all these people
随之而来的是这些人。
saying, "Hey, I'm so thankful for all of
他说：“嘿，我非常感谢所有的一切。”
this." And I was getting DMs from people
就是这样。”然后我就收到了人们的私信。
just pouring their life story to me.
他们只是向我倾诉他们的人生故事。
And there is no monetary value that
而且它没有货币价值。
beats that. There really isn't. And so I
比那好多了。确实没有。所以，我
like took a step back. I ran my numbers.
就像后退了一步。我计算了一下。
It was 84% pay cut. I thought it still
降薪幅度高达84%。我当时觉得它仍然
covers my mortgage. It covers my like
可以用来支付我的房贷。它涵盖了我的喜好
basic living expenses.
基本生活开支。
The biggest risk isn't quitting my job.
最大的风险不是辞职。
The biggest risk is letting this once in
最大的风险就是让它进来一次。
a lifetime opportunity pass me by and
千载难逢的机会从我身边溜走
never knowing where that path could have
永远无法预知那条路会通向何方
taken me. That was the biggest risk. And
带走了我。这是最大的风险。和
the hardest part was actually just
最难的部分其实就是
letting go of the identity that I
放下我曾经的身份
wrapped myself in.
把自己裹了起来。
Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; What was identity?
身份认同是什么？
&gt;&gt; I
我
my title was my identity. I'd worked in
我的头衔就是我的身份。我曾在……工作
banking for nine years and I could sit
我在银行工作了九年，我可以坐着
at a dinner table, cling on to my title,
在餐桌上，紧紧抓住我的头衔不放。
say I worked in finance and feel
假设我在金融行业工作，并且感觉
externally validated.
经外部验证。
And so that move to quit at the time
所以，当时采取的辞职行动就是如此。
that I did from a career, a corporate
我从职业生涯和公司做起
career which I've worked so hard for,
我为之努力奋斗的事业，
it's
它是
like it's what I wanted for so long. and
就像我一直以来梦寐以求的那样。和
then just let go of that and say
那就放下这件事，然后说
I'm letting go of that identity. It took
我要放弃那个身份。花了
so much reframing in my mind and so much
我的脑海中进行了大量的重新思考，而且……
mind work and so many things I had to do
脑力劳动和许多其他事情我必须做
to make myself feel comfortable to say
为了让自己感觉舒服些，我才说
okay I'm not letting anything else
好吧，我不会让其他任何事发生。
dictate the way my life goes from here.
决定我今后的人生走向。
It was a lot of work. And I would say if
工作量很大。我会说如果
anyone else is listening to this
还有其他人也在听这个吗？
thinking,
思维，
I'm in a place where
我身处一个这样的地方
I'm unhappy. I really want to do
我不开心。我真的很想做
something new, but I'm scared and I
这是新事物，但我很害怕，而且我
don't know what other people are going
不知道其他人要去哪里
to say and
可以说
what's society going to say if I quit or
如果我辞职，社会会怎么说？
take this other path.
走另一条路。
I could say the things that I did that
我可以说出我做过的那些事。
really helped me.
真的帮了我很大的忙。
And the first is
第一个是
spend more time on
花更多时间在
the path that you want to go down than
你想走的那条路
around the people that are telling you
周围都是告诉你这些话的人
otherwise.
否则。
Because so often we're half in half out.
因为我们常常处于半投入半退出的状态。
We're interested in something but we're
我们对某件事感兴趣，但是我们
not obsessed with it. And when you're
并没有痴迷于此。当你
interested, you just kind of just do
你感兴趣的话，就会这么做。
whatever needs to be done. But when
任何需要做的事情。但是当
you're obsessed,
你太着迷了。
you're going to do whatever it takes.
你会不惜一切代价。
And this applies to anything to
这适用于任何事物
changing your career to being a parent
转行成为父母
to being an entrepreneur.
成为一名企业家。
Become obsessed with that thing that you
对你迷恋的那件事
want to do cuz that will give you the
想这么做是因为那样会给你带来……
courage to make the hard decisions when
有勇气在……时做出艰难的决定
they come.
他们来了。
The second thing,
第二件事，
and I think I made a video on this too,
我想我之前也做过一个关于这个的视频。
I I wrote down on my phone on on an
我在手机上写下了……
Apple notes,
苹果指出，
and I wrote down all the things people
我把人们说的所有事情都写了下来。
were saying to me, the external noise.
他们告诉我，这是外部噪音。
And underneath it, I had what my inner
而在这一切之下，我拥有的是我内心深处的东西
voice was saying.
一个声音在说。
And it's really easy when your inner
当你的内心
voice isn't loud for it to be diluted by
声音不大，不会被稀释。
what everyone else around you is saying.
你周围其他人都在说什么。
that at that point if anyone said
那时如果有人说
anything or if anyone is saying anything
任何事，或者如果有人在说什么
to plant seeds of doubt in your head
在你的脑海里种下怀疑的种子
look at what your inner voice is saying
听听你内心的声音在说什么。
read it repeat it let that be louder
读一遍，重复一遍，让声音更大些。
than anything else that is happening
比其他任何事情都重要。
around you
你周围
&gt;&gt; and what was the external voices saying
外界的声音又在说什么呢？
&gt;&gt; well when my channel started picking up
当我的频道开始走红的时候
it was
那是
being shared into um WhatsApp groups of
被分享到 um WhatsApp 群组
people I know and friends of friends and
我认识的人以及朋友的朋友
friends and friends and it was just,
朋友们，还有朋友们，就是这样，
you know, when you're just starting
你知道，当你刚开始的时候
something new and someone is breaking
有新的东西，有人在打破
barriers, it's just trying to
障碍，它只是想
&gt;&gt; pull them back.
把它们拉回来。
&gt;&gt; Pull them back a little bit. This isn't
把它们往后拉一点。这不是
you.
你。
&gt;&gt; Mocking them subtly.
暗讽他们。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Why are you saying your numbers
是的。你为什么要说你的数字？
online? What are you doing? Lol. And
在线的？你在干什么？哈哈。和
you've just got to remember the reason
你只需要记住原因。
why I'm saying my numbers online. That
我为什么会在网上公布我的数字。那
is hard to do. It's hard to sit there
这很难做到。坐在那里真难受。
and say this is my salary over 9 years.
然后说这是我9年来的薪水。
It's hard to do that. But I I remind
这很难做到。但我提醒
myself it's to be transparent. It's to
就我个人而言，我只是想坦诚相待。这是为了
help people make the decisions that help
帮助人们做出有益的决定
them with money.
用钱帮助他们。
It's the same reason why I came back and
这也是我回来的原因。
said, "I want to say this because it's
他说：“我想说这些是因为……”
the transparency."
透明度。”
And I think the third thing
我认为第三点
I think everyone should like kind of
我觉得每个人都应该喜欢这种感觉
take into account when
考虑以下情况
they're making um Hold on, give me a
他们正在制作……等等，给我一个
second.
第二。
&gt;&gt; Where's where's this emotion coming
这种情绪究竟从何而来？
from? It's very deep inside you.
从？它深深地藏在你内心深处。
There was a lot of pain
当时非常痛苦
during my career
在我的职业生涯中
and I felt really trapped at times but I
我有时感觉自己真的被困住了，但是
don't know how to escape
不知道如何逃脱
but also cuz I know a lot of people are
但也因为我知道很多人都是
probably hearing this and thinking I'm
听到这话，他可能在想我
also in that place
也在那个地方
and so I really feel like my purpose is
所以我觉得我的目标是
to help as many people to go from
帮助尽可能多的人从
feeling trapped to
感到被困住了
freeing themselves and using money to do
他们挣脱束缚，并利用金钱去做
that. And so I guess that's why I'm
那。所以我想这就是我的原因吧
feeling like
感觉像
it's bringing it all out because this is
它把一切都暴露出来了，因为这是
just alignment for me.
对我来说，只需要对齐就行了。
And it's just like bringing back the
这就像是把……带回来了
memories of what where I was at that
回忆起当时我在哪里。
time and what I had to do to
时间和我必须做的事情
like just take that cup because at the
就像拿着那个杯子一样，因为在
end of the day, no one else has to deal
说到底，其他人都不用操心。
with your
你的
with the decisions you make in life more
你在生活中做出的决定更多
than you. They have to deal with maybe
比你强。他们或许需要应对这种情况。
the consequence of a moment. But only
瞬间的后果。但仅
you have to deal with the consequences
你必须承担后果。
of all the decisions that you make in
你在……中做出的所有决定
life. Only you have to go to a job and
生活。你只需要去上班就行了。
whe a company that you don't want to
当你不想和一家公司合作时
work in. Only you have to live that day.
上班。你只需要活过那一天。
Only you have to
只有你
be with a partner if that's the reason
如果这就是原因，那就和伴侣在一起吧。
you chose. If if you chose because
你选择了。如果你选择因为
everyone else is saying it, only you
其他人都这么说，只有你这么说。
have to do that. Only you have to grow
必须这么做。只有你才需要成长
old with the memories of what could
满怀着对往事的回忆
have, should have, would have been
曾经，本应，本会是
and live with the what if. And that's
并接受“如果当初……”的假设。就是这样。
why I I guess there's so many people
我猜是因为人太多了吧。
that I know and that probably listening
我知道，而且可能正在听。
to this that know deep down there's
内心深处知道这一点的人……
something more out there. And I just
还有更多未知的东西。而我只是
want to if anything give them the
如果有什么想做的，那就是给他们
courage to say
鼓起勇气说
take that risk. It's usually a
承担这个风险。通常情况下，
calculated risk. And if it's to do with
经过权衡的风险。如果这与……有关
your money and finances, spend some
用你的钱和财务，花一些
time, make sure you have your emergency
时间到了，请确保你已做好应急准备。
fund or whatever it is that's needed,
资金或其他任何所需的东西，
but align your money to match your life
但要让你的金钱与你的生活相匹配。
decisions
决策
cuz it can really be freeing.
因为它真的能让人感到自由。
&gt;&gt; Have you spoken much about the pain?
你有没有多谈过你的疼痛？
&gt;&gt; Why?
为什么？
&gt;&gt; It's my content is personal finance.
我的内容是关于个人理财的。
It's not really about me. It's about
这其实跟我没关系。这是关于
personal finance. I'm just trying to
个人理财。我只是想
educate people. Um, yeah,
教育民众。嗯，是的。
I didn't
我没有
I probably wouldn't have spoken about it
我大概不会谈论这件事。
here if you didn't ask me the question
如果你没问我这个问题的话……
about
关于
where it's come from. It's taking me
它来自哪里。它带走了我
back to the start. And sometimes you go
回到起点。有时你会去
into a journey and you get tunnel vision
进入一段旅程，你就会陷入隧道视野。
and you forget why you did it and you
你忘记了你为什么这么做，然后你
forget why you started. And
忘记你最初为什么开始。和
you forget all the people that helped
你忘记了所有帮助过你的人。
you on that journey. And there was a lot
你在这段旅程中。而且有很多
of people that helped me and at
感谢帮助过我的人，以及
different points.
不同的观点。
My partner, my mom, my dad, my sisters,
我的伴侣、我的妈妈、我的爸爸、我的姐妹们
like they've all helped me at different
就像他们都在不同方面帮助过我一样。
points. And the people I learned from,
积分。还有那些我曾向其学习的人，
my mentors, like it's just all
我的导师们，就好像这一切都是真的
a reminder as to
提醒一下
how it started and how different things
它是如何开始的，以及不同的事物
have lined up.
已经排好队了。
&gt;&gt; What was the hardest day when you look
当你回头看时，你觉得最难熬的一天是什么时候？
back through that transition that you've
回顾你所经历的那段过渡时期
been on? What was was there a hardest
一直开着吗？最难的是什么？
day, a hardest moment?
一天中最难熬的时刻是什么？
&gt;&gt; The hardest day was that morning when I
最难熬的一天就是那天早上，当时我
emailed my manager to get on a Zoom call
我给经理发了邮件，约他参加Zoom会议。
and I said, "I'm turning down that
我说：“我拒绝那个提议。”
bonus.
奖金。
I'm leaving banking." That was the
我要离开银行业了。” 就是这样。
hardest.
最难。
&gt;&gt; If I was a fly on the wall,
如果我是一只墙上的苍蝇，
&gt;&gt; yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; What would I have seen that day?
那天我会看到什么？
You'd see
你会看到
a girl in her late 20s
一位二十多岁的女孩
taking or saying no to a path that could
选择或拒绝一条可能……的道路
make money and that was very certain and
赚钱是肯定的。
that followed the default path
遵循默认路径
to go to a path where she wasn't sure if
走向一条她并不确定的道路
she was going to make money. She didn't
她打算赚钱。她没有
know how it would turn out, but she did
她知道结果会如何，但她还是这么做了。
it because it meant so much to her and
因为这对她意义重大
she did it because she saw the impact
她这样做是因为她看到了影响。
she was having.
她正在经历。
And in her 10 years or nine years in
在她10年或9年的时光里
banking, she's never felt like she's had
在银行业，她从未觉得自己拥有过什么。
that impact on individuals. It's been on
对个人产生影响。它一直在
for corporates or for sovereigns. It's
无论是对企业还是对主权国家而言。它是
never been for
从未
specific people or day-to-day people who
特定的人或日常接触的人
need it.
需要它。
And she did it and she didn't know where
她真的这么做了，但她不知道地点在哪里。
it was going to lead her.
这会指引她。
&gt;&gt; Is there an element of
是否存在以下因素
being a first or second generation
作为第一代或第二代
immigrant that ties into this? Because I
与此相关的移民？因为我
hear so often when people come up to me
经常听到人们走过来跟我说这些话
in the in the gym and you know their
在健身房里，你知道他们的
their mother's African like my mother's
他们的母亲和我母亲一样，都是非洲人。
African and and I was born in Africa and
我出生在非洲，我是非洲人。
so my mother's Nigerian and put
我母亲是尼日利亚人，而且
tremendous weight on you know going to
你知道，肩负着巨大的压力
university and becoming a success in the
大学生活以及在学业上取得成功
eyes of the public and then I hear a lot
公众的目光，然后我听到了很多。
from sort of more Asian
有点像亚洲人
first generation immigrants or second
第一代移民或第二代移民
generation immigrants that they feel you
移民一代，他们觉得你
know the doctor lawyer can't remember
知道医生律师记不起来了
what the third one was doctor lawyer
第三个是什么？医生律师
something
某物
&gt;&gt; accountant I don't know
会计师，我不认识
&gt;&gt; maybe finance
或许是金融
&gt;&gt; do you think that plays a role
你认为这会起作用吗？
&gt;&gt; into why you go down a certain path.
探究你为何会走上某条道路。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. In in terms of like if you're at
是的。比如，如果你在……
home and you're you have first
回家，你首先
generation immigrant parents and they
一代移民父母和他们
see success as like one of three jobs,
将成功看作是以下三种工作之一：
it becomes harder to break out. Like
逃脱变得越来越困难。喜欢
breaking out is basically makes you a
突破基本上会让你变成
failure at home.
在家失败了。
&gt;&gt; I think there's two things. I think it's
我认为有两件事。我认为是
definitely that's a big part of it. but
这绝对是其中一个重要因素。但
also seeing what your parents did and
还要看看你父母都做了些什么
how hard they worked to get you onto a
他们为了让你上大学付出了多少努力
path of security, which is a job, and
安全之路，也就是一份工作，
then saying, "Yeah, you worked really
然后说：“是啊，你真的做得很好。”
hard and I'm throwing that away."
很难，但我却放弃了。
There's a lot of guilt that comes with
随之而来的是深深的内疚感
that.
那。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; So, I think it's I think it's both. I
所以，我认为两者都是。我
think it's
我觉得是
&gt;&gt; Did you feel that guilt?
你当时感到内疚吗？
&gt;&gt; I did at the time. Massive guilt.
当时我确实这么做了。深深的愧疚感。
&gt;&gt; Massive guilt. I couldn't tell anyone
深深的愧疚感。我无法告诉任何人
that I was quitting until after I quit.
直到我辞职之后，我才意识到自己原本打算辞职。
The only person who knew was my then
当时唯一知道这件事的人就是我。
boyfriend, now husband.
男朋友，现在是丈夫。
&gt;&gt; Your parents didn't know.
你的父母并不知道。
&gt;&gt; They didn't know till after I quit. I
直到我辞职后他们才知道。我
couldn't tell them.
我没法告诉他们。
&gt;&gt; Why?
为什么？
&gt;&gt; Cuz I knew that if they said something,
因为我知道如果他们说了什么，
I might have just changed my decision.
我可能刚刚改变了主意。
&gt;&gt; And you think they would have said
你觉得他们会说
something?
某物？
&gt;&gt; I don't know. But when I told them, they
我不知道。但当我告诉他们时，他们
supported it because they knew it was
他们支持它，因为他们知道它是
also too late. I think they might have
也太晚了。我认为他们可能已经
just said, "Hey, this is secure." Well,
我只是说：“嘿，这很安全。”出色地，
maybe there's something in that. Maybe
或许这其中有些道理。或许
in those big decisions where, as you
在那些重大决定中，当你
say, you're going to deal with the
比如说，你要处理……
consequences yourself, both the upside
后果由你自己承担，既有好处也有坏处。
and the regret. Maybe consensus and
以及随之而来的遗憾。或许可以达成共识
focus groups aren't needed in such a
在这种情况下，不需要焦点小组。
moment when we should be tuning into the
我们应该关注的时刻
voice inside. Because yeah, external
内心独白。因为，是的，外部的
voices will just complicate those
声音只会让事情变得更复杂。
things. But I also think, you know, I
事物。但我觉得，你知道，我
say this to people a lot when they come
经常对来访的人说这句话
up to me and they say, "I'm in this
这取决于我，他们会说：“我参与其中。”
situation. I'm in finance. I'm working
情况。我在金融行业工作。我在工作
in the city. I've got this dream of
在城市里。我做了一个梦……
being a violin player in Peru."
在秘鲁当小提琴手。
The first question I often ask them is
我经常问他们的第一个问题是：
like, could you go back if you're wrong?
比如，如果你错了，可以回头吗？
Because if you could go back if you're
因为如果你能回到过去，如果你是
wrong, then that's what we call a I
错了，那我们就称之为“我”。
think it's a type one decision in
我认为这属于第一类决定。
business, which is a door that is
商业，也就是一扇门
reversible. And so many people spend one
可逆的。所以很多人会花一小时
year, 3 years, 5 years, 10 years, 20
一年，3年，5年，10年，20年
years of their life stood in front of a
他们生命中的数年都站在……面前
type one decision, a door that they
第一类决定，一扇他们打开的门
could walk back through if they're
如果他们愿意，可以走回去
wrong. And actually, it's just like such
错误的。实际上，就是这样。
a crazy shame not to make those type one
不做那种类型的产品真是太可惜了。
decisions at speed
快速决策
&gt;&gt; if if it's reversible. And it's so crazy
如果这是可逆的。真是太疯狂了
because like 95% of the time when I ask
因为大约95%的情况下，当我问这个问题时，答案都是否定的。
someone that question, they respond.
有人提出这个问题，他们会回答。
They said, "Yeah, I could go back to
他们说：“是的，我可以回去……”
investment banking if I was wrong."
如果我错了，那我就去投资银行了。
Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; I'm like, "Go do the violin thing then.
我当时就想，“那就去拉小提琴吧。”
Go up, fail. It might work out,
去搞砸吧，去失败吧。或许会成功。
whatever, but come back here if you're
随便吧，但如果你是……就回来这里
if you can." So
如果可以的话。” 所以
&gt;&gt; yeah, you won't have that pain of what
是的，你不会再经历那种痛苦了。
if anymore.
如果还有的话。
&gt;&gt; The what if. Yeah. And I I remember
如果……会怎样？是的。我还记得
reading that study from Bon Bronny
阅读邦·布朗尼的那项研究
Bronnyware.
布朗尼餐具。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Palative nurse who interviewed people on
一位接受过临终关怀培训的护士采访了人们
their deathbeds. And it was um I think
他们的临终时刻。嗯，我想是这样的。
the number one regret is not living the
最大的遗憾就是没有好好生活。
life that I think I could have lived.
我觉得我本可以过上那样的生活。
And I've always remembered that. I
我一直都记得这件事。我
thought, okay, so if it's reversible,
我心想，好吧，如果它是可逆的，
then maybe go through that door as fast
然后或许可以尽快穿过那扇门。
as you can. Nisha, thank you so much for
尽你所能。妮莎，非常感谢你
doing what you do. It's really um it's
做你正在做的事。真是……嗯……
really incredibly important. And I think
非常重要。我觉得
the very fact that your channel has been
你的频道已经存在的事实本身就说明了这一点
so resonant and so far reaching speaks
如此引人共鸣，如此影响深远
to an unmet demand in people's
满足人们未被满足的需求
understanding of finance, but also
对金融的理解，以及其他方面的理解
having a voice that they can very much
拥有发言权，他们能够非常有效地
relate to that um simplifies, makes
与此相关，嗯，简化了，使
things complicated things accessible,
事情变得复杂，事情变得简单。
but also just a human being that is um
但他也只是一个普通人，嗯……
relatable in many forms. your intentions
在许多方面都具有关联性。你的意图
of why you're doing what you're doing
你做这件事的原因
are so abundantly clear and I could see
非常清晰，我能看到
that in the emotion. I could see that
那是一种情感。我看得出来
you really really do care about other
你真的很关心他人
people and actually your decision to
人们以及你实际上的决定
take a leap from the world of investment
从投资领域跳出来
banking which was much more secure and
银行服务更加安全可靠。
high status in many people's eyes at
在许多人眼中，他/她拥有很高的地位。
that moment in time was one also
那一刻也是其中之一
inspired by the fact that you want to do
受你想做这件事的启发
good for the world and that is exactly
对世界有益，而这正是如此。
what you're doing. So I highly recommend
你在做什么。所以我强烈推荐
everybody goes and checks out your
大家都去看你
channel. and I'm going to link it below
渠道。我会在下方附上链接。
um if they want to continue this
嗯，如果他们想继续下去的话
conversation because you make very
因为你很会聊天，所以很
actionable, concise, clear videos on all
提供所有相关内容的实用、简洁、清晰的视频
the subjects we've talked about, but
我们讨论过的话题，但是
many more. Um and also to go follow you
还有很多。嗯，还有，请关注你。
on social media, which I'll also link
在社交媒体上，我也会附上链接。
everywhere else. Um but I just want to
其他地方。嗯，但我只是想
thank you for your time and hope
感谢您抽出时间并致以希望
hopefully we can talk again soon when
希望我们能尽快再次交谈
you've uh written a book and the the
你写了一本书，而且
book comes out.
新书出版了。
&gt;&gt; Thank you so much, Stephen. It's been a
非常感谢你，斯蒂芬。一直以来
pleasure.
乐趣。
&gt;&gt; This has always blown my mind a little
这件事一直让我有点难以置信。
bit. 53% of you that listen to this show
少量。 53% 的听众收听了这个节目
regularly haven't yet subscribed to the
经常还没有订阅
show. So, could I ask you for a favor?
展示。那么，我能请你帮个忙吗？
If you like the show and you like what
如果你喜欢这个节目，并且喜欢什么
we do here and you want to support us,
我们在这里确实这样做了，而你们也想支持我们。
the free simple way that you can do just
你可以用这种免费又简单的方法做到这一点
that is by hitting the subscribe button.
也就是点击订阅按钮。
And my commitment to you is if you do
我对你的承诺是，如果你这样做
that, then I'll do everything in my
那样的话，我就会做我的一切。
power, me and my team, to make sure that
我和我的团队拥有权力，以确保
this show is better for you every single
这个节目对你来说更好！
week. We'll listen to your feedback.
星期。我们会认真听取您的反馈意见。
We'll find the guests that you want me
我们会找到你想要的客人。
to speak to and we'll continue to do
我们会与他们沟通，并继续这样做。
what we do. Thank you so much. We
我们做什么。太感谢了。我们
launched these conversation cards and
推出了这些对话卡片，
they sold out. And we launched them
它们都卖光了。我们推出了它们
again and they sold out again. We
他们又一次售罄了。我们
launched them again and they sold out
它们再次上市后便销售一空。
again because people love playing these
再次因为人们喜欢玩这些游戏。
with colleagues at work, with friends at
与同事在工作中，与朋友们在……
home, and also with family. And we've
在家，也和家人在一起。我们已经
also got a big audience that use them as
也拥有大量将其用作
journal prompts. Every single time a
写作提示。每一次
guest comes on the diary of a CEO, they
一位嘉宾出现在CEO的日程安排中，他们
leave a question for the next guest in
请留下一个问题，以便下一位客人提问。
the diary. And I've sat here with some
日记。我一直和一些人坐在这里。
of the most incredible people in the
世界上最了不起的人
world. And they've left all of these
世界。他们留下了所有这些
questions in the diary. And I've ranked
日记中的问题。我已经排名了
them from one to three in terms of the
它们在各方面都从一到三名不等。
depth. One being a starter question. And
深度。第一个问题是引导性的。和
level three, if you look on the back
第三层，如果你看背面的话。
here, this is a level three, becomes a
这里，这是三级，变成了
much deeper question that builds even
一个更深层次的问题，甚至会引发更多问题。
more connection. If you turn the cards
加强联系。如果你翻牌
over and you scan that QR code, you can
扫描该二维码，即可
see who answered the card and watch the
看看谁回复了卡片，然后观看。
video of them answering it in real time.
他们实时回答问题的视频。
So, if you would like to get your hands
所以，如果你想得到它
on some of these conversation cards, go
在某些对话卡片上，去
to the diary.com or look at the link in
访问 diary.com 或查看链接
the description below.
以下是描述。
Heat. Heat. N.
热。热。N.
[Music]
[音乐]